<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Memoires of the transactions in Savoy during this war wherein the Duke of Savoy's foul play with the allies, and his secret correspondence with the French king, are fully detected and demonstrated, by authentick proofs, and undeniable matter of fact : with remarks upon the separate treaty of Savoy with France, and the present posture of affairs with relation to a general peace / made English from the original.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1697</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 214 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 97 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A50582</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M1673</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R2398</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13659757</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13659757</idno>
            <idno type="VID">101085</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A50582)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 101085)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 795:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Memoires of the transactions in Savoy during this war wherein the Duke of Savoy's foul play with the allies, and his secret correspondence with the French king, are fully detected and demonstrated, by authentick proofs, and undeniable matter of fact : with remarks upon the separate treaty of Savoy with France, and the present posture of affairs with relation to a general peace / made English from the original.</title>
                  <author>Savage, John, 1673-1747.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[14], 3-180 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for M. Gylliflower, W. Freeman, M. Watson J. Walthe, and R. Parker,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1697.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Anonymous French work translated by John Savage.  Cf. DNB.</note>
                  <note>Advertisements on preliminary p. [9-14]</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Victor Amadeus --  I, --  King of Sardinia, 1666-1732.</term>
               <term>Louis --  XIV, --  King of France, 1638-1715.</term>
               <term>France. --  Treaties, etc. --  Savoy (Duchy), 1696 Aug. 29.</term>
               <term>France --  Foreign relations --  Savoy (Duchy)</term>
               <term>Savoy (France and Italy) --  Foreign relations --  France.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:101085:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:101085:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>MEMOIRES</hi> OF THE Tranſactions IN SAVOY During This WAR. WHEREIN The Duke of <hi>SAVOY</hi>'s Foul Play with the <hi>ALLIES,</hi> and His Secret Correſpondence with the <hi>French</hi> King, are fully detected and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrated, by Authentick Proofs, and Undeniable Matter of Fact. WITH Remarks upon the Separate Treaty of <hi>Savoy</hi> with <hi>France,</hi> and the Preſent Poſture of Affairs with Relation to a General Peace.</p>
            <lg>
               <l>Fas mihi <hi>Sabbaudi</hi> ſcelerata reſolvere jura;</l>
               <l>Fas odiſſe virum atque omnia ferre ſub auras.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>Made <hi>Engliſh</hi> from the Original.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>M. Gilliflower, W. Freeman, M. Wotton, J. Waltho,</hi> and <hi>R. Parker.</hi> 1697.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:101085:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:101085:2"/>
            <head>TO THE Right Honourable Charles <hi>Lord</hi> Spencer.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>AMbition,</hi> the darling Infirmity of all Mankind; but more eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially of Writers, has natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally put me upon this bold Attempt of addreſſing this little <hi>Piece</hi> to Your Lordſhip, to the end that whatever the Performance is, my Aim at leaſt might be Commendable.
<pb facs="tcp:101085:3"/>This Motive has brought upon Your Lordſhip a Trouble which will undoubtedly be follow'd by many others; yet ſtill it is my peculiar Happineſs, of which I am not a little proud, to be the Firſt that pay an early Tribute to Bloom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Vertue. Nevertheleſs, to check my Vanity, it is alſo my Misfortune, that not ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving wherewithal of my own Growth, I am forc'd to tender the Product of a Foreign Country.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tranſlators</hi> are, as it were, the Nurſes of anothers Iſſue, and, like Them, generally contract from their Care a ſort of Habitual Tenderneſs, next
<pb facs="tcp:101085:3"/>to Natural: Yet even this almoſt Invincible Prejudice, can't ſo far prevail upon me, as to make me preſume to give any Character of our <hi>Author</hi> to Your Lordſhip, who are ſo much Superiour to me in Things of this High Importance. Thoſe that move in my low Sphere, are too remote to judge of Objects elevated ſo high above us: For Matters of the State have as great a <hi>Paralax</hi> to our View, as thoſe of the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>My Lord,</hi> You being Heir Apparent, as well to the Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and Vertues, as Eſtate and Honour of the Ableſt
<pb facs="tcp:101085:4"/>Stateſman in <hi>Europe,</hi> are better ſituated for ſuch Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coveries; and herein <hi>Nature</hi> has been kinder to Your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, than <hi>Fortune,</hi> tho' both have not been a little Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent. <hi>Dignities</hi> and <hi>Wealth</hi> are ſeldom Companions to <hi>good Senſe:</hi> But we find them all happily reconcil'd in Your Lordſhip, tho' at the ſame time we cannot but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the Preeminence to Your <hi>Judgment.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This, <hi>My Lord,</hi> entitles You to judge of this <hi>Author</hi>'s <hi>Reflections;</hi> and the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages You have of a near<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Inſpection into the ſecret Springs and Movements of
<pb facs="tcp:101085:4"/>the Affairs he treats of, ena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Your Lordſhip either to confirm his Truth, or convict him of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nſincerity.</p>
            <p>This was another Reaſon, <hi>My Lord,</hi> why I referr'd him to receive his Doom from Your Lordſhip, either to ſtand or fall as You approve or diſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low. From Your Definitive Sentence there can lie no Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal, ſince <hi>Nature, Art,</hi> and <hi>Fortune</hi> have all conſpir'd to qualifie You with <hi>Great Parts, Learning,</hi> and <hi>Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity,</hi> which render Your Authority unqueſtionable.</p>
            <p>My own Performance I on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſubmit to Your Lordſhips Candour and Goodneſs, the
<pb facs="tcp:101085:5"/>reſt of Your Noble Qualifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions being Enemies to ſuch weak Endeavours: Yet I hope Your Lordſhips Pardon for my Preſumption, as well as Failings, ſince they only flow from an irreſiſtible Ambition to publiſh to the World how much I am,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute> 
               <signed> Your Lordſhips moſt Humble, Obedient, and Devoted Servant, <hi>JOHN SAVAGE.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:101085:5"/>
            <head>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>OOKS lately Printed for <hi>M. Gillyflower</hi> in <hi>Weſtminſter-Hall, W. Freeman, M. Wotton</hi> in <hi>Fleetſtreet, J. Waltho</hi> in the <hi>Temple,</hi> and <hi>R. Parker</hi> under the <hi>Piazza</hi> of the <hi>Royal Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change</hi> in <hi>Cornhill.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THE <hi>Compleat Horſeman:</hi> Diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering the ſureſt <hi>Marks</hi> of the <hi>Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, Goodneſs,</hi> and <hi>Vices</hi> of <hi>Horſes,</hi> and deſcribing the <hi>Signs</hi> and <hi>Cauſes</hi> of their <hi>Diſeaſes,</hi> and the true <hi>Method</hi> both of their <hi>Preſervation</hi> and <hi>Cure:</hi> With <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flections</hi> upon the Irregular and Prepoſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Uſe of <hi>Bleeding</hi> and <hi>Purging.</hi> To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with the Art of <hi>Shooing,</hi> and a Deſcription of ſeveral Kinds of <hi>Shoes,</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dapted to the various Defects of <hi>Bad Feet,</hi> and for the Preſervation of thoſe that are <hi>Good;</hi> and the Beſt Method of Breeding <hi>Colts;</hi> with Directions to be obſerv'd in <hi>Backing</hi> 'em, and <hi>Making their Mouths, &amp;c.</hi> By the <hi>Sieur de Solleyfell,</hi> one of the <hi>Heads</hi> of the <hi>Royal Academy</hi> at <hi>Paris.</hi> The Eighth Edition, review'd and methodically augmented. Done into <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and adorn'd with <hi>Figures. Folio.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:101085:6"/>
            <p>The <hi>Compleat Surgeon:</hi> or, The whole Art of <hi>Surgery</hi> explain'd, in a moſt fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar Method. Containing an exact Account of its Principles and ſeveral Parts, <hi>viz.</hi> Of the <hi>Bones, Muſcles, Tumours, Ulcers,</hi> and <hi>Wounds</hi> ſimple and complicated, or thoſe by <hi>Gun-ſhot;</hi> as alſo of <hi>Venereal Diſeaſes,</hi> the <hi>Scurvy, Fractures, Luxa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi> and all ſorts of <hi>Chirurgical Ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations;</hi> together with their proper <hi>Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dages</hi> and <hi>Dreſſings.</hi> To which is added, A <hi>Chirurgical Diſpenſatory;</hi> ſhewing the Manner how to prepare all ſuch <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines</hi> as are moſt neceſſary for a <hi>Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geon,</hi> and particularly the <hi>Mercurial Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacaea.</hi> Written in <hi>French</hi> by <hi>M. le Clerc,</hi> Phyſician in Ordinary, and Privy-Counſellor to the <hi>French</hi> King; and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully tranſlated into <hi>Engliſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Art of <hi>Preſerving</hi> and <hi>Reſtoring Health.</hi> Explaining the <hi>Nature</hi> and <hi>Cauſes</hi> of the <hi>Diſtempers</hi> that afflict Mankind. Alſo ſhewing, That every Man is, or may be, his own beſt <hi>Phyſician.</hi> To which is added, A Treatiſe of the moſt Simple and Effectual <hi>Remedies</hi> for the Diſeaſes of Men and Women. Written in <hi>French</hi> by <hi>M. Flam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd</hi> M. D. and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully tranſlated into <hi>Engliſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:101085:6"/>
            <p>The <hi>Roman Hiſtory,</hi> from the Build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the <hi>City,</hi> to the perfect Settlement of the <hi>Empire</hi> by <hi>Auguſtus Caeſar.</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining the Space of 727 Years. Deſign'd as well for the underſtanding of the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> Authors, as the <hi>Roman</hi> Affairs. The Second Edition, carefully revis'd, and much improv'd. By <hi>Laurence Echard</hi> A. M. of <hi>Chriſt's-College</hi> in <hi>Cambridge.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A <hi>New Voyage</hi> to the <hi>Levant:</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining an Account of the moſt Remarka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Curioſities in <hi>Germany, France, Italy, Malta,</hi> and <hi>Turkey;</hi> With Hiſtorical <hi>Obſervations</hi> relating to the <hi>Preſent</hi> and <hi>Ancient</hi> State of thoſe Countries. By the <hi>Sieur du Mont.</hi> Done into <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and adorn'd with <hi>Figures.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now in the Preſs, and will be ſpeedily Publiſh'd.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>OF Wiſdom:</hi> Three Books. Written Originally in <hi>French</hi> by the <hi>Sieur de Charron;</hi> With an Account of the <hi>Author.</hi> Made <hi>Engliſh</hi> by Mr. <hi>Stan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hope,</hi> late Fellow of <hi>King's-College</hi> in <hi>Cambridge,</hi> from the beſt Edition, cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected and enlarged by the Author, a little before his Death.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:101085:7"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:101085:7"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:101085:8"/>
            <p>A <hi>New Journey</hi> thro a Vaſt Countrey lately diſcover'd, extending above Four thouſand Miles, between <hi>New France</hi> and <hi>New Mexico</hi> in <hi>America:</hi> With a Deſcription of the Great <hi>Lakes, Cataracts, Rivers, Plants, Animals,</hi> with the <hi>Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, Cuſtoms,</hi> and <hi>Languages</hi> of the ſeveral Native <hi>Indians,</hi> and the Adva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages of Commerce with thoſe different Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, which are thought to reach to the <hi>South Seas.</hi> The whole illuſtrated with a <hi>Map</hi> of the Countrey and <hi>Figures,</hi> and Dedicated to His Majeſty King <hi>William.</hi> By <hi>M. Hennapin,</hi> now Reſident in <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:101085:8"/>
            <head>MEMOIRES OF THE TRANSACTIONS IN SAVOY.</head>
            <p>WHen a Man ſeriouſly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiders upon what Motives <hi>Victor Amedeus</hi> II. Duke of <hi>Savoy</hi> embrac'd the Intereſt of the moſt Serene Allies, and entred into a Confederacy with ſo many Auguſt Princes, whoſe only Aim is the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe of <hi>Chriſtendom,</hi> and Security of <hi>Europe;</hi> he will be under the greateſt Surpriſe imaginable, to hear that His Royal Highneſs, without any regard to an Alliance ſolemnly ſworn before the Abbot <hi>Grimani</hi> the Emperor's Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:101085:9"/>ſhould all of a ſudden take off the Mask, and forſake a Party which had ſacrific'd but too much for his Support. This Conduct of his can have no other Cauſe than the pernici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Counſels of his Cabinet-Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, who having been under-hand corrupted by the Artifices and vaſt Sums of Money of the <hi>French</hi> Court, have undoubtedly occaſion'd all theſe Proceedings, ſo very oppoſite to his true Intereſt. Thoſe that are beſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with his Royal Highneſs, differ ſomething in his Character: They all agree, he is a Man of Senſe and Wit, Active, Generous, and Brave: But ſome add, he is exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly Covetous; which is plain enough by his ſcraping up above Twenty Millions during this War.</p>
            <p>But who are thoſe that have ſo well advis'd his Highneſs? Is not the Count of <hi>Bens,</hi> Preſident of the Council of War, one of 'em? And that, as he is a great Time-ſerver, full of Deſign and Diſſimulation; One whoſe more peculiar Character is to be a down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right Courtier, ſince he will freely
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:101085:9"/>offer his Service, and ſhew great Kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to his Viſitors, but ſeldom or never obliges any.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="*" place="margin">After this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner he behav'd him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf towards the <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh</hi> Miniſters, when they viſited him; whilſt at the ſame time he made a more hearty Welcome to the Emiſſaries of <hi>France.</hi>
               </note>He will wait up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on People out of his very Doors with the greateſt Civility imaginable, which might very well gain him the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute of a moſt offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious and obliging Perſon, did not his Hypocriſie glare thro' his Courteſie, and detect the Malignity of his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions.</p>
            <p>After this refin'd Courtier, comes the Prince of <hi>Carignan,</hi> his Royal Highneſs's Uncle, who troubles him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf but little with Affairs of State, chooſing rather to live like a <hi>Stoick</hi> than <hi>Politician;</hi> his Genius confining him wholly to a ſupine Neglect of all Buſineſs and Publick Affairs.</p>
            <p>Next comes the Chevalier <hi>Tane,</hi> the Duke's Favourite, who underſtands the Art of Diſſimulation and Flattery ſo perfectly well, that he eaſily diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhes
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:101085:10"/>himſelf to be a <hi>Jeſuite</hi> of ſome ſtanding. This Perſon has a great Aſcendant over his Royal Highneſs, inſomuch that whatever he ſays or does cannot fail to meet with Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plauſe. In a word, he is the <hi>Apollo</hi> of <hi>Turin,</hi> and his Deciſions are liſtned to as Oracles.</p>
            <p>After him is the Marqueſs of <hi>St. Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas,</hi> Chief Miniſter for Foreign Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs. This Perſon is employ'd in all Negotiations abroad, and that by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of his Experience formerly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quir'd by defending his Matter againſt the Princes of <hi>Italy</hi> his Neighbours. He is very proper to improve his Duke's Intereſts, and alſo Sincere and Honeſt, as far as the <hi>Italian</hi> Politicks will give him leave; except that he often promiſes, but ſeldom keeps his Word.</p>
            <p>To all theſe choice Miniſters of his Royal Highneſs's Cabinet, we muſt yet add Two more, exceedingly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siderable, and who are as it were the Soul that informs the whole Body. Theſe are, her Royal Highneſs the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:101085:10"/>Dutcheſs, and the Marqueſs of <hi>Bag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſque,</hi> General of the Duke's Forces. Every body knows the Dutcheſs to be Daughter to the Duke of <hi>Orleans,</hi> Brother of the <hi>French</hi> King; and therefore her Inclinations muſt rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonably be ſuppos'd to correſpond with her Birth. This is to ſpeak all in a word; ſo that I have reckon'd up more than ſufficient to form a good Council. Women have natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally the Gift of Pleaſing and Perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding; they are generally ſubtle and diſſembling: Wherefore in this Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly we may aſcribe to her Royal Highneſs all the Qualities of <hi>Meduſa</hi>'s Head, which were to render motion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, or metamorphoſe into Monſters, ſuch as oppos'd the Deliberations in favour of <hi>France.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To this Stateſwoman we muſt moreover aſſociate the Dutcheſs Dow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ager, his Royal Highneſs's Mother, who has never yet approv'd her ſelf ſo truly <hi>French</hi> as upon this Occaſion. However, perhaps rich Preſents and dazling <hi>Louidors</hi> have blinded her, and caus'd her to alter her Opinion with
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:101085:11"/>her Condition. But be the Occaſion what it will, 'tis certain, ſhe had no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſmall ſhare in inclining the Balance, tho' whether to her own Advantage or not, may come hereafter to be queſtion'd. <hi>France</hi> could never have fail'd to ſucceed, ſince it ſo prudently made uſe of Women's Wit, which generally bears the Bell againſt all Oppoſers.</p>
            <p>Two ſuch Female Preſidents were not enough for this Council; a third of the other Sex muſt be added to 'em, a Man who was bold, and of Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity ſufficient to put their Reſolves in execution. For this Work none was thought ſo proper as the Marqueſs of <hi>Bagnaſque,</hi> to whoſe Honour it may be ſaid that he acquitted himſelf like a brave Captain; and conſequently de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved both Praiſes and Applauſes of all the Court. Nevertheleſs none ſtuck ſo cloſe to him as the the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants and <hi>Engliſh</hi> Troops, tho' at the ſame time he expoſed 'em by his ſecret Intelligences with Mareſchal <hi>Catinat,</hi> to a more bloody and cruel Maſſacre than that of St. <hi>Bartholomew.</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:101085:11"/>Time that clears all things will diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover the reſt, and I ſhall reſerve a farther Illuſtration of it to the Sequel of this Work.</p>
            <p>For the preſent, I will only add, that this Marqueſs is very conſiderable at the Court of <hi>Turin,</hi> on account of his great Employments which have acquir'd him an Authority that makes him look'd upon as the ſole <hi>Arbiter</hi> both of the Good and Ill there practiſed. He is his Royal High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes chief Favourite, General of his Armies, a Knight, Great Maſter of the Ordnance, and heretofore Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of <hi>Montmellian,</hi> now of <hi>Coni.</hi> Moreover, he has had the Fortune to have all his Orders well executed by his Lieutenant-Generals the Marqueſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of <hi>Caſaly Pianeſe, Tane</hi> and <hi>Parella,</hi> all who have been faithful Abettors in favour of the <hi>French</hi> Court, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd Penſions and Bribes according<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. Thus his Royal Highneſs muſt needs have been well ſerv'd by Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters that have made it their chief Aim to advance the Intereſt and Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of <hi>France.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:101085:12"/>
            <p>After having thus given a ſmall Sketch of his Royal Highneſs's chief Favourites, it would not be amiſs to ſay ſomething of his ſeveral Miniſters that have been ſent to the moſt Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rene Allies throughout the whole Courſe of this War; which to perform accurately, I ſhall content my ſelf on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with affirming, that the Preſident <hi>de la Tour,</hi> Envoy to his <hi>Britannick</hi> Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, as alſo to the <hi>States General;</hi> and likewiſe the Count of <hi>Turin,</hi> Envoy to his Electoral Highneſs of <hi>Bavaria,</hi> are both Jeſuits, as well as the other Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters employ'd to the reſt of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federates. But here we muſt except Monſieur <hi>Perier</hi> Reſident at the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour's Court, who is indeed the Son of a Banker. He has purchas'd a great many fair Poſſeſſions in <hi>Tranſylvania,</hi> and <hi>France</hi> has ſupply'd him with 400000 <hi>Piſtoles</hi> for that purpoſe: But you may very well imagine ſhe did not do it for nothing; he no doubt was ſerviceable to her in his turn. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this we muſt not wonder if this Prince's Affairs have been ſo well ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nag'd. He could not have pitch'd
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:101085:12"/>upon fitter Perſons for his Service, nor more proper to bring his Deſigns a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout, which nevertheleſs he has all along endeavour'd to conceal from his firſt pretended Rupture with <hi>France.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But before we come to Particulars of his Highneſs's Conduce in this War towards the moſt Serene Allies, let us look into the Cauſes of his Grievances, which oblig'd him to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare againſt a Crown he was ty'd to by a kind of <hi>Gordian</hi> Knot; and which <hi>France,</hi> upon Concluſion of the Peace, repreſented by Fire-works as an Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blem, to denote to the Allies, that their Conjunction was eaſie to be diſſolv'd when the Duke of <hi>Savoy</hi> was once withdrawn.</p>
            <p>We have already made known the Conditions or rather Inclinations of this Duke's Favourites; and we are wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to diſcharge his Highneſs and lay the Blame wholly upon thoſe Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters: Therefore let us dive into his moſt inmoſt Receſſes, and have ſo much Charity for him as to believe his Deſigns were always juſt, and that
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:101085:13"/>he had all the reaſon in the World to break with <hi>France,</hi> to deliver himſelf from a Slavery he had ſo long under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gone.</p>
            <p>The Occaſion of his Royal High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs's Engaging againſt this Crown muſt then be ſuppoſed to be too free himſelf from a Yoke that was into<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerable. His Neighbours the <hi>French</hi> reduc'd him to that Condition that he ſcarce durſt rule in his own Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace, but depended ſo abſolutely on that Monarch, that he was even like a Vaſſal to his Lord; inſomuch that upon his leaſt Advances, <hi>France</hi> was preſently upon the Catch to pry into his Conduct, tho' he never meant 'em the leaſt harm. Fatal Law! which always impoſes the greateſt Reſpect and Submiſſion upon the Weak. Nay, this Prince's ſtrict Alliance with that Kingdom, by his Marriage with Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damoiſelle <hi>d Orleans,</hi> did but ſubject him the more to a Power which exacts O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience from all.</p>
            <p>This Affinity, which he no doubt foreſaw to be fatal to him, his Court be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:101085:13"/>always crowded with <hi>French,</hi> which were as ſo many Spies ſet over him to inform their Maſter of whatever paſs'd in his Councils, influenc'd him at laſt with the ſevereſt Diſcontent, and fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led him full of ſecret Alarms and Fears that he might one Day be robb'd of his Dukedom in like manner as the Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> had been. We ſhould never have done, if we intended to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count the ſeveral Inſults made him by the <hi>French</hi> King, even from his Minority to this Rupture, whereby we may perceive what deſperate Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zards Princes run that match into the Royal Family of <hi>France.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If his Royal Highneſs had thought fit to have liſten'd to the Advice of the Emperour and ſome Princes of <hi>Italy,</hi> his Neighbours and faithful Friends, who counſel'd him to marry one of the Princeſſes of the Houſe of <hi>Newbourg,</hi> no doubt he had play'd his Game better, and follow'd, his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt ſurer: When, on the contrary, he now lies under the greateſt Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint, to be turn'd and manag'd at the Pleaſure of <hi>France;</hi> and to do
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:101085:14"/>whatever that Imperious Crown thinks fit to command.</p>
            <p>The Alliances of the Princes of the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria</hi> with <hi>France</hi> have coſt 'em ſo dear, that their greateſt Poſſeſſions are now in danger of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volving to that Crown; and which has been the Occaſion of the firſt Sparks that have, kindl'd this War in <hi>Europe.</hi> If therefore his Royal Highneſs had pleas'd to benefit him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf by theſe Examples, as many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Princes have done, he would never have conſented to this Marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age; and thereupon might the better have ſecur'd his Quiet, aſcertain'd the Succeſſion of his Dominions to his rightful Heirs; might have maintain'd a Neutrality, and procur'd a ſtrict Alliance with his Imperial Majeſty, to whom he has had much greater Obligations than to the <hi>French</hi> King.</p>
            <p>Moreover, what ſufficient Reaſons had not his Royal Highneſs to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſt the Councils of <hi>France,</hi> after their Deſigns to out him of his Throne, by filling his Head with Chimerical
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:101085:14"/>Thoughts of the Crown of <hi>Portugal?</hi> The <hi>French</hi> King had manag'd this Intrigue ſo ſecretly, and his Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters carried it on with ſuch Dexteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, that they had perſuaded the King of <hi>Portugal</hi> to beſtow his Daughter in Marriage on this young Prince: And his Royal Highneſs was ſo far aſſur'd of the Sincerity of their In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions, that he had freely conſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to it, they having firſt inſinuated to him, that the K. of <hi>Portugal</hi> being incapable of having more Children, his Crown by ſuch means muſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallibly deſcend to him. Hereupon it was advis'd neceſſary for this Duke to go to that Kingdom, abandon his own Dominions, and reſide ſo far diſtant in Expectation of <hi>Don Pedro</hi>'s Death, that he might be in a more im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate Readineſs to aſcend his Throne. Whilſt this politick Crown fed the Court of <hi>Turin</hi> with theſe vain Hopes, it was intended the <hi>French</hi> King ſhould ſeize upon his Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of <hi>Savoy,</hi> and unite
'em to his own.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:101085:15"/>
            <p>This Negotiation was ſo far ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanc'd, that his Royal Highneſſe's Equipage was ſet forth, and got as far as <hi>Grenoble,</hi> when the Dutcheſs <hi>Dowager</hi> his Mother, influenc'd by the chief Lords of the Court, who all perceiv'd clearly the Deſigns of <hi>France,</hi> to deprive this Prince of his Dukedom, did all ſhe could to prevent ſo fatal a Miſcarriage. Nevertheleſs all her En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours would have ſignified nothing, had not his Subjects with Tears in their Eyes, run in Crowds about his Palace, earneſtly imploring their law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Sovereign not to leave 'em. His Royal Highneſs at length gave way to their importunate Entreaties, and ſuffer'd himſelf to be won by their juſt Prayers. Whereupon this Grand Negotiation, which had almoſt drain'd the Coffers of <hi>France,</hi> fell to the Ground on a ſudden, and was never reſum'd after.</p>
            <p>His moſt Chriſtian Majeſty having been thus baffl'd in his Deſigns upon <hi>Savoy,</hi> diſſembl'd his Reſentments for ſome time; till at length he ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted the Court of <hi>Turin</hi> by one
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:101085:15"/>of his Miniſters, that he was extreme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſorry, that a Propoſal to advance his Royal Highneſs to the Throne of <hi>Portugal</hi> ſhould be ſo vigorouſly oppos'd. But ſince the Dutcheſs his Mother, and prepoſterous Love of his Subjects, had prevail'd againſt his En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours, he was reſolv'd for his part to thank <hi>Don Pedro,</hi> by his Ambaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſador, for his kind Compliance with his Requeſt, and leave the Duke to do as he thought fit: And moreover, that if he had but in the leaſt ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin'd that his Negotiation would not have been accepted, he would never have troubl'd his Head about it. It has always been the Cuſtom of <hi>France</hi> to enlarge its Dominions more by Policy than Force, and which has been partly owing to Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, and partly to the Addreſs of its Miniſters. This has been a Secret un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known to other Courts of <hi>Europe,</hi> or, perhaps rather abhorr'd by 'em.</p>
            <p>But whatever it be, the <hi>French</hi> King finding it impoſſible to prevail ſo far againſt his Highneſs, by reaſon of the Situation of his Country, as to get
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:101085:16"/>any Entrance into <hi>Italy,</hi> to the end that he might ſtrike in with the firſt Diſturbances amongſt thoſe Princes, or, at leaſt keep 'em in awe, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe Jealouſie into 'em, as he has for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly done to the other Princes of <hi>Europe</hi> his Neighbours; thought beſt, after this Baffle, to engage the young Duke by another Artifice; and that was to propoſe to him one of his own Daughters in Marriage. His moſt Chriſtian Majeſty's Intereſt was yet ſo good at the Court of <hi>Turin,</hi> that the Dutcheſs <hi>Dowager</hi> and his Royal Highneſs's Council preferr'd this Prof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer of Madamoiſelle <hi>d'Orleans</hi> to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of the Emperour and ſome Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of <hi>Italy.</hi> The Fear of enraging ſo powerful a Monarch as that of <hi>France,</hi> and who might prove ſo dangerous a Neighbour, who had moreover formerly, at the Death of his Royal Highneſs's Father <hi>Charles Emanuel</hi> the ſecond, conſented to be his Guar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dian, ſoon enclin'd the Council of <hi>Turin</hi> to accept Madamoiſelle <hi>d'Orleans</hi> before either the Princeſs of <hi>Newburgh</hi> or <hi>Tuſcany.</hi> This was a Marriage therefore where Policy and Fear had a
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:101085:16"/>greater ſhare than Inclination, and conſequently his Royal Highneſs could not expect but what he has ſince ſo often experienc'd to his coſt. Never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs what has already happen'd, is nothing in reſpect of what in all Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bability may hereafter befal him. It may be, his Deſtiny has reſerv'd a Scourge that ſhall prove fatal both to him, his Succeſſours, and the general Repoſe of <hi>Italy</hi> beſides. Theſe are the Preſages of ſuch as are well vers'd in the Politicks of theſe times, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any farther penetrating into Futu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, for my own part, I dare affirm, that one of theſe things muſt inevita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly happen, either that <hi>France</hi> bound its Ambition on this ſide of <hi>Italy,</hi> or that ſhe become one Day Miſtriſs of all <hi>Savoy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>French</hi> King's Pretenſions to this Dutchy, and the preſent Poſture of Affairs encline him naturally to that end, and the only ſhift his Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Highneſs ſeems to have had left, was to have perſiſted in that juſt War, in Conjunction with the moſt Serene Allies. The potent Princes which
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:101085:17"/>compoſe this League, have not been wanting to repreſent often to him by their Miniſters his ſlippery Proceedings whilſt he gave ear to the flattering Promiſes of the common Enemy. His Imperial and Catholick Majeſty's Envoys were even tir'd with proffering their important Reaſons which were ſo capable to undeceive him; but his Royal Highneſs rather enclin'd to be ſeduc'd by the Emiſſaries of <hi>France,</hi> than preſerv'd by the wholſome Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of the Allies; the Difference between which being, that the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil and Promiſes of the Confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates were ſolid and real, when thoſe of <hi>France</hi> were full of nothing but Venom, Deceit and <hi>Chimera's.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But to ſearch deeper into the Court of <hi>Turin,</hi> which is, without diſpute, one of the moſt ſubtle and politick in in <hi>Europe;</hi> it is aſolutely neceſſary to trace back their firſt Differences with the <hi>French</hi> King: After which we in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to follow his Royal Highneſs Step by Step in his Conduct during this War, as well in regard to the <hi>French</hi> King as to the moſt Serene Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies.</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:101085:17"/>
            <p>At the beginning of the Year 1690, the <hi>French</hi> King having reſolv'd to carry the War into <hi>Italy,</hi> the Duke of <hi>Fuenſalida</hi> Governour of <hi>Milan,</hi> with all the diligence imaginable, began to raiſe Troops, fill up Magazines, and repair his Fortifications, to the end that he might be in a Condition to oppoſe the Progreſſes of the <hi>French,</hi> who were then marching towards <hi>Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</hi> But at the ſame time, what moſt perplex'd this Governour, was the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct of the Court of <hi>Turin;</hi> which was a Riddle ſo obſcure, that even the moſt refin'd Politicians were not able to ſolve it. This gave him more Diſturbance than all the Preparations of <hi>France.</hi> For on one hand he ſuſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted the D. of <hi>Savoy</hi> to have under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand made a tripple Alliance with the <hi>French</hi> King and D. of <hi>Modena</hi> to joyn their Forces together, and fall upon the <hi>Milaneze;</hi> and on the other, he obſerv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed this Prince ſo very wavering, that he knew not what to think of him: For at the ſame time that he promis'd the <hi>French</hi> King to ſtand Neuter, he enga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged his Word to the Emperour and
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:101085:18"/>King of <hi>Spain,</hi> that he would declare on their ſide.</p>
            <p>The different Diſpoſitions of his Royal Highneſs at this Juncture, and his ſtudi'd Conduct of Affairs, might very well augment the Jealouſies and Suſpicions of the <hi>French</hi> King, who began to fear that this Prince might at length play him an <hi>Italian</hi> Trick. The <hi>French</hi> therefore, who are gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally very wary, made it their chief Buſineſs to obſerve his Actions cloſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; and having diſcover'd ſomething that ſeem'd to bode 'em no good, his Moſt Chriſtian Majeſty immediately ſent him word, That he was not at all ſatisfi'd with his Neutrality, but further requir'd the Citadels of <hi>Verceil</hi> and <hi>Turin</hi> for Security of his Promiſe.</p>
            <p>This haughty Meſſage from the <hi>French</hi> King did not at all diſcompoſe the Duke; he was reſolv'd upon an even Temper, the better to carry on his Deſigns: Therefore he contented himſelf for the preſent with only de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiring the <hi>French</hi> King to allow him ſome Time for an Anſwer. This pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifi'd
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:101085:18"/>the angry Monarch for a while, hoping thereby to obtain from him an exact Neutrality, which was all that he deſir'd, to the end that the <hi>French</hi> might the more eaſily enter <hi>Italy,</hi> and facilitate the Conqueſt of <hi>Milan.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>During this, the Emiſſaries of <hi>France</hi> at his Royal Highneſs's Court diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver'd another Proceeding, which ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamly augmented their Jealouſies; and that was, That the Duke was about to forſake their Intereſt, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage in that of the Emperour. All the World knows his Royal Highneſs pretends a Right to the Kingdom of <hi>Cyprus,</hi> ſince <hi>Lewis</hi> the Third, Duke or <hi>Savoy,</hi> married <hi>Charlotte</hi> Widow of <hi>John</hi> King of <hi>Portugal,</hi> Daughter of <hi>John,</hi> Son of <hi>James Paleologus</hi> Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour of the Eaſt, who gave for Porti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to his ſaid Daughter <hi>Charlotte</hi> the Kingdom of <hi>Cyprus,</hi> in ſuch manner, that this <hi>Lewis</hi> Duke of <hi>Savoy</hi> was Crown'd King of <hi>Cyprus</hi> in preſence of <hi>John de Luſignan</hi> King of <hi>Cyprus,</hi> his Father-in-Law. From thence the Dukes of <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voy</hi> have the Title of <hi>Royal Highneſs,</hi> and bear an Arch'd Crown, which
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:101085:19"/>the Kings of <hi>France,</hi> or other Princes of <hi>Europe,</hi> have never diſputed, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways giving 'em proportionable Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect; the Emperour only excepted, who wou'd never yet allow them that Regal Character.</p>
            <p>His Royal Highneſs conſidering there was now a favourable Opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity for him, ſince the Emperour thought fit to engage him by his Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters to break with <hi>France,</hi> made uſe of the Occaſion to offer a Million of <hi>Florins</hi> to his Imperial Majeſty, provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded he would acknowledge him King of <hi>Cyprus,</hi> and allow him the ſame Honours which the King of <hi>France</hi> and other Princes had always done. His Royal Highneſs further propos'd to his Imperial Majeſty, That he would buy the <hi>Fiefs</hi> which he had got in <hi>Savoy</hi> and the Republick of <hi>Genoa,</hi> which properly belong'd to the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour; for both which he proffer'd vaſt Sums of Money, not doubting in the leaſt but ſuch Propoſals wou'd be hearken'd to, at a time eſpecially when the Emperour had ſo great Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion for Money to ſupport his Wars
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:101085:19"/>againſt two Puiſſant Enemies. Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſs, his Imperial Majeſty at firſt refus'd all; but his Royal Highneſs not being a whit diſcourag'd, was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolv'd ſtill to manage <hi>France,</hi> and at the ſame time to repeat his Requeſts to the Emperour, till he had obtain'd what he ſo much deſir'd.</p>
            <p>This his Negotiation was at length concluded in his favour, and the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour was willing to yield to the Duke's Demands, provided the Million of <hi>Florins</hi> were paid into the Bank of <hi>Venice.</hi> This Tranſaction extreamly ſurpriz'd the <hi>French</hi> Court, inſomuch that they conceiv'd a more than ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Jealouſie that his Royal Highneſs was entred into a ſtrict Alliance with the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria</hi> their Enemy. This they thought would ſoon appear by a Rupture on the Duke's Side, which would abſolutely break their Meaſures, and exceedingly embroil their Deſigns on <hi>Italy;</hi> they having propos'd an Amity with his Royal Highneſs, and a Paſſage thro' his Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions, to be the beſt Means of dealing with the <hi>Milaneze,</hi> who they
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:101085:20"/>knew would never be ſtrong enough to reſiſt 'em, unleſs aſſiſted by the <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voyard.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Duke of <hi>Savoy,</hi> who is a great Maſter in the Art of Hypocriſie, made uſe of all his Cunning, after having plaid his own Game, to ſweeten the <hi>French</hi> King; aſſuring him by his Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter, That he never yet thought of forſaking his moſt Chriſtian Majeſty's Intereſt, nor attempting any thing which might in the leaſt infringe the inviolable Union betwixt 'em. But nevertheleſs, theſe ſubtle Proteſtations of his were not capable to diſſipate the Jealouſies of that Monarch. He had already ſo well obſerv'd the Conduct of the Court of <hi>Turin,</hi> that he began to treat them as Diſſemblers, and their Duke as a Cheat, who on the one ſide had plaid on his Moſt Chriſtian Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty, and on the other, on the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour. <hi>Mitchiavel</hi> has ſo well taught his Country-men, that we may affirm, the <hi>Italian</hi> Princes are thoſe that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand him beſt, and know how to make the beſt uſe of him.</p>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:101085:20"/>
            <p>It would be proper here to give an Account, before we proceed any fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, of an Intrigue concerted ſome time ſince between the Emperour and his Royal Highneſs, and diſcover'd by the <hi>French</hi> meerly by force of Money, which made 'em ever after ſo very jealous of this Prince's Conduct, that upon his leaſt Advances, his moſt Chriſtian Majeſty was immediately upon his Guard. This is the Relation, which muſt be ſuppos'd to be the more Authentick, as we had it from the beſt Original. In the Year 1687, a little after the famous League of <hi>Auſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burg,</hi> the Count <hi>B</hi>— was ſent by his Imperial Majeſty to the Court of <hi>Turin,</hi> to propoſe to his Royal High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs a new Negotiation. His Moſt Chriſtian Majeſty being ſoon ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with it by his Emiſſaries, immediately writ to his Embaſſadour reſident at that Court about it. Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuant to which, his Embaſſadour en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour'd all he could to be preſent at the Audience of this Miniſter, and moreover acquainted the Court of <hi>Turin,</hi> that he abſolutely inſiſted there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon.
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:101085:21"/>His Royal Highneſs believing he could never have a ſecret Interview with this Miniſter, by reaſon of the conſtant Attendance of the <hi>French</hi> Embaſſadour, reſolv'd to comply with the latter, but withal determin'd, by a ſecret Intelligence with the Envoy, to convert all the Embaſſy into Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies and Compliments.</p>
            <p>When this was done, the <hi>Count</hi> was exceeding impatient to acquit himſelf of his true Negotiation, and therefore reſolv'd to go diſguis'd like a Page into the Duke's Chamber, where he ſoon got an Opportunity to preſent him with a Writing to ſign, which contain'd ſome general Propoſitions; and moreover procur'd from him a Promiſe to be at the <hi>Carnival</hi> at <hi>Venice.</hi> His Royal Highneſs reſolv'd to be there at the Time appointed; but to avoid ſuſpicion, gave out, That he deſign'd only to go thither for Diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; when his true Reaſon was to confer with the Duke of <hi>Bavaria,</hi> and ſome other Princes, about a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſederacy againſt <hi>France.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:101085:21"/>
            <p>Some time after the Count's depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, the Duke made known his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Journey, when the <hi>French</hi> Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſador, fearing ſome Stratagem, would needs proffer his Service to wait on his Royal Highneſs, which the Duke endeavour'd to divert by all imaginable Means; but finding all fruitleſs, at laſt conſented to his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt, the better to prevent any Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicion that Miniſter might have of him.</p>
            <p>Theſe Princes being at length met at <hi>Venice,</hi> thought it moſt proper to treat ſecretly of the Affairs they came about; and for this purpoſe had pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cur'd a very fit Perſon, a Monk, to go backwards and forwards among them.</p>
            <p>By theſe Means an Alliance was ſoon ſtruck up between the Emperour, the Dukes of <hi>Savoy</hi> and <hi>Bavaria,</hi> and ſome other Sovereign Princes, upon the Foot of the Project concerted at <hi>Ausburg.</hi> The Treaty being thus ſign'd, the Princes took their Leaves
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:101085:22"/>of each other, and went towards their ſeveral Homes, after having drank liberally to the Succeſs of an Union they had ſo luckily engag'd in. The Duke of <hi>Savoy</hi> return'd thro' his Dominions as he came, accompanied by the <hi>French</hi> Embaſſador, who had not ſo much as quitted him one Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment all the while. His Royal High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, you muſt ſuppoſe, was not a little tickl'd with the Succeſs of this Expedition, which nevertheleſs was of no long continuance; for they had ſcarce travell'd a League, before the <hi>French</hi> Miniſter began to reproach him very ſeverely with having con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted a Confederacy with the King his Maſter's Enemies, which the Duke at firſt abſolutely denyd; but the Embaſſador immediately thereupon ſhewing him a Copy of the Treaty, you may imagine he remain'd under the greateſt Surprize.</p>
            <p>I don't queſtion but you will be glad to know by what Stratagem this Miniſter obtain'd a Paper of this Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance: Why, it was by means of the very Monk we before ſpoke of;
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:101085:22"/>for the Embaſſador having obſerv'd that Perſon to go and come often be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Princes, thought it but good Policy to ſound him, and at laſt ſo far ſucceeded, that upon paying the promis'd Sum of 200000 <hi>Livres,</hi> he obtain'd a true Copy of the Treaty. We may hereby obſerve, That no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing can eſcape the Knowledge of <hi>France,</hi> ſince ſhe is willing to give ſo liberally for her Intelligence. Theſe ſubtle Proceedings of the Duke's caus'd his Moſt Chriſtian Majeſty ever after to give no great Credit to his Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtations, but always to ſuſpect him of inclining to the Emperour's Intereſt.</p>
            <p>His Moſt Chriſtian Majeſty look'd upon this Treaty of <hi>Venice</hi> like that of <hi>Ausburg,</hi> to be a trifling Project, and no ways capable to oppoſe his De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns: But notwitſtanding, he reſerv'd a Reſolution to revenge the Treachery plaid him, upon the firſt Occaſion. But as the League of <hi>Ausburg</hi> ſerv'd for a Foundation to that of <hi>Venice,</hi> ſo, no doubt, this Treaty of <hi>Venice</hi> has been a Ground-plot for the Confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racy which has ſince been contracted with <hi>Savoy.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="32" facs="tcp:101085:23"/>
            <p>To return to my Subject: His Moſt Chriſtian Majeſty being but ill ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied with the Conduce of his Royal Highneſs, thought it high time not to ſuffer himſelf to be blinded any long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er by his fair Proteſtations; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore without further delay command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Monſieur <hi>Catinat</hi> immediately to paſs the Mountains with an Army of above 18000 Men. This General poſted away before his Army to <hi>Turin,</hi> to learn from the Duke's own Mouth, what was hitherto only tranſmitted by Miniſters, the Reſult of his Reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions.</p>
            <p>The Approaches of this Army ſoon alarm'd all the Princes of <hi>Italy,</hi> inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that they quickly got together to keep the War out of their own Territories, which was like to rage ſo fiercely in their Neighbourhood; or at leaſt to endeavour a Neutrality, if they could not obtain an Accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modation between the two Crowns. Herein the Great Duke of <hi>Tuſcany</hi> was the moſt earneſt; but what en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gag'd him chiefly, was, the dangerous
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:101085:23"/>Sickneſs of the <hi>Dauphineſs,</hi> hoping that if ſhe dy'd, by obliging <hi>France</hi> in this Mediation, he might have an Oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity to get his Daughter accepted in Marriage by the <hi>Dauphin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Duke of <hi>Fuenſalida</hi> fearing leſt Mareſchal <hi>Catinat</hi>'s arrival at <hi>Turin</hi> might alter the Diſpoſitions of that Court, which had already determin'd to declare in favour of the Emperour, thought his ſureſt way was to provide ſpeedily for his Defence, in caſe Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs might' happen diſadvantageous for the <hi>Milaneze.</hi> He immediately therefore iſſu'd out Commiſſions for new Levies; writ to the Vice-Roy of <hi>Naples, Sicily,</hi> and <hi>Sardinia,</hi> to ſend him freſh Recruits; got ready his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gazins, and ſoon ſtood upon his Guard, expecting Acts of Hoſtility every Day from the <hi>French.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Before we proceed further, it will not be amiſs to give a ſhort Account of the Rigours us'd by the Court of <hi>France</hi> towards his Royal Highneſs, by inſiſting peremptorily: on his dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the <hi>Vaudois</hi> out of his Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, for no Reaſon; and which was one of the principal Motives that en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gag'd
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:101085:24"/>the Duke of <hi>Savoy</hi> to ſeek after his Liberty, by a timely breaking with that Tyrant. For whenever it pleas'd this Moſt Chriſtian King to Command, he muſt unavoidably O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey, being no better than a Tributary to his Pleaſure. Every body knows, his Royal Highneſs cou'd not eaſily have been wrought upon to baniſh ſuch faithful Subjects as the <hi>Vaudois,</hi> who had ſo often ſignalliz'd their Zeal and Courage for both him and his Predeceſſors: But this Moſt Chriſtian King, having form'd his Deſign to extirpate the Reform'd Religion, not only out of <hi>France,</hi> but alſo where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever elſe he could prevail, corrupted ſo the Inclinations of this Prince and his Miniſters, that his Royal Highneſs all of a ſudden became a Perſecutor, in ſpite of his natural Diſpoſition to the contrary. As ſoon therefore as this pernicious Practice was begun at <hi>Turin,</hi> you might there perceive the ſame cruel Spirit and Politicks reign as in <hi>France;</hi> and his Royal Highneſs, whatever natural averſion he had for ſuch Barbarities, was forc'd to yield to the <hi>French</hi> Example, without ſo
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:101085:24"/>much as enquiring whether his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings were juſt or not.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Vaudois</hi> had enjoy'd an uninter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted Exerciſe of their Religion ever ſince the War with the <hi>Genoeſe,</hi> and were never perſecuted under the Reign of <hi>Charles Emanuel</hi> the Second, nor the Regency of the Dutcheſs Dowager, even till the Year 1685; which made them hope they might ſtill have the ſame Liberty under the preſent Reign of <hi>Victor Amedeus</hi> II. and the rather, becauſe they had done him conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Services againſt the <hi>Mondovite</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels, which he ſuppreſs'd meerly by their Aſſiſtance, in the Year 1684. All theſe Conſiderations enclin'd his Royal Highneſs to write 'em a very obliging Letter; but the Machinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the <hi>French</hi> King, who had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolv'd to deſtroy 'em, were ſo ſucceſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful at the Court of <hi>Turin,</hi> that he ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd whatever he pleas'd, his Royal Highneſs not daring to refuſe one in whoſe Power it was to force him to obey. The firſt Proceedings therefore of the <hi>French</hi> Miniſters were to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire, That the Governor of the Val<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies ſhould publiſh an Edict to forbid
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:101085:25"/>all. Strangers inhabiting there. This came out about the end of the end of the Year 1685, and was as a Fore-runner to all the Cruelties that were afterwards there practis'd. But here we may ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe his Royal Highneſs thus far, that he only conſented by a baſe Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſcenſion to have his Subjects but<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher'd by a Power that conſults only his heat of Revenge and Ambition to rule Paramount in all the Courts of <hi>Europe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>After the Expiration of the Edict of <hi>Nantes,</hi> the Council of <hi>France,</hi> who vow'd the Deſtruction of the <hi>Vaudois,</hi> together with the <hi>Hugonots,</hi> made freſh Motions to the Duke of <hi>Savoy,</hi> to publiſh a ſecond Edict againſt them; which they obtain'd the 31th of <hi>January</hi> 1686, and by which the Exerciſe of their Religion was forbid, under Penalty of their Lives, Confiſcation of their Goods, Demoliſhing of their Temples, and Baniſhment of their Preachers: And moreover, their Children were to be Baptiz'd, and brought up in the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Religion, at the peril of their Father's being otherwiſe ſent to the Gallies.</p>
            <pb n="37" facs="tcp:101085:25"/>
            <p>The <hi>Vaudois</hi> hereupon preſented four ſubſequent Petitions to his Royal Highneſs, humbly praying to have this Edict revok'd; but all to no purpoſe: for they were likely to be redreſs'd only by Delays. They could not in the leaſt imagine what ſhould induce the Duke of <hi>Savoy</hi> to treat 'em after ſo barbarous a manner; never miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſting the Influence of the <hi>French</hi> Miniſter, becauſe they thought them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves ſecure of his Moſt Chriſtian Majeſty's Protection, he having before declar'd himſelf <hi>Garrantee</hi> of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents granted 'em in the Years 1655 and 1664, which he not only pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cur'd from his Royal Highneſs in their favour, but alſo ſent a formidable Army into <hi>Piedmont</hi> to ſee 'em per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd.</p>
            <p>The Noiſe theſe Inhumane Practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces made in the World, mov'd the Proteſtant <hi>Swiſs-Cantons</hi> to diſpatch their Deputies to his Royal Highneſs, endeavouring to diſengage this Prince from his perſiſting in the Ruine of the <hi>Vaudois.</hi> Theſe Miniſters ſet forth from <hi>Baſle</hi> in the Year 1686, at the beginning of the Month of <hi>March;</hi>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:101085:26"/>when being arriv'd at <hi>Turin,</hi> and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving obtain'd Audience of his Royal Highneſs, they inſinuated, That the Proteſtant <hi>Cantons,</hi> their Maſters, were extremely concern'd for the cruel Treatment of his Royal Highneſs's faithful Subjects the <hi>Vaudois,</hi> and that as well in regard of the Ties of Friendſhip between them, and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity in Religion with them, as in reſpect of the Liberty of Conſcience granted 'em by his Royal Highneſs in the Years 1655 and 1664, which was altogether the Product of their Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation; and therefore, as they humbly conceiv'd, the Violation of it muſt be in prejudice of his Royal Highneſs's Word and Honour.</p>
            <p>Whatever ſolid Arguments theſe Embaſſadors could uſe to undeceive his Royal Highneſs, and encline him to revoke his Bloody Edict, were ſtill prevented by the Artifices of <hi>France,</hi> ſo that they might well have expected this Anſwer only, That the Duke of <hi>Savoy</hi> was ſo ſtrictly engag'd to the Moſt Chriſtian King, that it was not in his power to comply with their Requeſt; nay, tho' his natural Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:101085:26"/>was the moſt averſe in the World from perſecuting his moſt faithful Subjects; yet that of <hi>France</hi> having got the Aſcendant both over him and his Council, he was no longer Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of either. This anſwer you may imagine was but very little to their liking; therefore the Ambaſſadours thought themſelves oblig'd to preſent a Memorial to his Royal Highneſs, wherein among other things, they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinuated, that his Predeceſſors having engag'd their Royal Word to ſeveral Sovereigns, and particularly the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant <hi>Cantons</hi> their Maſters, that they wou'd never diſturb the Repoſe and Tranquillity of the <hi>Vaudois,</hi> and that becauſe of their Royal Patents, they had granted 'em, they humbly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd his Royal Highneſs could not diſpenſe with thoſe Engagments with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out violating his Royal Word; and that becauſe theſe Patents muſt not be barely look'd upon as Tolera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, but rather as perpetual Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſions, Irrevocable, Sacred and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>violable.</p>
            <p>The Ambaſſadours enforced theſe Reaſons by many others which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:101085:27"/>more needy to the Intereſt and Politicks of <hi>Savoy;</hi> and which might have been capable to have mov'd him, had not the <hi>French</hi> King oppos'd them by others that tended altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to introduce Fire, Blood and Slaughter into the Dominions of this Prince. Underſtanding Men have all along clearly perceiv'd, that the chief Aim of <hi>France</hi> was to weaken the Duke, by ruining the <hi>Vaudois,</hi> who, for their Valour, were always look'd upon as his right Arm; and who, tho' with their ſmall Number were able alone to bafflle the Deſigns of the <hi>French</hi> King, and oppoſe the Incurſions of his Troops.</p>
            <p>Many other Proteſtant Princes like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe writ to his Royal Highneſs in Favour of the <hi>Vaudois;</hi> but all with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out doing any good. This moſt Chriſtian King had gain'd ſo far up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his Inclinations, that even in ſpite of himſelf he was forc'd to yield to the Torrent that bore him down be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it, and which at laſt carry'd him to a Precipice that foretold no leſs than the utter Ruin of his Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. The <hi>Swiſs</hi> Ambaſſadors having
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:101085:27"/>at length demanded a poſitive Anſwer, his Royal Highneſs caus'd the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſs of St. <hi>Thomas,</hi> one of his Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters for Foreign Affairs, to acquaint 'em, that he was extremely ſorry it was not in his Power to comply with their Maſter's Requeſt: And the <hi>French</hi> Miniſter moreover ſuggeſted to him to add, that provided the laſt Edict was not already put in Execution, he would endeavour to find ſome Expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to procure the <hi>Vaudois</hi> Leave to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire out of his Dominions after that they had diſpoſed of their Poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
            <p>We ſhall paſs over in Silence ſeveral other Circumſtances that relate to this Negotiation, it not being my Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to enter into Particulars of the Cruelties exercis'd againſt the <hi>Vau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dois,</hi> for which a much larger Volume would not ſuffice. I think my ſelf only oblig'd to give an Account hereof the principal Accidents that have been the Occaſion of the Differences between the Duke of <hi>Savoy</hi> and <hi>France,</hi> from the very Beginning of this War. I ſhall next proceed to examine the Conduct of his Royal Highneſs, ſince
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:101085:28"/>his Rupture, as well in regard to the moſt Serene Allies, as <hi>France,</hi> even to the Concluſion of the Treaty late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſign'd by him; by which he is once more reconcil'd to a Crown that has promiſed a great deal, but will, no doubt, perform little or no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing.</p>
            <p>We may affirm freely, that this Prince, having been a Slave to the <hi>French</hi> King ſo many Years, and groan'd ſo long under a Yoke that other Sovereigns now fight to be ſecur'd from, never had a fairer Occaſion to releaſe him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf than at preſent, which he would have laid hold on, had he been but the leaſt ſenſible of his Intereſt. When a Man makes ſuch Overſights as this, he ſeldom or never recovery, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps for above theſe Hundred Years there may not happen a League ſo puiſſant and daring as this. There was no other way of withſtanding the Greatneſs of <hi>France,</hi> but by a Union of ſo many Princes; that Crown be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing too formidable to be oppos'd by a ſingle Force. According to common Opinion, God Almighty only has reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red this great Power to himſelf, who
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:101085:28"/>keeps in his hand the Performances of Princes; and who can in an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant thruſt 'em from their Thrones, and deprive 'em both of their Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities and their Force, whereof this Hiſtory every where abounds with convincing Examples. This being granted, there is no doubt, but the League of theſe moil Serene Princes now in War, againſt <hi>France,</hi> has been rais'd by this Almighty Power, to humble the exorbitant Greatneſs of that Crown; and this will the more plainly appear, if we conſider the Motives, that occaſion'd it, its uninterrupted Continuance for nine Years together, remaining always firm, and not to be ſhaken by the At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts and Artifices which <hi>France</hi> has all along made uſe of to weaken, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found or divide the Princes which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd it.</p>
            <p>Notwithſtanding theſe mighty Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts, and continu'd Diſſentions which this moſt Chriſtian King has endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour'd to ſow in almoſt all the Courts of Europe, they have nevertheleſs been ſo far from weakening them, that they have rather contributed towards a
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:101085:29"/>more firm and lading Alliance, which all the Confederates have unanimous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reſolv'd to carry on, except <hi>Savoy</hi> only, who may be juſtly reproach'd hereafter by all Princes for ſo baſe a Compliance with a Monarch that is already above half ruin'd.</p>
            <p>But before we go any farther, let us firſt ſee, what this Prince has freely promis'd to the moſt Serene Allies, and more particularly to the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, King of <hi>England,</hi> and United Provinces, which are to be conſider'd as the chief Actors in the League. In order whereunto, I ſhall oblige the Reader with a true Copy of the Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty that his Royal Highneſs made with the Emperour, and which was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented him by the Abbot <hi>Grimani</hi> to be ſign'd; which is as follows:</p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <hi>HIS Imperial Majeſty being ſenſibly mov'd with the late reiterated Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naces of the</hi> French <hi>King towards his Royal Highneſs, which ſo viſibly tend to op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs him; As likewiſe conſidering the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>violable Friendſhip his Royal Highneſs pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſes for his ſaid Imperial Majeſty: Alſo having moreover underſtood, that his moſt
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:101085:29"/>Chriſtian Majeſty had caus'd an Army to enter into the Territories of the ſaid Duke, to oblige him to give up two of his Chief Fortreſſes, as likewiſe to furniſh) him with</hi> 2000 <hi>Foot and Two Regiments of Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goons, to aſſiſt him in an Invaſion upon</hi> Milan; <hi>his Imperial Majeſty has thought himſelf oblig'd to ſuccour a Prince that has always approv'd himſelf an unſhaken Well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſher to the Empire. Whereupon he has herewith ſent the Sieur Abbot</hi> Vincent Grimani, <hi>with expreſs Orders and full Power to Negotiate, Treat, and Agree with his ſaid Royal Highneſs, in an Alli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance that may as well ſerve to ſtrengthen his Imperial Majeſty's Affairs, as to ſecure thoſe of his Royal Highneſs againſt the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture Attempts of</hi> France. <hi>And for this purpoſe his moſt Serene Highneſs</hi> Victor Amedeus <hi>the Second, Duke of</hi> Savoy, <hi>and the aforeſaid Sieur Abbot</hi> Grimani, <hi>do Article as follows.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">I. <hi>His Moſt Serene Highneſs obliges himſelf for the future not to enter into any Treaty of Alliance with the Moſt Chriſtian King, without Conſent of the Emperour: But to remain always under a good Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpondence with his Imperial Majeſty, as a faithful Prince of the Empire.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:101085:30"/>
               <p n="2">II. <hi>That he will never Act hut in Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction with his Imperial Majeſty, or ſome other of the Allies.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">III. <hi>That he will always employ his Forces againſt</hi> France <hi>or its Adherents.</hi>
               </p> 
            </q>
            <p>On the other Part, the Abbot <hi>Gri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mani,</hi> in the Name of His Imperial Majeſty and the Empire, promiſes,</p>
            <q>
               <p n="1">I. <hi>That his Imperial Majeſty will not enter into any Truce or Treaty of Peace with</hi> France, <hi>without his Royal Highneſs's being therein comprised.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">II. <hi>That the Emperour will ſo manage Matters, that the Governour of</hi> Milan <hi>ſhall always employ his Forces to preſerve the Dominions of his Royal Highneſs: As likewiſe, That the Spaniſh Fleet ſhall en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to ſecure the Town and County of</hi> Nice.</p>
               <p n="3">III. <hi>That his Imperial Majeſty will forthwith ſend</hi> 6000 <hi>of his beſt Troops, to be join'd with thoſe of his Royal High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and which his ſaid Imperial Majeſty engages to maintain, without expecting they ſhould have their Winter-Quarters in Piedmont.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">IV. <hi>That his Imperial Majeſty will uſe
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:101085:30"/>all his Endeavours to cauſe the</hi> Vaudois, French Refugies, <hi>and the</hi> 8000 <hi>Men which the Marqueſs of</hi> Borgomainero, <hi>Embaſſador from</hi> Spain, <hi>had promis'd ſhould go to</hi> Piedmont, <hi>ſhould join the Troops of his Royal Highneſs, the Emperor and Governor of</hi> Milan <hi>conſenting, he might make uſe of 'em at his pleaſure.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">V. <hi>That the Emperor and his Allies would endeavour to repoſſeſs his Royal Highneſs, either by Force or Treaty, of</hi> Pignerol, <hi>without any Pretence upon</hi> Montferrat <hi>for ſo doing; his Imperial Majeſty being willing to renounce all Title thereunto, the ancient Treaties notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">VI. <hi>And laſtly, His Imperial Majeſty will pretend no Right to any Conqueſt on that fide of</hi> France, <hi>but gives full liberty to his Royal Highneſs and the Governour of</hi> Milan <hi>to agree between 'em about it.</hi>
               </p> 
            </q>
            <p>This Treaty was Sign'd the Fourth of <hi>June,</hi> 1690; and the Abbot <hi>Gri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mani</hi> promis'd to get it Ratifi'd from <hi>Vienna</hi> in a Month.</p>
            <p>We may obſerve by the firſt Article, That his Royal Highneſs promiſes and agrees by a ſolemn Oath, not to
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:101085:31"/>enter into any Treaty either of Peace or Truce, with the Moſt Chriſtian King, without the Emperor's Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent; but to remain always under a good Correſpondence with his Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial Majeſty, as a faithful Prince of the Empire. But where is now the Performance of this ſolemn Promiſe? What is become of all theſe ſerious Engagements, which ought to have been ſo Sacred and Inviolable? Have not they been lately diſpens'd with by an unheard-of Baſeneſs? It muſt be acknowledg'd, that by this Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct his Royal Highneſs has unpardon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably affronted the Emperor, abus'd the moſt Serene Allies, and moreover been the greateſt of Enemies to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, by ſacrificing both his Dominions and his Liberty to the deceitful Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes of <hi>France;</hi> by which means he will not fail to incur the ſevereſt In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation of ſo many Potent Princes he has betray'd, and from whom he has receiv'd ſo many repeated Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligations.</p>
            <p>By the ſecond Article his Royal Highneſs promiſes to act altogether in Conjunction with the Emperor and
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:101085:31"/>the other Allies. But we can be confident here by convincing Proofs, which we ſhall make appear more at large hereafter, that his Royal High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs has had ſeveral ſecret Intelligen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces with <hi>Frame,</hi> throughout the whole Courſe of this War; and that he has been ſo far from acting in conjunction with the moſt Serene Allies, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to his ſolemn Promiſe, that he has all along under-hand favour'd the Enterprizes of the <hi>French</hi> King; and therein his Conduct has been the more faulty, as he has always endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour'd to approve his Sincerity and Good-will by his Envoys and other Miniſters; but which we are now ſenſible had no other Aim than to get out of us the Drift of our Deſigns, which he forthwith ſent to <hi>France.</hi> This has been the Occaſion, in a great meaſure, that the Arms of the moſt Serene Allies have made ſo little Progreſs in <hi>Flanders, Germany,</hi> and elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where, becauſe the <hi>French</hi> King being inform'd of all our Proceedings, took his Meaſures, and made his Advances accordingly; inſomuch that his For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces were almoſt always ſuperiour in
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:101085:32"/>Number to ours, which baffl'd our Deſigns either to Beſiege any Place, or give Battel: And if the glorious Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaking of the Siege of <hi>Namur</hi> ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceded ſo well, we may aſcribe it chiefly to the Duke of <hi>Savoy</hi>'s know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing nothing of it, being manag'd wholly by the King of <hi>England,</hi> with ſo great Circumſpection and Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, that that Action alone deceiv'd the Vigilance of <hi>France.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Conduce of his Royal High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs during theſe late Years, has been ſo little conformable to an honeſt Meaning, that in full Congreſs many Miniſters of the Allies have been ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lig'd to reproach his Envoy, Monſieur <hi>de la Tour,</hi> That his Maſter did not proceed according to Juſtice: But this Envoy being a Man of Parts, and able to defend his Prince's Proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, had always an Excuſe ready at hand; ſo that whilſt he fed the Court of <hi>England,</hi> and die other Allies, with his Maſter's mighty Projects, his Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Highneſs, by a ſecret Correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, did his Buſineſs with <hi>France,</hi> and moreover drain'd great Sums of Money from both Parties. Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:101085:32"/>Men daily obſerv'd, That this Credulity of ours would be no ſmall Obſtacle to a General Peace, which we nevertheleſs pretend to force <hi>France</hi> to a Compliance with: But the End has ſhewn, that the <hi>Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lians</hi> are better Proficients in the Art of Deceiving, than others; and that ſooner or later we always repent pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing too much Confidence in thoſe People.</p>
            <p>The third Article provides, That his Royal Highneſs ſhall always em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy his Forces againſt <hi>France</hi> or its Adherents, together with thoſe of the Allies. But this Article will appear to have been no leſs violated on the Part of his Royal Highneſs, than the former: For thoſe that Commanded the Auxiliary Troops in <hi>Italy,</hi> being Men of nice Diſcernment, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh'd Merit, having made it their Buſineſs to pry into the Conduct and Proceedings of this Prince, have been Eye-witneſſes of all his Intelligences with Monſieur <hi>Catinat,</hi> and have ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted us. That his Royal Highneſs was ſo far from acting in Conjunction with the moſt Serene Allies, that he
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:101085:33"/>apparently made it his Buſineſs to ſpare his own Troops, and to expoſe thoſe of the Confederates to the greateft Dangers. For in one Battel his Royal Highneſs's Generals, having private Intelligence with the <hi>French,</hi> delay'd till they were ready to pour down upon the <hi>Imperialiſts</hi> and <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants</hi> with their ſuperior Numbers, whilſt the <hi>Savoyards</hi> only look'd on, or elſe betaking themſelves to flight, abandon'd the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Troops to the Mercy of their Enemies. The like Practice has been generally obſerv'd in all the Skirmiſhes or Battels in <hi>Italy;</hi> inſomuch that by theſe fatal Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherries ſeveral brave and experienc'd Generals of the Allies have been in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>humanely butcher'd, without <hi>Savoy</hi>'s taking any care to remedy an Abuſe that was the ruine of thoſe that were only capable to make head againſt <hi>Frame,</hi> and ſecure his Royal Highneſs s Dominions.</p>
            <p>After having ſpoken of the Engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments the Duke of <hi>Savoy</hi> had with the Emperor, and which ought eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally to have united him to the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria;</hi> let us come to the ſtrict
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:101085:33"/>Alliance he had contracted with the King of <hi>England:</hi> And hereof we cannot give you a more ſignal Proof than the ſpecious <hi>Harangue</hi> made to his <hi>Britannick</hi> Majeſty by his tricking Envoy the President <hi>de la Tour,</hi> which is as follows.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>SIR,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>HIS Royal Highneſs congratulates Your Majeſties glorious Acceſs to a Throne due to Your Birth, merited by Your Virtue, and maintain'd by Your Valour. Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence ordain'd it for Your Sacred Head, for the Accompliſhment of Heavens Deſigns from all Eternity: That Providence which, after a long forbearance, raiſes up Choſen Inſtruments to ſuppreſs Violence, and protect Juſtice. The wonderful Beginnings of Your Reign are aſſur'd Preſages of the Bleſſings which Heaven is preparing for the Integrity of Your Intentions, which have no other Aim than to reſtore this flouriſhing Kingdom to that Grandeur which it anciently enjoy'd, and to break off thoſe Chains under the weight of which all <hi>Europe</hi> at preſent groans. This magna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimous Deſign, ſo worthy the <hi>Heroe</hi> of our Age, ſoon fill'd his Royal Highneſs
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:101085:34"/>with unſpeakable Joy, tho' he were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain'd to keep it undiſclos'd for a time in the Privacies of his Heart; and if after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards he could not forbear to let it break forth, the Obligation for that Happineſs is due to Your Majeſty, who has at length inſpir'd him with Hopes of Liberty, after ſo in any Years of Servitude.</p>
                  <p>My Words, Sir, and the Treaty which I have already ſign'd at the <hi>Hague</hi> with Your Majeſties Envoy, but faintly expreſs my Maſter's paſſionate Deſires to unite himſelf to Your Majeſty by an inviolable Devotion to Your Service. The Honour which he has of being one that appertains to Your Majeſty, has knit the firſt Knot of this Union; and the Protection You grant him with ſo much Generoſity, has brought it to the perfection of being indiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolvable. Theſe are the ſincere Sentiments of his Royal Highneſs, with which I dare not preſume to intermix any thing of my own: For how ardent ſoever my Zeal may be, how profound ſoever my Venera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Your Majeſties Glory, I know not how better to expreſs it than by a ſilent Reſpect and Admiration.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <pb n="55" facs="tcp:101085:34"/>
            <p>Can there be any thing more to the purpoſe, better ſtudi'd, and more eloquent, than this <hi>Harangue?</hi> His Royal Highneſs ſeems to inſinuate, he will always be govern'd by his <hi>Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tannick</hi> Majeſty, to whom he ſolemnly vows eternal Friendſhip, and for whom he expreſſes the greateſt Vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration imaginable: A Prince whom he acknowledges God has rais'd to the Crown of <hi>England</hi> to break off the Chains of <hi>Europe,</hi> and more particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly to free him from a Slavery which he had groan'd under ſo many Years. His Royal Highneſs, I ſay, profeſſes ſo entire a Reſpect for the King of <hi>England,</hi> that he ſeems to think of nothing more than Revenge and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtility againſt <hi>France;</hi> inſomuch that to hear him ſpeak, you would believe he were the moſt zealous of all the <hi>League.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But here we muſt obſerve, That his Royal Highneſs did not a little diſſemble, when he dictated this Speech to his <hi>Envoy;</hi> and, for my part, I am of opinion, that a Man cannot have extraordinary Principles, that can ſo eaſily digeſt Hypocriſie
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:101085:35"/>and Treachery. Methinks a bare regard to ones Honour, of which every Man ought to be tender, eſpecially Sovereign Princes, might have been a ſufficient Check to ſuch an inglorious Action, which is rather the reſult of a mean and daſtardly Soul, than a brave and noble.</p>
            <p>Whatever it be, certain it is, that this Prince, whom all <hi>Europe</hi> look'd upon with admiration, having taken off the Mask of Hypocriſie, ſhews us a quite different Face from what his Miniſters, more Jeſuits than Embaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dors, had repreſented him.</p>
            <p>When we ſeriouſly reflect upon the Particulars of his Royal Highneſs's Conduct during this War, we may obſerve how many different Strata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gems he has made uſe of to blind the Confederates, diſcover their ſecret Deſigns, therewithal ſpeedily to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form <hi>France;</hi> and laſtly, to drain this latter, and more openly the former, of vaſt Sums of Money, with which lie has all along fill'd his Coffers. This Paſſion thus prevailing over his Highneſs, makes us look upon his Treachery as the Fruits of a ſordid
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:101085:35"/>Avarice and baſe Policy, by which he has ſervilely comply'd with <hi>France,</hi> and withal endeavour'd to ſacrifice the Intereſt of the moſt Serene Allies, as likewiſe the Common Safety of <hi>Europe,</hi> whatever his Miniſter <hi>de la Tour</hi> might ſay to the contrary. I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve this is his trueſt Character, tho' that Envoy and the reſt of his Fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity have endeavour'd to lull the Allies, by repreſenting their Maſter as another <hi>Caeſar</hi> or <hi>Alexander,</hi> abound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with Zeal, Conſtancy, and Bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very, and who would ſooner chuſe to die a thouſand times, than act any thing that ſhould be in the leaſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the Intereſt of the moſt Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſt Alliance he had engag'd in.</p>
            <p>However Matters go, theſe flatter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Miniſters will never be able to excuſe their Matter's Conduct. We are but too well acquainted with the Occaſion of it, tho' one would think a Prince ſhould have conſulted his Honour and Conſcience, before he attempted any thing at leaſt that might have prejudic'd thoſe that had ſo generouſly afforded him Protection, at a time eſpecially when he ſtood in ſo great need of it.</p>
            <pb n="58" facs="tcp:101085:36"/>
            <p>We have already ſeen the Preſident <hi>de la Tour</hi>'s Speech to the King of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> whereby his Royal Highneſs promiſes to enter into a ſtrict Alliance with his <hi>Britannick</hi> Majeſty and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Confederates. Now let us come to that of the Marqueſs <hi>de Govon,</hi> his Highneſs's Envoy extraordinary to King <hi>James,</hi> the Sixth of <hi>September</hi> laſt.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>SIR,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>HIS Royal Highneſs is at length happily reconciled to his moſt Chriſtian Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty againſt whom he bad raſhly taken up Arms, tho' he has all along receiv'd ſincere Proofs of his Majeſty's Protection. The ſtrict Leagues his noble Anceſtors have heretofore had with <hi>France,</hi> and the more exact Alliance his Royal Highneſs has con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted by his Marriage, have but the more disjoyn'd him from the Intereſt of that King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom. This Union which ought to have been the moſt inviolable, we have lately ſeen interrupted by the Artifices of his moſt Chriſtian Majeſty's and your Majeſty's E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies; to whom his Royal Highneſs has been hitherto ſo weak as to give ear. His Royal Highneſs therefore humbly beggs your
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:101085:36"/>Majeſty would, pleaſe to pardon his paſt Conduct, ſo very contrary to his ſincere De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires to re-eſtabliſh your Majeſty upon your Thrones. The Injuſtice and Oppreſſion of your Enemies, Sir, have cauſed his moſt Chriſtian Majeſty to engage in this War. God Almighty has hitherto favour'd his At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts, becauſe they are juſt; and 'tis alſo to be hop'd he will lend the like Attention to your Majeſty's Petition. His Royal Highneſs, for his part, will contribute all in his Power thereunto, who likewiſe flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters himſelf, that this Treaty lately ſign'd with his moſt Chriſtian Majeſty, may be a Means to divide thoſe Princes (whoſe Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on will infallibly oppoſe your Majeſty's Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum to your Dominions) which may facili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate a general Peace, the firſt Effects of which will undoubtedly be your Majeſty's Re-eſtabliſhment on your Throne. This has been the Occaſion, Sir, of his Royal High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs's withdrawing from the Allies, and which he hopes will be thought fully to anſwer his Promiſes to your Majeſty's Miniſters, ſent to ſollicite him in that behalf. This he would have perform'd ſooner, but your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty may be inform'd from the moſt Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an King, what Reaſons enclin'd him to the contrary. Theſe, Sir, an the ſincere Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtations
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:101085:37"/>of his Royal Highneſs, which he will endeavour to make appear by his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinu'd Prayers for the Proſperity of your Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Majeſty.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>We may find by this <hi>Harangue</hi> that his Royal Highneſs thinks fit to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble no longer. He has now per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd his Bargain. His Miniſter the Marqueſs of <hi>Govon</hi> has given a true Copy of his Inclinations; and, no doubt he had the ſame Sentiments when the ſubtle <hi>de la Tour</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounc'd his ſtudy'd <hi>Harangue;</hi> but then you muſt ſuppoſe he had not ſufficiently fleec'd the Allies. Let us obſerve therefore there is ſomething exceeding ſingular in the two different Characters which theſe Miniſters repreſent: One con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratulates King <hi>William</hi> upon his glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Acceſs to the Throne, while the other flatters King <hi>James</hi> with a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of his Reſtauration. But to ſhew farther how exceedingly the Duke of <hi>Savoy</hi> has both ſlighted and abus'd his Alliance with ſo many Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rene Princes, notwithſtanding their repeated Kindneſſes towards him, we
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:101085:37"/>muſt here examine into his Conduct during the whole War in <hi>Italy,</hi> the Particulars of which will be ſo much the more Authentick, as we have all along ſufficient Proofs of what we affirm; and I am pretty well aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red that all who are acquainted with the Court of <hi>Turin,</hi> will be ready to ſubſcribe to what I ſay. 'Tis not up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Account of Hatred or Partiality that I undertake herein to undeceive the <hi>Publick</hi> in an Affair that the Preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent <hi>de la Tour</hi> took ſo much Pains to conceal from the Court of <hi>England</hi> and States General, during his Reſidence at the <hi>Hague.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I know very well that he made it his chief Buſineſs to influence the Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derates, that whatever Account they might have of his Matter's partial Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings, it came altogether from the Malice of certain <hi>Jacobites,</hi> whoſe end was to render his Royal Highneſs ſuſpected, that they might thereby the better occaſion a Diſunion, which they imagin'd would prove fatal to the League. He likewiſe en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour'd to prove the moſt diſcerning of our Friends to be <hi>French</hi> Eniſſari<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:101085:38"/>whilſt he play'd his own part under a counterfeit Sincerity, fed the Credu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of the Allies with fair hopes, and by that means at length he obtain'd whatever he could deſire; whilſt his politick Matter was carrying on his Deſigns, which at laſt concluded in a Treaty with the <hi>French</hi> King. No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſure can be more baſe than this Practice: But let us proceed to Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars.</p>
            <p>You muſt know in the firſt Place, that in all the Councils of War held at <hi>Turin,</hi> from the very firſt Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagn, down to the laſt, the Duke of <hi>Savoy</hi> and his Miniſters would never admit any of thoſe of the Allies, but whom they thought fit; and exclude the beſt affected, ſuch as the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Generals, and other wiſe Officers, who might otherwiſe have been able to baffle their Deſigns, and detect their Treacheries. Whence it comes to paſs, that all the Reſolutions taken in thoſe Councils of War, have been in favour of the Enemy. To this may be added, the Antipathy that was all along obſervable betwixt the Generals of his Royal Highneſs and thoſe of
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:101085:38"/>the Allies; witneſs the repeated In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſults and bloody Outrages the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſſes of <hi>Bagnaſque</hi> and <hi>Parella</hi> offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to thoſe Officers of the Allies who had beſt ſignaliz'd themſelves upon eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Occaſion, and this by reaſon of their ſo loyally adhering to their. Maſter's Intereſt, who had entruſted 'em with the Command of their Forces.</p>
            <p>Secondly, the ſlow Proceedings of the Court of <hi>Turin</hi> were partial, the <hi>Italian</hi> Generals never caring to be in the Field, till they had given ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent time to <hi>Catinat</hi> to rally his Army, and receive Recruits which were ſent him from ſeveral Parts of <hi>France.</hi> Hence it comes, that he was always firſt in A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and poſſeſs'd himſelf of the moſt advantagious Poſts: for being ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periour in Number, and having the Field at liberty, he might very eaſily effect whatever he undertook, they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver offering to oppoſe him till he had done his Buſineſs, or at leaſt, was in a fair way to do it. I paſs by the fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent Intelligences by Spies between the Generals, that nothing might be acted but by common Content.</p>
            <pb n="64" facs="tcp:101085:39"/>
            <p>In the third Place, the Care the Court of <hi>Turin</hi> took to eſtabliſh Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gazines and Markets where the <hi>French</hi> were permitted to come and buy what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever Subſiſtence they had occaſion for, at a time, eſpecially when moſt of their Provinces were reduc'd to the extremeſt Want; and, which ought to be look'd upon as a juſt Scourge ſent by God to humble that haughty Power. This Want, I ſay, muſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily have forc'd the <hi>French</hi> forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with to have re-paſs'd the Mountains, had not his Royal Highneſs and his Council timely provided for their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief, by cauſing all ſorts of Commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities to be brought from <hi>Milan</hi> and other parts of <hi>Italy,</hi> to regale their E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy's Army. This was all done in Sight of the Allies; and when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever any Complaints were made, the Senate of <hi>Turin</hi> was dumb, or anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed only by Riddles, after the <hi>Italian</hi> Manner. All this while his Royal Highneſs crowded his Coffers with <hi>French Lonid'ors;</hi> and Mareſchal <hi>Cati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nat,</hi> who knew well his Temper, was not at all ſparing of 'em.</p>
            <pb n="65" facs="tcp:101085:39"/>
            <p>The Honour of <hi>France,</hi> and Preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of an Army, which was juſt then ready to periſh, gave way for no Parſimony. I mention nothing but what is notoriouſly known; and I appeal to the Generals of the moſt Serene Allies, who then commanded in <hi>Italy,</hi> if they have not been Eye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witneſſes of all I affirm.</p>
            <p>But let us proceed to other Practiſes, which are no leſs remarkable than the former. In the fifth Place, let us ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the Permiſſion that his Royal Highneſs gave to ſome Fellows diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſed like Peaſants, and ſent <hi>incog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nito</hi> by <hi>Catinat</hi> to ſubborn and liſt the Proteſtant Soldiers of die Regiments of <hi>Miremont</hi> and <hi>Montauban,</hi> whom they intended to carry off to the <hi>French</hi> Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, to the end that by their Diſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion the King of <hi>England's</hi> Forces might be ſo much the more weaken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and their own augmented. This, no doubt, was with deſign to favour the <hi>French</hi> King; who, if he could but get thoſe Proteſtant Enemies into his Power, thought himſelf ſecure of his Project, by the Intelligence he all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long had with his Royal Highneſs.
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:101085:40"/>This Relation is ſo much the leſs to be queſtion'd, as it was verify'd by the Surprizal of ſeveral of theſe diſguis'd Traytors by the Officers of theſe Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giments, who taking 'em in the very Act, after having debauch'd above five and twenty Soldiers, immediately com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain'd of 'em to his Royal Highneſs, who remitting 'em to a Council of War, the Officers went away very well ſatisfied, believing they would be pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed according to the Enormity of their Crimes: But, would you think it? inſtead of doing ſo exemplary a Piece of Juſtice, they quite contrary aſſiſted 'em in their Eſcape. Of all which, to comply with the Reader's Curioſity, we will give the ſeveral Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars.</p>
            <p>Mareſchal <hi>Catinat</hi> every Market-day ſent a <hi>Piemonteze,</hi> diſguis'd like a Pea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant, into the Proteſtants Winter-Quarters, where this Traytor was wont to debauch by Money or fair Promiſes, about twenty five or thirty at a time, and ſend 'em by Night with a Guide to <hi>Pignerol.</hi> Herewith the Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers of theſe Regiments being at length inform'd, by means of ſome
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:101085:40"/>Deſerters, who had been taken, reſolv'd to pretend to be lifted themſelves, that they might the better diſcover the Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lain, who took upon him to liſt. For this Purpoſe they put on their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Soldiers Clothes, and by means of one of thoſe Deſerters who had been taken, they were conducted to the counterfeit Peaſant's Quarters, who receiving 'em with a great deal of Joy, immediately gave them Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, and told 'em the Names of the Regiments, and Captains that wait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for 'em at <hi>Pignerol.</hi> The Day of their Departure being come, the Pea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant promis'd to go along with 'em; when they being between twenty and thirty in all, as well Officers as Soldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, began to ſet forward; But their <hi>Piemonteze</hi> Captain was ſoon ſurpriz'd by a Preſent of Irons being brought him to carry him before the Governour, who promis'd the ſevereſt Juſtice on ſo villanous a Deſign. Some time after fix Officers of the fame Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments went and polled themſelves in the Night-time, in a Place where they knew the Deſerters muſt needs paſs, with deſign to diſcover more of
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:101085:41"/>theſe Villans, who were ſent to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce their Men to the Enemy. For this purpoſe they got up into ſev<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>al Trees, that they might keep them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves the better from being diſcovered. Whilſt they lay thus conceal'd, there came a Peaſant from the Town, whom they preſently ſeiz'd, and diving into his Pockets, found a Letter from the Governour, in whoſe Hands they had left the firſt Traytor. This Letter was an Anſwer to one of the Duke of <hi>Savoy</hi>'s, whereby he gave his Highneſs to underſtand, that according to his Commands, he would continue Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters ſo, that the <hi>Piemonteze</hi> Priſoner ſhould eſcape without having any harm done him. The Peaſant upon demand who gave him that Letter, anſwer'd, it was the Governour him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; which ſufficiently laid open the ſecret Intellegences the Court of <hi>Turin</hi> had with the Enemy, in order to ruine the Proteſtant Regiments. The Original of this Letter is ſtill to be ſeen in my Lord <hi>Galloway</hi>'s Hands, as a Monument of the Treachery and Baſeneſs of the Generals and other Officers of his Royal Highneſs.</p>
            <pb n="69" facs="tcp:101085:41"/>
            <p>His Royal Highneſs ſaw all this with his own Eyes; nothing eſcap'd his Knowledge. Nevertheleſs every thing was paſs'd by in profound Silence, and neglect. The poor Officers only of theſe Regiments, might murmur and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain, as long as they pleas'd, to ſee themſelves in a fair way to be ruin'd by theſe repeated Deſertions. To this Remark we may farther add the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign his Royal Highneſs had to ſell theſe Regiments by an uſurp'd Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity to the <hi>Venetians</hi> to go and ſerve in the <hi>Morea,</hi> which they muſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly have yielded to, had not they ſo vigorouſly oppos'd thoſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſals, affirming they belong'd only to his <hi>Britannick</hi> Majeſty, in whoſe Power it was alone to diſpoſe of 'em in that Nature. Theſe Matters being thus tranſacled in the Sight of all <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope,</hi> ſhall his Royal Highneſs's flatter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Miniſters for the future dare to boaſt their Maſter's Sincerity without a juſt Reproach? But let us proceed to the other Treacheries.</p>
            <p>In the ſixth Place comes the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct of his Royal Highneſs towards ſeveral <hi>French</hi> Refugees; who being
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:101085:42"/>oblig'd to paſs thro' this Prince's Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, inſtead of receiving them civilly, as he ought to have done; on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary he caus'd 'em all to be arreſted; and moreover order'd them to be bound Hand and Foot, and ſent to Mareſchal <hi>Cannat</hi> as Deſerters from his Army; and this altho' ſeveral Letters were writ him from <hi>France,</hi> that they had never been in any Service; but were the Sons of ſeveral rich Merchants, whom their Fathers thought fit to ſend out of that Kingdom. I believe there was never the like Cruelty thought on; and, which, ſufficiently demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, how little his Royal High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs ſeem'd to value the King of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> who had all along declar'd him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf their Protector, whilſt his Ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtneſs to comply with <hi>France</hi> was thereby unqueſtionably made appear. Of this Action I my ſelf was an Eye-witneſs, as well as all the Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers of the Auxiliary Forces.</p>
            <p>In the ſeventh Place, the Court of <hi>Turin</hi> every Year receiv'd the <hi>French</hi> Faſhions, by rich Preſents from the King of <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Monſieur,</hi> to the Duke of <hi>Savoy</hi> and his Dutcheſs, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:101085:42"/>that there was a continual Concourſe of Courriers between <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Turin,</hi> which ſhew'd the ſtrict Union between the two Crowns in ſpight of all the Well-meaning preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to the Allies.</p>
            <p>In the eighth Place, his Royal Highneſs s Conduct in beſieging <hi>Guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtre</hi> and <hi>Ambroa</hi> in <hi>Dauphinè,</hi> before he had made himſelf Maſter of <hi>Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anzon,</hi> where the French had their chief Magazines, as well as neglect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſeveral other Polls to favour his Retreat, and cut off that of Monſieur <hi>Catinat,</hi> viſibly prove his Royal High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs had all along Intelligence with the <hi>French,</hi> and that they two play'd their Game by Confederacy, which thoſe Officers in the Army who had leaſt Experience could eaſily diſcover. The deceas'd Mareſchal <hi>Schomberg</hi> of happy Memory was therewithal more than ordinarily af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected. He obſerv'd all their Proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings; but they were altogether out of his Power to redreſs. The <hi>Italian Junto</hi> governed all, and provided his Royal Highneſs did but amuſe the Confederacy with his imaginary
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:101085:43"/>Conqueſts and Irruptions into <hi>France,</hi> he had leiſure enough to receive Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney on both ſides.</p>
            <p>In the ninth Place, upon his Royal Highneſs's entering <hi>Dauphinè,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as he ought to have taken care that Count <hi>Schomberg,</hi> who commanded a ſeparate Army, which daily encrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by the Proteſtants which joyn'd him from all Provinces of <hi>France,</hi> might not want Proviſions, he not only ſuffer'd 'em to want Proviſions, but alſo neceſſary Amunition, for fear that Body mighty become more pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erful than that which his Highneſs commanded, and which conſequently might have proceeded farther than his private Intelligence with <hi>France</hi> would give leave; which oblig'd him to go no farther than <hi>Gap,</hi> his bare entring <hi>Dauphinè</hi> being ſufficient to blind the Allies, and drain their Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes. Hereupon the Proteſtants under Count <hi>Schomberg</hi>'s Conduct, not being able to ſubſiſt, were forc'd to diſperſe, which was the true Reaſon of the ſmall Progreſs of the Confederates Arms in <hi>Dauphinè.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="73" facs="tcp:101085:43"/>
            <p>There was alſo another Paſſage, which manifeſtly proves the Duke of <hi>Savoy</hi>'s Intelligence with <hi>France,</hi> which was, that his Royal Highneſs apprehending the Confederate Forces might grow too potent, and overrun <hi>France,</hi> which was not at all conducing to his purpoſe, ſuddenly feign'd a Relapſe of his Illneſs by the <hi>Small-Pox;</hi> of which, 'tis certain he was perfectly well in eight Days, intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this ſuppos'd Indiſpoſition to be an Excuſe for his Retreat, when he might have taken <hi>Grenoble,</hi> the Capital City of <hi>Dauphinè,</hi> and thence proceeded with his victorious Arms as far as <hi>Lyons;</hi> and at the ſame time made ſo conſiderable a Diverſion, that it would have been eaſie for the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies to have taken ſome important Place, or at leaſt to have enter'd that Kingdom either by way of <hi>Flanders,</hi> the <hi>Franche Comte,</hi> or County of <hi>Lux<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>embourg.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The moſt conſiderable Officers in our Army, under the Command of Count <hi>Schomberg,</hi> aſſure us unani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouſly, that this was the only Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity to have brought <hi>France</hi> to
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:101085:44"/>reaſonable Terms, provided the Duke of <hi>Savoy</hi> had but done his Part. This Campagne would have forc'd the <hi>French</hi> King to whatever Conditions we could have deſir'd, and moreover might have produc'd an honourable and laſting Peace. He was like to be attack'd then on his weak Side, and that Army might have march'd into the very Heart of his Kingdom, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out his being able to oppoſe 'em in the leaſt, unleſs he would have ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd the other Side, which would have been but the ſame thing. But we find the Duke of <hi>Savoy</hi> thought fit to ſtop their Proceedings by ſeveral Policies; one of which was, by ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering the poor Proteſtants, under the Command of Count <hi>Schomberg,</hi> to periſh with Hunger, the Remainder of which were forc'd to diſperſe in ſearch of Suſtenance, having not ſeen a morſel of Bread for eight days to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether. Thus we may ſee, that thoſe who have always aſſur'd us that the Duke of <hi>Savoy</hi> ſhuffl'd with the Allies, ſpoke true, as we have ſince found by experience. But what is more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable, is, that this Prince, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:101085:44"/>the many juggling Parts he has plaid, yet pretends to have done the <hi>League</hi> many conſiderable Services. Theſe his Miniſters endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to explain, by perſwading us, that their Maſter's chief Aim was all along a General Peace. But after all has been ſaid, I leave to any rational Man to judge, if the Allies would do prudently to depend any farther upon ſuch a Mediator. But let us proceed to what follows, that we may know what they and their Maſter were able to do, had they been but rightly diſpos'd.</p>
            <p>We have juſt now obſerv'd, That his Royal Highneſs found means to ſtop the Progreſs of the Arms of the Allies; but we forgot to add, how he manag'd his own Troops, and thoſe of the Emperour commanded by his Generals, who acted all along in Confederacy with <hi>Catinat,</hi> in a Pare repugnant to all the Rules of good Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licy, and which was extremely ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claim'd againſt by Mareſchal <hi>Schom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berg,</hi> but to no purpoſe. This was to lay all in Blood and Aſhes, and make more Ravage and Havock in leſs than
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:101085:45"/>three Months, than the <hi>Tartars</hi> and <hi>Turks</hi> do in many Campagns together by their Incurſions. This Conduct of his was directly contrary to that of Count <hi>Schomberg,</hi> whoſe Method was to conquer rather by Goodneſs and Clemency, than Rigour and Cruelty; by which means he drew to his Army an infinite number of People from all Provinces of <hi>France,</hi> and might have perform'd ſomething very conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, had they not been baſely pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented. But here the Proteſtants, not being able to conceive the Duke enter'd <hi>France</hi> out of any kindneſs to them, when they ſaw him burn their Houſes, and plunder their Goods, by which he reduc'd 'em all to Beggary and Miſery, ſoon forſook his Army, joyn'd the Militia againſt him, and from Friends became irreconcilable Enemies to the Allies.</p>
            <p>Another Practice of the Duke's up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the like Occaſion, broke all the Meaſures of Monſieur <hi>Schomberg,</hi> which was to march towards the <hi>Rhone,</hi> and approach the <hi>Sevenes,</hi> with deſign to fortifie himſelf there all the Winter, and by thoſe means kindle an
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:101085:45"/>an inteſtine War, which would infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libly have been fatal to <hi>France.</hi> This Affair was concerted with a great deal of Prudence, and afterwards put in practiſe, one would think, with as much Caution, tho' it prov'd quite to the contrary: For Monſieur <hi>Schomberg</hi> having ſent ſeveral Officers, diſguis'd like Peaſants, among the Malecon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents, got a Promiſe from 'em, That they would rife the firſt opportunity; which Secret he immediately entruſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the Duke of <hi>Savoy,</hi> who almoſt as ſoon reveal'd it to the Court of <hi>France;</hi> ſo that when it was expected the Proteſtants ſhould be up in Arms, they were all of a ſudden clapp'd up and ſecur'd, and this by reaſon his Royal Highneſs had ſent their Names to the <hi>French</hi> King.</p>
            <p>Monſieur <hi>Chanlais</hi> was at the Court of <hi>Turin,</hi> with no other Deſign than to penetrate into thoſe of the Allies, which his Royal Highneſs communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated to him: And when Complaints were made to that Prince for ſuffering ſuch a ſuſpected Man near him, he anſwer'd, That he was ſent from the <hi>French</hi> King to make him Propoſals
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:101085:46"/>towards an Accommodation, which he had always rejected as injurious to his Honour, and the ſincere deſire he ever had to remain ſtrictly united to the moſt Serene Allies; and by this Sham he eluded the juſt Suſpicions that were entertain'd of his foul Play. In fine, his Highneſs was ſo indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent about the Deſign of penetrating into the Heart of <hi>France,</hi> that Count <hi>Schomberg</hi> and the Officers of his Party did openly complain of it: But his Highneſs had a mind to ſacrifice, is it were out of a Frolick, the Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt of the Allies; and was well e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough pleas'd, provided he might follow the Directions of the Court of <hi>France;</hi> that being all the Advantage he aim'd at in this great Expedition, ſince which things always went worſe and worſe.</p>
            <p>When the Allies entred <hi>Dauphine,</hi> and poſſeſt themſelves of <hi>Guilliſtre,</hi> they made there 2500 <hi>Iriſhmen</hi> Priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners. What did his Highneſs do with them? He ſent them to <hi>Piedmont,</hi> and a great part of them made their eſcape by the way, thro' his own Orders, and return'd into <hi>France:</hi>
               <pb n="79" facs="tcp:101085:46"/>The reſt of them were ſent to the Blockade before <hi>Caſal.</hi> All the World knows what care <hi>France</hi> had taken to ſend Proviſions into that Place, which was reduc'd to great Straits for want of them. The <hi>Iriſh</hi> being now before <hi>Caſal,</hi> and the General that comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the Blockade being a good <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voyard,</hi> he ſuffer'd them to go into the Place, according to the ſecret Orders he had from his Highneſs; ſo that <hi>France</hi> got ſtill ſome Advantage by her ſeeming Loſſes. At the Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>render of <hi>Caſal,</hi> it was articl'd. That all the Cannon ſhould be carried away. This was put in execution: But what did his Highneſs do with it? He remov'd it from <hi>Caſal,</hi> to ſend it to <hi>Pignerol.</hi> Several Pieces of that Artillery having been ſtopt by the Confederate Troops, who ſaw them file off towards <hi>Pignerol,</hi> his Highneſs ſent preſently Orders to let them go; and by night thoſe Pieces were car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried to a certain Poſt within three Hours March of <hi>Pignerol,</hi> where the <hi>French</hi> came to fetch them. More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over, the Generals of the Auxiliary Troops knew very well that the Siege
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:101085:47"/>of Caſal was never undertaken with his Highneſs's Conſent; and if after much Debate, that Siege was at laſt reſolv'd upon, 'twas becauſe it was obſerv'd that his Highneſs's Deſign was only to amuſe a great part of the Confederate Troops with a Blockade, leſt they ſhould be employ'd elſewhere againſt <hi>France,</hi> whoſe Intereſt he has favour'd all along.</p>
            <p>We may alſo relate in this place, as an undeniable Proof of his High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs's juggling with <hi>France,</hi> the fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent Indiſpoſitions he pretended when any thing was to be done a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt that Crown. Upon theſe Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions he was benumb d and frozen, always ſick, there was nothing ready, he wanted all things, he had no Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, becauſe he was not paid, ſaid his Miniſters. But his private Treaty with the <hi>French</hi> King is ſcarce conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, but he preſently takes off his perfidious Mask: Then he is all Fire, full of Courage and Bravery; he is in perfect Health; in ſhort, there's nothing wanting to beſiege <hi>Valance:</hi> He is the firſt in viewing the Works, and encouraging the <hi>French</hi> Soldiers
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:101085:47"/>by his own Example: He confers with Monſieur <hi>Catinat</hi> about the Means of poſſeſſing himſelf of all the <hi>Milaneſe,</hi> and putting all the neighbouring States under Contributi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and does more, in ſome meaſure, againſt the Allies in leſs than ſix Weeks time, than he had done againſt <hi>France</hi> during ſix Campagns of open War. Was there ever ſuch a foul, diſſembling, tricking Conduct as this is?</p>
            <p>Let us proceed to the Bombarding of <hi>Pignerol.</hi> The Emperour and King of <hi>Great Britain</hi> had ſeveral times writ to his Highneſs to lay Siege to that important Fortreſs, both for his private Intereſt, and the Honour of the Confederates: And in order to it, they had taken care to provide him with all Neceſſaries for that Expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. But his Highneſs ſtill juggling with the <hi>French</hi> King, trick'd the moſt Serene Allies upon this occaſion, as he had done upon all other; and changes the Project of a Siege, una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimouſly reſolv'd upon by all the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerals, into a pitiful Bombardment: For the greateſt part of the Bombs
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:101085:48"/>being full of Sand, burſt in the Air, without any effect; and his Highneſs's Engineers did not underſtand one another, becauſe Orders were ill given. In ſhort, this Enteprize miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carried, as others had done, becauſe the leaſt of the Court of <hi>Turn</hi>'s, Thoughts were to make any Conqueſt upon <hi>France.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In fine, we may add to all theſe Tranſactions, the premeditated De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign of his Royal Highneſs's Generals, of deſtroying all the Proteſtants that ſerv'd in his Army, without excepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, by expoſing them to inevitable Danger, as they did at the Battel of <hi>Stafarde,</hi> and in all other Rencounters. What paſs'd in the Camp of <hi>Dement</hi> is ſtill an undeniable Proof of it; witneſs the Complaints that were made to his Highneſs by the Marqueſs of <hi>Montauban</hi> and the Baron of <hi>Bearn.</hi> That Prince's Indifference in an Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fair of the greateſt conſequence, made him ſtill excuſe his Generals, and lay the blame upon thoſe whoſe only aim was to maintain the Intereſt of the Allies, and vindicate the injur'd Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of the King of <hi>England,</hi> by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincing
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:101085:48"/>vincing his Highneſs by Authentick Proofs and undeniable matter of Fact, that his Generals betray'd him, and favour'd the Deſigns of Mareſchal <hi>de Catinat,</hi> by the ſecret Intelligence they had with him. But his Highneſs was ſo far from diſowning the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct of his Generals, that he rather authoriz'd it, ſince they did nothing without his Conſent and private Orders.</p>
            <p>The Marqueſs of <hi>Montauban</hi> and the Baron of <hi>Bearn,</hi> who have given ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Proofs of their Bravery upon all Occaſions, took theſe Treacheries ſo much to heart, that they were at laſt forc'd to engage in a Quarrel, which had been of ſad Conſequence to the Marqueſs of <hi>Bagnaſque,</hi> had that General had Courage enough to have decided the Controverſie by the Sword, when he was challeng'd from the Marqueſs of <hi>Montauban,</hi> by the Baron of <hi>Bearn,</hi> who brought him the Parole of Honour.</p>
            <p>We ſhall briefly relate what paſs'd upon this Occaſion; both becauſe 'tis a curious Story that will ſerve to make the World perfectly acquainted with the <hi>Genius</hi> of the Court of <hi>Turin,</hi> and
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:101085:49"/>and the Cowardiſe of his Highneſs's Generals; and at the ſame time to make the <hi>Eulogy</hi> of the Conduct of the Marqueſs of <hi>Montauban,</hi> and the Baron of <hi>Bearn,</hi> the full of which was Colonel of a Regiment of Proteſtants, and the other Major of a <hi>Brigade.</hi> The glorious Proofs theſe two Officers have given of their Merit, have gain'd them much Reputation in <hi>Italy;</hi> and the Bravery of the Baron of <hi>Bearn,</hi> who is born of an illuſtrious Family in <hi>France,</hi> has upon this Occaſion juſtly deſerv'd the Applauſes of all the Offices of the Auxiliary Troops of the Confederates; the Particulars of which are as follows.</p>
            <p>The Marqueſs of <hi>Bagnaſque,</hi> chief Favourite to the Duke of <hi>Savoy,</hi> and firſt General of his Forces, reſolv'd by his Highneſs's Conſent to rid himſelf of all the Proteſtants; and having try'd ſeveral ways to deſtroy them, which prov'd all ineffectual, through the Prudence and Wiſdom of their Commanders, endeavour'd at laſt to put his deteſtable Deſign in Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, by ſeparating them from the reſt of the Army. This happen'd at the
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:101085:49"/>Camp of <hi>Demont,</hi> where the innocent Blood of ſo many brave Men was to be ſpilt by as barbarous and cruel a Slaughter as ever was the Bloody Maſſacre of St. <hi>Bartholomew.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The only Regiments of Proteſtants that were then in the Army, were thoſe of <hi>Lillemarais</hi> and <hi>Montauban,</hi> commanded by the Marqueſs of <hi>Montauban.</hi> Theſe two Regiments were therefore ſeparated from the reſt of his Highneſs's Troops, by the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of General <hi>Bagnaſque,</hi> to their great Surprize and Aſtoniſhment at a thing ſo unuſual and barbarous. The Night being over, the Officers of thoſe Regiments perceiv'd at Break of Day General <hi>Bagnaſque,</hi> at the Head of fourſcore Officers, making towards them with their Piſtols ready cock'd in their Hands. They were follow'd by a great Detatchment of choice Men to ſupport them. <hi>Bagnaſque</hi> went preſently up to Monſieur <hi>de Montau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ban,</hi> with deſign to ſhoot him, which was to be a Signal for his Highneſs's Troops, who were in order of Battle, to make a Diſcharge upon the two Regiments of Proteſtants. But the
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:101085:50"/>Marqueſs of <hi>Montauban</hi>'s Prudence ſecur'd the Lives of his Men; becauſe inſtead of making any Show of ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon his Defence, which was all that General <hi>Bagnaſque</hi> deſir'd, the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to excuſe himſelf and colour his Treachery, he was contented open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to proteſt againſt the Violence done him, and ſaid he would make his Complaints to the Duke of <hi>Savoy,</hi> and to his Maſter the King of Great <hi>Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain;</hi> adding, that this was a Violati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Right of Nations, and an Abuſe offer'd to the Honour of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, of which he would be revenged.</p>
            <p>General <hi>Bagnaſque</hi> who thought the Proteſtants would have fir'd upon his Men, was quite out of Countenance by this unexpected Conduct, and return'd to his Army mad with the Sting of the Diſappointment. The Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſs of <hi>Montaubau</hi> highly reſented this Violence, and the abuſive Language <hi>Bagnaſque</hi> gave him, to provoke him to make Reſiſtance, which he could not do at that time, without ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing his Men to he cruelly ſlaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter'd at the firſt Diſcharge, ſince <hi>Bag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſque</hi>'s Party was above 100 to one:
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:101085:50"/>Therefore he prudently diſſembl'd his Reſentment for the preſent, expecting a favourable Opportunity to be reveng'd.</p>
            <p>The Marqueſs of <hi>Montauban</hi> being come to the Court of <hi>Turin,</hi> made his Complaints to his Royal High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and gave him the Particulars of the Treachery and Barbarity of his General. The Duke of <hi>Savoy</hi> was ſo far from eſpouſing the Quarrel of op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs d Innocence, that on the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry he excus'd <hi>Bagnaſque,</hi> and made appear, in the Sequel of this Affair, that he authoriz'd all that his Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral had done; to the great Diſſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of all the Officers of the Auxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liary Troops, who highly commend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Marqueſs of <hi>Montauban</hi>'s Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence upon this Occaſion.</p>
            <p>The Marqueſs of <hi>Montauban</hi> reſolv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at laſt to revenge the Abuſe offer'd him, by his own Sword, and challenge General <hi>Bagnaſque.</hi> He could not put this <hi>Deſign</hi> in Execution as long as he was in the Service; becauſe <hi>Bagnaſque</hi> commanded in chief under his Royal Highneſs all the Auxiliary Troops. Having conſulted with ſeveral Officers of Merit, his Friends, he at laſt took the
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:101085:51"/>Reſolution to lay down his Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and went immediately to his Highneſs to make him a Compliment, and take his Leave of him, pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Deſign of retiring into <hi>Holland.</hi> After this firſt Step, he ſtaid ſome Days in <hi>Turin,</hi> in order to challenge General <hi>Bagnaſque;</hi> who having a Hint given him of it, his Cowardiſe made him keep within doors; and by this Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caution baffl'd the Vigilance of the Marqueſs of <hi>Montauban,</hi> and broke his Meaſures. In the mean time he had taken his Leave of the Duke of <hi>Savoy;</hi> and the Fear of being arreſted, if his Deſign ſhould be diſcover'd to his Highneſs, made him uſe a Stratagem, both to get <hi>Bagnaſque</hi> out of his Houſe, and ſecure himſelf againſt being ſurpriz'd. In order to that, he applied himſelf to the Baron of <hi>Bearn,</hi> and concerted with him what he ought to do in his Abſence.</p>
            <p>The Baron of <hi>Bearn,</hi> who always made it a Point of Honour to lay hold of any Opportunity, where either he can ſerve a Friend, or ſignalize his Courage, took readily upon him this
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:101085:51"/>Negotiation, which requir'd no leſs Prudence than Secreſie to bring it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout, as will appear in the Sequel of this Diſcourſe.</p>
            <p>Eight Days were paſt after the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſs of <hi>Montauban</hi>'s Departure, before the Baron of <hi>Bearn</hi> could put his De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign in Execution; becauſe General <hi>Bagnaſque</hi> kept ſtill within doors. At laſt his Spies came to tell him one Morning, that <hi>Bagnaſque</hi> deſign'd to go to Maſs, and that his Coach was ready at his Door. The Baron of <hi>Bearn</hi> without loſing time, went ſtrait to that General's Houſe; and being come into the Court, he ſaw <hi>Bagnaſque</hi> in his Coach. The Baron of <hi>Bearn</hi> kept at a diſtance, for fear of inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupting the Converſation of a Lady that was then at the Boot ſpeaking to the General.</p>
            <p>Aſſoon as the Lady was gone, he came near the Coach, open'd the Boot, and deſir'd the General <hi>Bagnaſque</hi> to oblige him ſo far as to come out of his Coach for a Moment, and go to a Corner of his Court, having ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to communicate to him. <hi>Bag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſque</hi> came out of the Coach, leaning
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:101085:52"/>on the Baron of <hi>Bearn</hi>'s Hand; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he was troubl'd with the Gout; and going a little aſide, the Baron of <hi>Bearn</hi> ſpoke to him thus: <hi>Sir, I have the more willingly took upon me a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion the Marqueſs of</hi> Montauban <hi>has given me, becauſe he has to do with a Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon whoſe Virtue and Merit equal the great Reputation he has in the World He has deſir d me to tell you, that he expects Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction for the Abuſes offer'd him in the Camp of</hi> Demont, <hi>at the Head of the Troops of the King of</hi> England. <hi>And for that purpoſe he leaves to you to appoint the time, to chooſe your own Arms, the Number of thoſe that are to fight, and the way of Fighting, either on Foot or on Horſeback; and only reſerves to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf the Choice of the Place, which muſt be out of his Royal Highneſs's Dominions; becauſe he has took his leave of him; and diſires he ſhould know nothing of it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Marqueſs of <hi>Bagnaſque</hi> extreme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſurpriz'd at this unexpected Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliment, anſwer'd with his natural Haughtineſs; <hi>Monſieur</hi> de Montauban <hi>will not fight, I am ſure: He'll never come to the Place. Sir,</hi> return d the Baron of <hi>Bearn, I bring you the Parole of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:101085:52"/>from the Marqueſs of</hi> Montauban, <hi>and I will anſwer for it. Surely he will never fight,</hi> reply'd General <hi>Bagnaſque</hi> in a higher Tone; <hi>and if Monſieur</hi> de Montauban <hi>thinks himſelf injur'd, let him demand Satisfaction himſelf. Sir,</hi> return'd the Baron, <hi>Such Words do not only wrong thoſe that ſend theſe fort of Compliments, but offend at the ſame time the Honour of thoſe that make them.</hi> And clapping his Hand to his Sword, he told the General, <hi>Sir, You muſt reſolve quickly; for I ſhall not leave you till I have a poſitive Anſwer; And if you wo'nt have to do with the Marqueſs of</hi> Montauban, <hi>you muſt have to do with me.</hi> To this the Marqueſs of <hi>Bagnaſque</hi> anſwer'd to the Baron, <hi>Sir, I will fight with Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtols on Herſeback: As for the Place, I cannot appoint it at preſent. But Sir,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply'd the Baron, <hi>The Marqueſs of</hi> Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tauban <hi>being out of his Highneſs's Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, I muſt go and give him an Account of what I have done. Sir,</hi> return'd <hi>Bagnaſque, I will write you word about it where<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ver you are.</hi> By this time they perceiv'd Monſieur <hi>Chamouſſet,</hi> Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our of the Citadel of <hi>Turin,</hi> who came to ſee General <hi>Bagnaſque;</hi> and the
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:101085:53"/>Baron of <hi>Bearn</hi> told the General, <hi>Sir, let as talk of other Things, and keep this Affair ſecret among our ſelves.</hi> They preſently chang'd their Diſcourſe, and Monſieur <hi>Chamouſſet</hi> being come up to them, they talkt about the new Arms that were to be given to the King of <hi>England</hi>'s Troops next Campagn, and other indifferent Things.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Bagnaſque</hi> having took Coach again, the Baron of <hi>Bearn</hi> ſtaid ſo long with <hi>Chamouſſet</hi> till the General was gone a good way the Street, for fear he ſhould tell him what had paſs'd be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt them: And immediately after the Baron took Poſt: to acquaint the Marqueſs of <hi>Montanban</hi> with his Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotiation, expecting a Letter from General <hi>Bagnaſque</hi> about the Place of Aſſignation. The Baron of <hi>Bearn</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing inform'd from <hi>Turin,</hi> that <hi>Bag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſque,</hi> in ſtead of being as good as his Word, had been ſo imprudent as to make this Affair publick; and that, upon his acquainting his Wife with it, ſhe had had a Miſcarriage; and that theſe Reports were ſpread all over <hi>Turin,</hi> and even come to his Highneſs's Ears; was ſo incens'd againſt <hi>Bag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſque,</hi>
               <pb n="93" facs="tcp:101085:53"/>that he reſolv'd to return <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cognito</hi> to <hi>Turin,</hi> to force him to keep his Promiſe.</p>
            <p>You muſt know, that after the Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron of <hi>Bearn</hi>'s departure, <hi>Bagnaſque</hi> had ſent for all his Relations, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving acquainted them with what had paſt, they conſulted together how to ſecure the Reputation of the General, and baffle the Purſuits of Meſſieurs <hi>de Montauban</hi> and <hi>de Bearn.</hi> After a long Conference, they thought it conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to ſend to Monſieur <hi>Duprè,</hi> a Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonel in the Imperial Troops, to know of him whether in <hi>Germany</hi> an Infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rior Officer, who thought himſelf in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jur'd by his General, had right to Challenge him? Colonel <hi>Duprà,</hi> who is an old Officer, told them, he had, provided the offended Officer took his time, when the General was not at the Head of the Troops under his Command. Theſe Gentlemen report<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to Monſieur <hi>de Bagnaſque</hi> and his Relations, Monſieur <hi>Dupre</hi>'s Anſwer, which was not ſatisfactory, becauſe they did not tell <hi>Duprè</hi> who the Chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge had been ſent to, thinking the Colonel would have expreſt himſelf
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:101085:54"/>quite mother way, upon conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Monſieur <hi>Bagnaſque</hi>'s Quality; ſo that they were ſent back to Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur <hi>Dupré,</hi> with a Charge to give him the Particulars of the whole Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fair, and tell him the Names of thoſe that had made the Challenge, and him the Challenge was made to.</p>
            <p>Colonel <hi>Dupré</hi> was at that time in his Chamber, troubled with the Gout, and ſitting in an Arm-Chair. His Lieutenant-Colonel and ſeveral other Officers were come to make him a Viſit, when <hi>Bagnaſque</hi>'s Relations en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred the Room, and ſaid aloud before all the Company, That when they ask'd Monſieur <hi>Dupré</hi>'s Advice, they had forgot to acquaint him, that the Challenge in queſtion was ſent to <hi>Bagnaſque</hi> by the Baron of <hi>Bearn,</hi> from the Marquis of <hi>Montauban.</hi> Monſieur <hi>Dupré</hi> made anſwer, That thoſe Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen were Men of Quality, Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and Merit; and beſides, that being in a Service different from that of the General's, the time of his Command being over, they had right to demand Satisfaction by the Sword, of the Injuries that had been offer'd
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:101085:54"/>them. The Lieutenant-Colonel back'd his Sentiments, and ſaid, That it was the common Practice in <hi>Germany,</hi> and almoſt every where elſe; That Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieurs <hi>de Montauban</hi> and <hi>de Bearn</hi> were brave and honourable Officers in the Army, and that Monſieur <hi>de Bagnaſque</hi> ought not to refuſe them the Satisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction they demanded of him.</p>
            <p>The Baron of <hi>Bearn</hi> finding by all theſe Proceedings, that General <hi>Bag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſque</hi> made a Fool of him, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign'd to ſhuffle off his Promiſe, bent his Thoughts upon the Means of en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tring <hi>Turin</hi> without being known; which was no eaſie matter, becauſe the Guards were doubled at the City-Gates, and no Perſon admitted in, without being firſt examin'd. In or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to this Deſign, he put on a Livery, and under that Diſguiſe baffl'd the Vigilance of the Guards, and went <hi>incognito</hi> to a Jew-Merchant, who liv'd four Houſes from that of Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral <hi>Bagnaſque</hi>'s, where he ſtaid, wait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for the General's going out. And as his Window look'd into the Court of <hi>Bagnaſque</hi>'s Houſe, one Morning having perceiv'd his Coach at the
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:101085:55"/>Door, he got himſelf ready, and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd a Sergeant of <hi>Montauban</hi>'s Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, who had accompanied him diſguis'd under a Peaſant's Habit, to obſerve all that paſs'd, and that in caſe the General's Men came to their Maſter's Relief, he ſhould draw upon them and fight them.</p>
            <p>General <hi>Bagnaſque</hi> having took Coach at his Door, went into the Street; when the Baron of <hi>Bearn</hi> ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king ſtrait up to him, and ſtriking the Horſes with his Cane, ſtopt them ſhort, open'd the Boot, and thruſt himſelf into the Coach. The Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral was in the greateſt Surprize ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginable at the ſight of the Baron of <hi>Bearn: Sir,</hi> ſaid the Baron to him, <hi>I expect you ſhall make good your Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe; our Affair is now publick, and one of us is no Man of Honour.</hi> At that, he took <hi>Bagnaſque</hi> by the Arm, to get him out of the Coach, and force him to draw. That General having open'd his Coat, told him, <hi>Sir, I will fight with Piſtols on Horſe-back. We muſt have Seconds, and Judges of the Combate. I ll fight Monſieur</hi> de Montauban; <hi>and as for you, Sir, I have a very gailant
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:101085:55"/>Gentleman, who will find you ſufficient Play. Sir,</hi> (reply'd the Baron of <hi>Bearn</hi>) <hi>I am glad you take care of your own Security: When the Gentleman you deſign for me, ſhall have any Buſineſs with me, I am confident it will never injure his Reputation. In the mean time, what Day do you appoint for the Perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of your Promiſe? Sir,</hi> (anſwer'd General <hi>Bagnaſque</hi>) <hi>Count</hi> Serval <hi>my Nephew is going to be married; the Wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding will be kept at</hi> Verceil: <hi>I am to be at it, and for that purpoſe I'll ſet out from this Place on Twelfth-day Eve, and the next day I'll be at</hi> Verceil, <hi>where we'll fight. You may depend upon it, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint the Marqueſs of</hi> Montauban <hi>with it, that he may be ready againſt that Time.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Baron of <hi>Bearn</hi> took his leave of General <hi>Bagnaſque,</hi> and having be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore-hand hir'd Poſt-horſes at the three Gates of the City, he mounted the firſt that he could come at, and went to <hi>Carignan</hi> thro' a By-way, for fear of being ſurpriz'd; for about half an Hour after his departure, <hi>Bag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſque</hi> order'd the Gates of the City to be ſhut, in order to arreſt him, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:101085:56"/>to his Highneſs's Command. Several Horſemen were immediately ſent up and down the Countrey; but the Baron of <hi>Bearn</hi> baited but one moment at <hi>Carignan,</hi> and went Poſt to <hi>Milan,</hi> where the Marqueſs of <hi>Montauban</hi> ſtaid for him. At his ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rival he gave him the Particulars of this ſecond Challenge.</p>
            <p>Theſe two Gentlemen had now no other Thoughts than to get their Arms ready againſt the appointed day; and becauſe Monſieur <hi>de Bag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſque</hi> had demanded Judges of the Fight, they pitch'd upon Colonel <hi>Beetſleer,</hi> a <hi>Griſon</hi> by Birth, who was in the Service of the King of <hi>Spain.</hi> They could not chuſe a Perſon of greater Merit, nor one that Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral <hi>Bagnaſque</hi> ought to be leſs jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous of. Colonel <hi>Beetſleer</hi> accepted of their Propoſal like a Gentleman: He told them, he would not only be a Spectator of the Fight, but alſo ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count it an Honour to draw his Sword in their Quarrel. They return'd him their Thanks, and deſir'd him only to do them the Honour to be preſent as Judge of the Fight, which he very generouſly granted.</p>
            <pb n="99" facs="tcp:101085:56"/>
            <p>One day the Baron of <hi>Bearn</hi> going out of Monſieur <hi>Beetſleer</hi>'s Houſe, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd the Marqueſs <hi>Daix,</hi> Lieutenant in the Guards of his Royal Highneſs, who was come Poſt from <hi>Turin.</hi> He went preſently to the Marqueſs of <hi>Montauban,</hi> to confer with him about what they had to do: For the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſs <hi>Daix</hi> had brought Orders, which his Royal Highneſs had obtain'd from Monſieur <hi>de Leganez</hi> Governor of the <hi>Milaneſe,</hi> who hapned to be then at <hi>Turin,</hi> to arreſt them: And while the Marqueſs <hi>Daix</hi> enquired for the Houſe of Monſieur <hi>Louvigny,</hi> who command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in <hi>Milan</hi> in the abſence of Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur <hi>de Leganez,</hi> to put his Orders in execution, Meſſieurs <hi>de Montauban</hi> and <hi>de Bearn,</hi> having firſt diſcours'd with Colonel <hi>Beetſleer,</hi> reſolv'd to take Poſt, and leave <hi>Milan</hi> with all expedition.</p>
            <p>To put the change upon the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſs <hi>Daix,</hi> and baffle the Deſign of his Journey, they hir'd a Calaſh, which they gave to their Servants, ordering them to go before, and make as if they deſign'd for <hi>Caſal;</hi> but to come to meet them at <hi>Verceil</hi> by ſome by-way or other. The Marqueſs <hi>Daix</hi> being
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:101085:57"/>deluded by this Artifice, went Poſt to <hi>Caſal,</hi> with deſign to prevail with the Governor of that Place to arreſt them there. In the mean time the Marqueſs of <hi>Montauban</hi> and the Baron of <hi>Bearn,</hi> having deſir'd Colonel <hi>Beetſleer</hi> to follow them, repair'd to the Borough of <hi>Verceil,</hi> the Place of Aſſignation. They arriv'd there ſeven days before, and ſtaid till ſeven days after the time appointed by Monſieur <hi>Bag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſque:</hi> But that General broke his Promiſe, and never came to the Place. Meſſieurs <hi>de Montaubon</hi> and <hi>de Bearn</hi> entred an Act of their Appearance and Stay, and took Certificates of the Parſon and Magiſtrates of the Place; and ſeeing all their Endeavours were eluded by the Cowardiſe of Monſieur <hi>de Bagnaſque,</hi> the Marqueſs of <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tauban</hi> reſolv'd at laſt to go for <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and the Baron of <hi>Bearn</hi> to return to <hi>Turin,</hi> with deſign to fight <hi>Bagnaſque</hi> where-ever he could meet him, and revenge the Contempt, and Breach of his Promiſe.</p>
            <p>It is to be obſerved by the By, That if Meſſieurs <hi>de Montauban</hi> and <hi>de Bearn</hi> had been arreſted at <hi>Milan</hi> by
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:101085:57"/>the Marqueſs <hi>Daix, Bagnaſque,</hi> to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure his Honour, had reſolv'd to go to the appointed Place, whilſt his Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions would have given out in <hi>Turin,</hi> That Meſſieurs <hi>de Montauban</hi> and <hi>de Bearn</hi> were Cowards, who had broke the Appointment. At laſt <hi>Bagnaſque</hi>'s Friends, conſidering that the General was not ſafe, and that the Baron of <hi>Bearn,</hi> who had ſtopt him in his own Coach in the middle of <hi>Turin,</hi> would ſooner or later ſurpriſe him a third time, thought it convenient to uſe all means to make away with ſo dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous an Enemy; and for that purpoſe, they gave Two hundred Piſtols to Ten or Twelve Soldiers to murder him.</p>
            <p>Some of theſe villanous Wretches having communicated their deteſtable Deſign to ſome of their Comerades of the Regiment of <hi>Montauban,</hi> theſe gave Information of it to their Officers, who preſently notified it to the Baron of <hi>Bearn.</hi> The Hatred and Reſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>Bagnaſque</hi> did not ſtop here: The Marqueſſes of <hi>Pianeſe, Caral, Tane,</hi> and <hi>Perella,</hi> all four related to that Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral, had ſeveral Conferences upon that Affair. The Safety of <hi>Bagnaſque</hi>'s
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:101085:58"/>Perſon, (who beſides the great Places he had both in the Army and at Court, was alſo his Royal Highneſs's Favourite) was ſo dear to them, that they us'd all their Endeavours with his Royal Highneſs to get an Order to put <hi>Bagnaſque</hi> under arreſt; both to make his Family eaſie, and break the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns of the Baron of <hi>Bearn,</hi> who would have attack'd him where-ever he could have met him.</p>
            <p>His Royal Highneſs eſpous'd the Quarrel of his General ſo warmly, that he prevail'd with my Lord <hi>Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loway</hi> to deprive the Baron of all his Employments, notwithſtanding the Remonſtrances of Monſieur <hi>Lilemarais,</hi> who wrote to his Lordſhip, that Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers could not be carried to that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremity, without doing him the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Injuſtice in the World; ſince the Baron of <hi>Bearn</hi> was acknowledg'd by all the Army to be a brave Officer, who always had diſcharg'd his Duty with Honour, and who, beſides that, was diſtinguiſh'd by his Quality, as being extracted from one of the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſt Families in <hi>France.</hi> But all this was to no purpoſe; for <hi>Bagnaſque</hi>'s
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:101085:58"/>Cowardiſe, and the great Intereſt he had at Court, ſtill prevail'd upon all other Conſiderations.</p>
            <p>However, his Royal Highneſs be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſatisfied of the Valour and Merit of the Baron of <hi>Bearn,</hi> reſolv'd at laſt to deſire my Lord <hi>Galloway</hi> to make him advantageous Offers from him, upon condition that he would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce the Marqueſs of <hi>Montauban</hi>'s Intereſt, and forget what had paſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween him and General <hi>Bagnaſque.</hi> The Baron of <hi>Bearn</hi> anſwer'd, That he acted not in this Affair out of any private Intereſt, but only becauſe the Honour of the King of <hi>England</hi> was at ſtake, ſince General <hi>Bagnaſque</hi> had abus'd his Troops, and their Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Marqueſs of <hi>Montauban;</hi> and that for his part, he had rather ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice all his Employments, than aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don his Friend's Cauſe.</p>
            <p>My Lord <hi>Galloway</hi> order'd him, by his Royal Highneſs's Command, to be under Arreſt, and told him, That the preſent Juncture of Affairs exacted from him that Complaiſance for his Royal Highneſs. The Baron of <hi>Bearn</hi> proteſted againſt the Injuſtice done
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:101085:59"/>him, and put himſelf under the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection of the Confederate Princes. Monſieur <hi>de Varennes</hi> General of the Troops of <hi>Brandenburgh,</hi> Monſieur <hi>Vander-Meer</hi> Miniſter of the States, and ſeveral other Men of Note, being now concern'd in this Affair, my Lord <hi>Galloway</hi> prevail'd with his High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to have the Baron of <hi>Bearn</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leas'd from his Confinement. Thus being at liberty, he at laſt left <hi>Turin,</hi> and went into <hi>Holland,</hi> to give His Majeſty of <hi>Great Britain</hi> an Account of all that had paſt in this Affair. Before his departure, his Highneſs de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſir'd my Lord <hi>Galloway</hi> to offer him a Regiment, if he would go and ſerve the <hi>Venetians;</hi> and upon his refuſal, he offer'd him Money, and Letters of Recommendation to the King of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi> He anſwer'd, That he return'd his Royal Highneſs Thanks for the Offers made him upon ſo hard Terms; That if my Lord <hi>Galloway</hi> was pleas'd to give him Letters for his <hi>Britannick</hi> Majeſty, he would gladly accept of them; but as for thoſe of his High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, he had no occaſion for them; and that the only Favour he expected
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:101085:59"/>from him, was to order the Payment of the Arrears due to him. The Duke of <hi>Savoy</hi> ſeeing that all theſe Offers were not able to ſhake his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution, or make him betray his Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, ſpoke no more about that Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fair. Only my Lord <hi>Galloway</hi> and Monſieur <hi>Vander-Meer</hi> gave him Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters; the firſt, for the King; and the other, for the States of the United Provinces.</p>
            <p>You have in this ſhort Hiſtory a faithful Picture of the Miniſters of the Court of <hi>Savoy,</hi> of the Genius and Inclinations of his Highneſs's Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerals; and in fine, of the ſhuffling Conduct of that Prince with reſpect to the Troops of the Allies. We ſay nothing here but what is notoriouſly known; and if we would recount all the Treacheries we have ſeen with our own Eyes, we ſhould ſwell up this Diſcourſe to a great Volume. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, we would have the World know, that it was not for want of his High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs's Endeavours, if all the Confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Troops were not ſacrific'd to the <hi>French;</hi> and that nothing but the Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence and Wiſdom of the Generals
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:101085:60"/>that commanded them, has ſav'd them from his premeditated Deſigns of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroying them.</p>
            <p>After that, I leave to the Confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates to judge, whether, at this time, they ought to look upon the Duke of <hi>Savoy</hi> as a well-affected Prince, who never had ought but the Intereſt of the Confederacy in proſpect, as his Miniſters are pleas'd to inſinuate it; or as a ſworn and irreconcileable Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, the more dangerous, in that he has been acquainted with all that paſs'd in the Cloſet of the Confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Princes, both to ſerve his own Ends, and thoſe of the Common Enemy.</p>
            <p>Cautions may be us'd againſt the Surprizes of an open and declar'd Enemy; but 'tis a very hard matter to prevent being cheated by a Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate Prince, who proclaims his Friendſhip and the Sincerity of his Intentions in all the Courts of <hi>Europe,</hi> by his flattering Miniſters; and who, at the bottom, is no better than a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembling Shuffler. Honeſty is now a days a Cloke for every Body; and the greateſt Cheats in the World are
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:101085:60"/>ſtill induſtriouſly careful to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted Honeſt. I confeſs, 'tis im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible to read any Man's Thoughts: But however, one might have known by all the Actions of the Duke of <hi>Savoy,</hi> and the repeated Informations that have been given to the Confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates, that he kept Intelligence with <hi>France:</hi> Yet at this very time there are ſome People that can hardly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve it; which is much the ſame thing, as if a Man ſhould firſt ſhut his Eyes, and then maintain, that it is Night at Noon-day. This pernicious Supineneſs and Careleſneſs is now the Cauſe of the ill Diſpoſitions towards the Concluſion of a General Peace.</p>
            <p>Haughty and ambitious <hi>France</hi> fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies to have done much, by winning over the Duke of <hi>Savoy</hi> to her Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt: She hopes by that to ſhake the Conſtancy of the other Princes, draw off ſome of the weakeſt by the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of his Royal Highneſs, offering them great Advantages; and after ſhe has engag'd theſe, ſhe reckons upon the Diviſion of the Heads of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federacy, who will at laſt grow weary of a War that does but exhauſt their
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:101085:61"/>Riches. But we may aſſure the <hi>French</hi> Council, that they are in a mighty Errour in this Point, and that they entertain themſelves with empty chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merical Hopes, ſince the Heads of the Confeder<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cy who have ſupply'd the Duke of <hi>Savoy</hi> with all the Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſaries for the Diversion he promis'd to make, but did not perform, are fully reſolv'd to take ſuch Meaſures for the future, as never to be cheated again by any of their Allies; and beſides, never to make a Peace with <hi>France,</hi> but upon ſuch Terms as they have agreed amongſt themſelves: And whatever <hi>France</hi> may imagine, they ſhall not want for Money: Two or three Campagns more do not ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie much; and then we may ſee who ſhall have the better on't. <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>Tis enough we are very well inform'd of the For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of that Crown, and what ſhe's able to do, being ſo exhauſted as ſhe is, and having left no Stone unturn'd to procure a Peace. The only thing the Confederates ſeem now to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd for, is the Perfidiouſneſs of the Duke of <hi>Savoy,</hi> who has moſt baſely betray'd them; this they take more
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:101085:61"/>to heart, than all the imaginary Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages <hi>France</hi> expects to draw from it.</p>
            <p>By all this we may ſafely conclude, that when the Duke of <hi>Savoy</hi> entred into the Alliance, he had no other Aim in proſpect, than to favour the Deſigns of <hi>France,</hi> under the ſpecious Pretence of ſome Diſcontents againſt that Crown. The Mask is now turn'd up; and we have evidently diſcover'd, that he has acted in combination with <hi>France</hi> during all the War of <hi>Italy.</hi> Now theſe are the Fruits which the <hi>French</hi> King and Duke of <hi>Savoy</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected to reap from their ſecret In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligence. Firſt, The Duke of <hi>Savoy</hi> hop'd to get conſiderably, by empty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Purſes of ſo many Allies who muſt have recourſe to him, to get an eaſie Paſſage into <hi>France,</hi> and by that means effect as much in one Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagn, as could be perform'd in the Proceſs of a long War. The <hi>French</hi> King likewiſe thought it no leſs for his advantage, than the Duke his Confederate; becauſe this Prince cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out for Help, the Confederates would be ſure to ſend him a great
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:101085:62"/>number of Auxiliaries, with vaſt Sums of Money, to maintain and keep up a Diverſion, which was look'd upon as the only way to bring <hi>France</hi> to rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable Terms; and theſe were as many Enemies from which the <hi>French</hi> King freed himſelf in <hi>Flanders</hi> and <hi>Germany,</hi> while Monſieur <hi>de Catinat,</hi> his General, kept them at a Bay with a Handful of Men, who had never been able to ſtand before them, had not the Duke of <hi>Savoy</hi> juggl'd with him.</p>
            <p>The <hi>French</hi> King cunningly improving the Diverſion he oblig'd the Confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates to make in <hi>Italy</hi> through the Duke of <hi>Savoy</hi>'s means, purſu'd his Conqueſts in <hi>Flanders</hi> and on the <hi>Rhine.</hi> He won Battels, and took ſtrong Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, under the Conduct of the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſchals of <hi>Luxemburg</hi> and <hi>de Lorge,</hi> to whom he always ſent the Choice of his Men, whereas he only gave Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur <hi>Catinat</hi> new-rais'd raw Soldiers, or <hi>Iriſhmen,</hi> becauſe he went upon ſure grounds, and that this was ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to entertain a War on that Side.</p>
            <p>Another great Reaſon prevail'd with the <hi>French</hi> King, which extreme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:101085:62"/>favour'd his Deſigns towards the Ruine of the other Confederate Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; and which was never found out, till the Ill was grown paſt Remedy. This was, that the Duke of <hi>Savoy</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring himſelf for the Confederates, and at the ſame time keeping his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligence with <hi>France,</hi> the Miniſters of the Duke would be ſtill welcome in all the Courts of the Alli'd Princes, and that under colour of a Common Concern, he would be made privy to all the Secrets, and be acquainted with their ſtrong and weak Side, which he would diſcover to the <hi>French</hi> King. 'Tis for that reaſon that the Duke of <hi>Savoy</hi> ſent none but choice Wits (and moſt of them <hi>Jeſuits,</hi> as being the moſt ſubtle and intriguing) to reſide with the Confederate Princes. Thoſe Miniſters have extreamly well diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charg'd their Duty; for it has been obſerv'd, that every Poſt the Court of <hi>France</hi> had certain and preciſe Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations of all that paſs'd in the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs, in the Councils of War, and all other Conſultations. Hence it is, that the <hi>French</hi> King and his Generals were always upon their Guard; and
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:101085:63"/>whatever the Allies undertook, the <hi>French</hi> expected them behind good Retrenchments, provided with all Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſaries to make their Deſigns miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carry.</p>
            <p>To this alſo ought to be imputed the inconſiderable Succeſſes of the Bombardments, and other Enterpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of the Confederate Fleet upon the <hi>French</hi> Coaſts: For the Preſident <hi>de la Tour,</hi> who reſided at the Court of <hi>England</hi> during the Winter, never came back but to acquaint the Duke his Maſter (as this did the <hi>French</hi> King) with all the Deſigns that were to be put in execution the next Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagn.</p>
            <p>There's ſtill another Reaſon that has much contributed to induce the Duke of <hi>Savoy</hi> to play <hi>Jack of Both Sides</hi> during this War; which is, That his Dominions being very poor, and ſeveral of his Subjects forc'd thro' Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity to beg their Bread in moſt Countries of <hi>Europe,</hi> he hop'd by the War of <hi>Italy</hi> to draw with the Auxili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ary Troops of the Confederates, a great part of their Moneys: Which indeed has made his People very rich,
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:101085:63"/>and fill'd his Coffers ſo, that at this time he may be ſaid to be one of the richeſt Princes of <hi>Chriſtendom</hi> in ready Caſh. This Money was not all got by the Confederates; <hi>France</hi> has alſo brought in her Share, ſince 'tis her Gold only that has dazzl'd this Prince and his Miniſters. But the <hi>French</hi> King little cares how much he gives, ſo he may compaſs his Ends, and gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie his Ambition. That Monarch expreſs'd his Thoughts very plainly about that Matter: For being one day at dinner when News was brought him that the Treaty was at laſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded with the Duke of <hi>Savoy,</hi> he ſaid before all the Company, <hi>That the Peace of</hi> Italy <hi>had coſt him dear; but he was ſure a general Peace would make him amends for all the Sums he had disburs'd.</hi> Theſe Words need neither Explana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion nor Comment; therefore let's return to our Subject.</p>
            <p>When the Duke of <hi>Savoy</hi> declar'd for the Allies againſt <hi>France,</hi> he hop'd to reap by it an Advantage no leſs conſiderable than all the reſt, ſince it nearly concerns his Honour and pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Intereſt. For ſince the Death of
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:101085:64"/>his Predeceſſor <hi>Charles Emanuel</hi> II. he had liv'd an obſcure retir'd Life, that little became a Sovereign Prince, who takes Place among Crown'd Heads, altho' his Revenues be in no manner anſwerable to that high Dignity. Therefore it was now high time for him to make himſelf talk'd of in the World, to illuſtrate his Reign by ſome great Action, and eternize his Memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry by ſome ſurprizing Event. His Temper and Inclinations did naturally lead him to it: For, to give every one his Due, he is a Man of Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, and wants nothing that can make a great Warrior. All theſe Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons prompted him to take upon him that Part which we have ſeen him act ever ſince the beginning of the War. By this means he deſign'd to make his Friendſhip and Alliance courted by all the Princes in <hi>Europe,</hi> and become, as it were, the Umpire and Arbitrator of the General Peace.</p>
            <p>Another thing which the Duke of <hi>Savoy</hi> aim'd at, was to lay ſuch great Obligations upon <hi>France,</hi> (at a Jun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture when ſhe was expos'd to a World of Enemies, that had conſpir'd her
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:101085:64"/>Ruin) as would engage the <hi>French</hi> King not to treat him as a Pety Prince, as he did before, and to have more Regard and Eſteem for him for the future. As for the <hi>French</hi> King, beſides the Advantages he deſign'd to draw from his Royal Highneſs's Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret Alliance, which was to bring the Confederates to a General Peace, he has ſtill had another Artifice in proſpect, which neither the Duke nor his Council ever thought of, and which will prove fatal to his Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions and Liberty. For by engaging him to ſide with the Allies, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tray them afterwards, he draws upon him their irreconcilable Hatred: And the Confederates have all the Reaſon in the World to treat him for the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture as an ambidextrous Shuffler, and refuſe him their Aſſiſtance, when <hi>France,</hi> after a Peace is concluded, ſhall go to ſtrip him of his Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, as ſhe did the Duke of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> and ſeveral other Princes who had done her almoſt the like Services.</p>
            <p>It is not the firſt time that the Dukes of <hi>Savoy</hi> have loſt their Dominions, as appears by the Quarrels which
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:101085:65"/>
               <hi>Charles Emanuel,</hi> Grandfather to his Royal Highneſs had with King <hi>Henry</hi> III. and <hi>Henry</hi> IV. of <hi>France. Henry</hi> III. being in War againſt a powerful League, <hi>Charles Emanuel</hi> did much the ſame as <hi>Victor Amedeus</hi> his Succeſſor has done in our Days. Me entertain'd great Hopes of enlarging his Fortune if he ſhould improve that Opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, to declare himſelf againſt <hi>France;</hi> and accordingly in the Year 1588, he joyn'd his Arms to thoſe of the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of <hi>Henry</hi> III. and having formed a powerful Party, of which he made himſelf Chief, he entred <hi>Provence,</hi> ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priz'd the Cities of <hi>Marſeilles</hi> and <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les;</hi> and was ſo puff'd up with theſe Succeſſes, that he coin'd a Medal to eternize his Memory; where he was repreſented under the Emblem of a <hi>Centaurus</hi> trampling upon a Crown, with this <hi>Motto, OPPORTUNE, Seaſonably;</hi> meaning that he could not have a more ſeaſonable Opportunity to hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <hi>France.</hi> He paid dear for this <hi>Bravado;</hi> for in the Year 1600, <hi>Henry</hi> IV. having pacify'd the Trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles and Commotions that diſtracted <hi>France,</hi> and had given Occaſion to
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:101085:65"/>
               <hi>Charles Emanuel</hi> to form great De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns againſt that Crown, reſolv'd to be reveng'd of him; and having bent the Streſs of the War towards <hi>Italy,</hi> made himſelf Maſter of the greateſt Part of <hi>Savoy</hi> and <hi>Piedmont.</hi> And to be even with the Duke, he coin'd a Medal, where he was ſeen in the Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure of <hi>Hercules</hi> beating down with his Club the proud <hi>Centaurus,</hi> with this <hi>Latin Motto, OPPORTUNIUS;</hi> that is, <hi>More Seaſonably and Succeſſfully.</hi> Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Conqueſt of <hi>Savoy</hi> and <hi>Pied<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mont, Henry</hi> IV. at the Entreaty of Pope <hi>Clement</hi> VIII. was at laſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail'd upon to be reconcil'd with the diſtreſs'd Duke; tho' it was the Opinion of all the Politicians of thoſe Times, that <hi>Henry</hi> IV. ought to have kept <hi>Savoy</hi> and <hi>Piedmont,</hi> both to chaſtize the inconſiderate Raſhneſs of that Prince, and have a free and open Way to enter <hi>Italy</hi> whenever he pleas'd. This is the Advice that Cardinal <hi>d'Oſſat,</hi> one of the greateſt Stateſmen in thoſe Days gave <hi>Henry</hi> IV. But upon this Occaſion that Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch ſhew'd more Generoſity than Policy, and reſtor'd <hi>Charles Emanuel</hi> to all his Dominions.</p>
            <pb n="118" facs="tcp:101085:66"/>
            <p>One might now very well ask <hi>Victor Amedeus</hi> II. who broke with <hi>France</hi> in a Conjuncture of time, much like that when <hi>Charles Emanuel</hi> declar'd himſelf againſt <hi>Henry</hi> III. that is, when all <hi>Europe</hi> arm'd againſt her, and attack'd her on the four Corners of the Kingdom. One might, I ſay, ask that Prince, who is now at laſt recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil'd with the <hi>French</hi> King, through the Mediation of the Pope and the other Princes of <hi>Italy,</hi> what Security <hi>France</hi> gives him to put his Dominions out of Danger? Will not the <hi>French</hi> King after a general Peace is concluded, have the faireſt Opportunity in the World to ſtrip him of them? Shall he want Pretences for that Purpoſe? And is not the Duke of <hi>Savoy</hi>'s Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct at the firſt Breaking out of the War of <hi>Italy</hi> a ſufficient one, ſince he alone has carried the Fire-brand of War into <hi>France</hi> by the Irruption into <hi>Dauphine?</hi> All theſe Proceedings will furniſh new Matter of Diſcord and Diviſion, which in time will kindle a greater Fire, and revive the old Pretenſions of the <hi>French</hi> King to the Dukedom of <hi>Savoy,</hi> Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pality
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:101085:66"/>of <hi>Piedmont,</hi> and County of <hi>Nice.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Savoy</hi> was annex'd to the Crown of <hi>France,</hi> about twelve hundred Years ago. This happen'd in the Reign of King <hi>Clovis,</hi> who got it by way of Conqueſt from <hi>Gundebald</hi> King of <hi>Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gundy;</hi> becauſe this Prince had embrac'd the Party of <hi>Alaric</hi> King of the <hi>Goths,</hi> who wag'd War againſt <hi>France, Clovis</hi> incens'd againſt <hi>Gundebald,</hi> turn'd him out of his Dominions, and reduc'd him to live on a ſmall Penſion the reſt of his Life. This unfortunate Prince being dead, his Dominions fell for ever to the Crown of <hi>France</hi> by the Deceaſe of <hi>Clotildis,</hi> Siſter to <hi>Gundebald,</hi> and Wife to <hi>Clovis,</hi> to whom they belong'd by Legal Right after her Brother's Death. So that this Princeſs dying without Iſſue, they were appropriated to the Crown of <hi>France,</hi> although <hi>Savoy</hi> had ſeveral times been given by way of Appen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age to the ſecond and third Sons, till the Emperour <hi>Charles the Bald</hi> preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Bozon,</hi> Count of <hi>Arles</hi> with the anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Kingdom of <hi>Burgundy,</hi> to which he joyn'd <hi>Savoy</hi> to be holden for ever by
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:101085:67"/>by Fealty and Homage from the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour of <hi>Germany.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Kingom of <hi>Arles</hi> was of no long Duration, and had but four or five Kings, the laſt of which named <hi>Rodol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phus,</hi> being dead without Iſſue, <hi>Hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert</hi> of <hi>Morienne,</hi> who then was Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour of <hi>Savoy,</hi> was veſted with it by the Emperour <hi>Conradus the Salick.</hi> He was ſucceeded by <hi>Amedeus</hi> his Son, from whom is deriv'd the preſent Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily of <hi>Savoy;</hi> which is the more il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſtrious and ancient, becauſe <hi>Hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert</hi> was deſcended from the Dukes of <hi>Saxony.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>However the Crown of <hi>France</hi> main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains now-a-days, that the veſting of thoſe Dominions had no legal Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation: Firſt, becauſe the Empire ought to return hereditarily to the Houſe of <hi>France,</hi> after the Deceaſe of <hi>Charles the Burley,</hi> the laſt Emperour of the <hi>Carlovingian</hi> Race, upon whom <hi>Conradus the Salick</hi> had uſurp'd it. Beſides this, <hi>France</hi> produces another Title to <hi>Savoy;</hi> which is, that it was annex'd to it a long time before the Erection of the Empire; and therefore ought now to be accounted a part of its Demeſnes.
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:101085:67"/>To all theſe Claims to <hi>Savoy, France</hi> adds ſtill a new one; which is deriv'd from <hi>Louiſe</hi> of <hi>Savoy</hi> Mother to <hi>Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis</hi> I. King of <hi>France,</hi> and Daughter to <hi>Philip</hi> VII. Duke of <hi>Savoy;</hi> who at his Marriage with <hi>Margaret</hi> of <hi>Bourbon,</hi> had ſtipulated that their Children ſhould ſucceed one another in the Dutchy and all its Dependencies.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Philip</hi> had two Children by <hi>Marga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret,</hi> viz. <hi>Philibert</hi> and <hi>Louiſe; Philibert</hi> being dead, <hi>Louiſe</hi> his Siſter claim'd the Succeſſion; but becauſe there was ſtill two Male-Children by a ſecond Marriage, <hi>viz. Charles</hi> and the Duke of <hi>Nemours,</hi> who by the Prerogative of their Sex ſet up their Title to the Dutchy, <hi>Louiſe</hi> was poſtpon'd, and <hi>Charles</hi> made himſelf Maſter of <hi>Savoy,</hi> with the Conſent of the States of the Country. After all theſe ſeveral in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtine Quarrels, <hi>Savoy</hi> was again di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbed by the War <hi>Francis</hi> I. made in <hi>Italy.</hi> This Prince having entred that Dutchy with a formidable Army, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duc'd it to his Obedience in a very little time. The Conqueſt of the Principality of <hi>Piedmont</hi> and County of <hi>Nice</hi> ſoon follow'd that of <hi>Savoy;</hi>
               <pb n="122" facs="tcp:101085:68"/>all which coſt <hi>Francis</hi> I. but one Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagn. By this means <hi>Charles</hi> was en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirely diſpoſſeſs'd of his Dominions, and had not one Foot of Ground left him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Francis</hi> I. and <hi>Henry</hi> II. his Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor, were Maſters of them for about twenty four Years; that is, till the Peace of <hi>Chateau</hi> in <hi>Cambreſis</hi> was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded in 1559, whereby King <hi>Henry</hi> yielded to <hi>Spain</hi> above 400 Towns and 198 Gariſon'd Fortreſſes, among which were compris'd all thoſe of <hi>Savoy</hi> and <hi>Piedmont,</hi> except <hi>Turin, Viniers, Ville<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neuve, Aſt, Chevas</hi> and <hi>Pignerol,</hi> which <hi>Charles</hi> IX. and <hi>Henry</hi> III. at laſt reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to the Duke.</p>
            <p>However, as it is moſt certain that the <hi>French</hi> King never ſtints his Preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, nor regards the Treaties made by his Predeceſſors, he will be ſure to revive in due time the Title he has to <hi>Savoy;</hi> which is like to be as ſoon as a general Peace is concluded. So that the preſent Duke of <hi>Savoy</hi> may be ſaid to be like thoſe that are born to be unhappy: For he never moves a Step to favour the Deſigns of <hi>France,</hi> but he draws towards the Brink of a Precipice.</p>
            <pb n="123" facs="tcp:101085:68"/>
            <p>Several Reaſons engage the <hi>French</hi> King to ſet up anew his Title to <hi>Savoy</hi> as ſoon as a general Peace is concluded. Firſt or all, the new Right he gets by the Marriage of the young Dutcheſs of <hi>Savoy,</hi> the Duke's eldeſt Daughter, with the Duke of <hi>Burgundy;</hi> becauſe in caſe the Iſſue Male fail, that Princeſs becomes preſumptive Heir of all the Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of <hi>Victor Amedeus</hi> II. her Father. And 'tis certain the Court of <hi>France</hi> did much depend upon that, although its Miniſters have endeavour'd to give another Turn to the Eagerneſs the <hi>French</hi> King has ſhew'd in courting the Duke. 'Tis a Truth acknowledg'd by all Politicians, that the chief way the <hi>French</hi> King has us'd to enlarge his Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions, has always been by Marriages, ſince he ſeldom or never concluded a Treaty of Peace, but he had a Prince or a Princeſs of the Blood to beſtow upon his Enemies, in order to make them ſubſervient to his Deſigns. But as ſoon as the Deferences and Reſpects uſually paid to new-married People, are over, <hi>France</hi> always ſpeaks to another Tune, and will have her own at any rate.
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:101085:69"/>So that the Duke of <hi>Savoy</hi> may take his Meaſures accordingly: And I will be a falſe Prophet, if the Match he has lately concluded with the Duke of <hi>Burgundy</hi> do not prove fatal to his Liberty, and the Tranquillity of his Dominions. The ſecond Reaſon that will induce the <hi>French</hi> King to pick a Quarrel with the Duke of <hi>Savoy,</hi> is, that he never forgives Injuries that are offer'd him; and if he ſeems now to court and flatter him, 'tis only to draw him the better to the Trap he lays for him. 'Tis certain the <hi>French</hi> King will never pardon his declaring himſelf againſt him, and taking up Arms to favour the Deſigns of his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies: And the firſt Buſineſs of this Monarch's Revenge, will be to enſlave him. All the Submiſſions his Royal Highneſs will then uſe, ſuch as to go to <hi>France</hi> in Perſon (as did the Doge of <hi>Genoa</hi> ſome Years ago) to expreſs his Sorrow for embracing the Confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racy; all theſe reſpectful Steps, I ſay, will ſerve but to encreaſe the Contempt <hi>France</hi> has for a Prince that can do her no Hurt.</p>
            <pb n="125" facs="tcp:101085:69"/>
            <p>The third Motive that will engage <hi>France</hi> not to have any regard for the Duke of <hi>Savoy</hi> after the Concluſion of a general Peace, is the great Paſſion ſhe ever had to have no other Bounda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries than the <hi>Alps</hi> on the Side of <hi>Italy.</hi> Therefore we ought to look upon the Reſtitution of the important Place and Fortreſs of <hi>Pignerol</hi> as a fallacious <hi>Chimera,</hi> and a Decoy of the <hi>French</hi> King's to bring the Duke of <hi>Savoy</hi> to a Negotiation of Peace; well know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that this Prince being once diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arm'd, and depriv'd of all the Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies of the Confederates, it will bean eaſie matter to make him ſubmit to what Terms he pleaſes. So that his Highneſs's Safety did entirely depend upon the Support of the Confederate Princes.</p>
            <p>Having briefly related the ſeveral Claims of the <hi>French</hi> King to <hi>Savoy,</hi> and the ſeveral Motives, which will infallibly induce him to revive them as ſoon as he is rid of all his Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies; we ſhall now ſpeak to the Wrong his Royal Highneſs has done the Allies, after they have been ſo kind to him as to ſhare with him, the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:101085:70"/>of bringing to reaſonable Terms a Monarch, who from the beginning of his Reign has meditated the Sla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very of all <hi>Europe.</hi> But what makes the Duke of <hi>Savoy</hi>'s Conduct the more inexcuſable, is, that by undoing himſelf, he had a mind to involve all the Confederates in the ſame Ruin, and blaſt, as it were in one Moment ail the Fruits that were to be gathered from nine Campaigns, which have coſt the Allied Princes the Blood of their moſt faithful Subjects, and their own Toils and Labours, not to men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion the vaſt Treaſure that has been ſpent to maintain and carry on the War.</p>
            <p>The Duke of <hi>Savoy</hi>'s late Conduct in putting himſelf at the Head of a <hi>French</hi> Army, to haſten the Reduction of <hi>Valence</hi> (which had been follow'd by the entire Conqueſt of the <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laneſe</hi>) is but too plain a Proof of what he aims at; and of the ſecret Corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpondence he has had all along with <hi>France,</hi> in order to betray the Allies: To which may be added, his being ſo buſie in haſtening the Emperour and King of <hi>Spain</hi> to accept of a Neu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trality,
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:101085:70"/>without giving the Negotia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>s Time to conſider of and exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine ſo important an Affair, ſo that his only end was to force all the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies to agree to the general Peace, which <hi>France</hi> courts with ſo much Impatience, and which ſhe had never brought about if it had not been for Duke of <hi>Savoy.</hi> 'Tis upon that Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count that the <hi>French</hi> King has had ſo much regard for the Court of <hi>Turin;</hi> becauſe he had been long acquainted with the <hi>Genius</hi> and weak Side of his Royal Highneſs, which is to be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirely governed by Intereſt.</p>
            <p>Therefore we muſt not wonder if the Gold of <hi>France</hi> has been more powerful with the Duke of <hi>Savoy</hi> than the Honour he would have got by ſtanding it out at a Juncture of Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs, which would infallibly have ruin'd <hi>France,</hi> and procur'd great Advantages to all the Confederates, not to ſpeak of a ſolid and laſting Peace that would have enſued. I do not doubt but the <hi>French</hi> King's In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trigues have been favour'd upon this Occaſion, by the unanimous Concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of the Princes of <hi>Italy.</hi> The
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:101085:71"/>War in that Country fill'd them with Fears and Jealouſies, and kept 'em extremely ſubject, by reaſon of the Contributions they were oblig'd to pay to the Auxiliary Troops. This Conſtraint, and the other Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orders which are the inſeparable At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendants of War, have engag'd 'em to join their Inſtances with the ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt Endeavours of the <hi>French</hi> King, and all together have undoubtedly much contributed to make the Duke of <hi>Savoy</hi> take a courſe ſo directly oppoſite to his Intereſt.</p>
            <p>His Royal Highneſs's Miniſters do openly complain, that the Confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates have not perform'd what they promis'd to the Duke their Maſter; That he wanted Men and Money at a time when his Dominions lay expos'd as a Prey to a powerful Army incamp'd at the Gates of <hi>Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rin,</hi> with full Reſolution to bombard it, if the Duke did not preſently accept of the <hi>French</hi> King's Offers: That his Highneſs having conſider'd the imminent Danger of loſing all in one Moment, was forc'd to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer the Repoſe and Safety of his
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:101085:71"/>People to all the private Advantages he might have got by making a longer Reſiſtance; which amount to no more than the Honour of not forſaking a Party whoſe Intereſt it was to prolong the War, thereby to force the <hi>French</hi> King to make more advantagious Offers than thoſe he had already made: And that in this caſe his Highneſs wrongs himſelf more than the Confederates.</p>
            <p>To this we anſwer, That the Allies are very well inform'd of the true Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives that have prevail'd with his Highneſs upon this Occaſion, ſince all the Intrigue was juggl'd with the <hi>French</hi> King at our Lady of <hi>Loretto</hi>'s.</p>
            <p>This pious Journy of the Court of <hi>Turin,</hi> was only deſign'd to draw the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liminaries of a Treaty which his High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs &amp; his Miniſters have been ſo care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful of keeping ſecret from the Allies.</p>
            <p>'Tis well known, that his Highneſs thro' the Mediation of the Pope's <hi>Nuntio,</hi> and ſome Princes of <hi>Italy,</hi> enter'd into Articles with <hi>France,</hi> and agreed with the <hi>French</hi> King's Pleni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potentiaries upon all the Steps he was to make to cheat the Confederates.</p>
            <pb n="130" facs="tcp:101085:72"/>
            <p>According to this Project the <hi>French</hi> King promis'd to reinforce conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly his Army in <hi>Italy,</hi> to give Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders to Monſieur <hi>Catinat</hi> to be early in the Field, and prevent thereby the Arrival of the Auxiliary Troops which the Emperour and the other Confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Princes ſent to his Aſſiſtance: That Monſieur <hi>Catinat</hi> ſhould go and incamp before the Gates of <hi>Turin,</hi> threatning to bombard that capital City, and lay it in Aſhes in leſs than 24 Hours, unleſs his Highneſs pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented the impending Storm by a ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy Reconciliation with the <hi>French</hi> King upon the Terms he offer'd him. That by this means his Highneſs would be excus'd, and his Conduct ſeem leſs ſuſpicious and blameable to the Allies.</p>
            <p>It was no hard matter for the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerals that commanded the Auxiliary Troops of the Confederates in <hi>Italy</hi> to penetrate into the Deſigns of the Court of <hi>Turin,</hi> by reaſon of the little Care his Highneſs took of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king himſelf Maſter of ſuch Poſts as might have made Monſieur <hi>Catinat</hi>'s Deſigns miſcarry. On the contrary,
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:101085:72"/>one might have read his ſecret Joy in his Face: For he knew very well that there was nothing to be fear'd from the great Preparations of the <hi>French.</hi> Yet the better to colour his Play, he cauſed all the Ladies, and the Lords unfit for War, to go out of <hi>Turin.</hi> On the other ſide, it was given out in the <hi>French</hi> Army, that they only waited for the heavy Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non and Bomb-Waggons from <hi>Pigne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rol.</hi> But this Artillery and Ammuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was ſtill coming; and that Slow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, ſo unuſual with the <hi>French,</hi> eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially in important Expeditions, is an undeniable Proof that the Court of <hi>Turin</hi> juggl'd, and acted in Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bination with <hi>France,</hi> to baffle the Confederates. In the mean time the <hi>French</hi> King's Emiſſaries went to and fro from the Court of <hi>Turin</hi> to Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur <hi>Catinat;</hi> and all that to put the Change upon the Confederates, and cover the foul Play and Treachery of his Royal Highneſs.</p>
            <p>We ſhould never have dons, if we did relate all the Artifices that have been uſed to carry on this important Negotiation, which was look'd upon
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:101085:73"/>by <hi>France,</hi> as the great Wheel that is to ſet all the Springs going a towards a general Peace.</p>
            <p>Let's now come to the private Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty his Royal Highneſs has lately con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded. By that Treaty the <hi>French</hi> King promiſes him,</p>
            <list>
               <item>I. The Reſtitution of the important Fortreſs of <hi>Pignerol,</hi> upon condition that its Fortifications ſhall be razed at a general Peace.</item>
               <item>II. To give him four Millions of Livres in ready Mony, to be paid on the ſame Day the Treaty is rati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied.</item>
               <item>III. The Reſtitution of <hi>Nice, Mont<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>melian</hi> and other Places, conquer'd upon his Royal Highneſs by the Arms of the moſt Chriſtian King, from the beginning of the War to this preſent time.</item>
               <item>IV. To match the young Dutch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſs of <hi>Savoy,</hi> his eldeſt Daughter, with his Highneſs the Duke of <hi>Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gundy.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>V. That the Princeſs ſhall have Honours paid her as Dutch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſs of <hi>Burgundy,</hi> and in that Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity ſhall take place at the Court
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:101085:73"/>of <hi>France,</hi> of the Princeſſes of the Blood.</item>
               <item>VI. That upon the Confederates refuſing a Neutrality in <hi>Italy,</hi> his moſt Chriſtian Majeſty engages to join his Forces to thoſe of his Royal Highneſs towards the Conqueſt of the <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laneſe.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>VII. That after the Reduction of that Dutchy the moſt Chriſtian King ſhall put it into the Hands of his Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Highneſs, to enjoy it for ever, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out demanding any thing for the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pences of that Expedition, and to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure him in the Poſſeſſion of it, by protecting him againſt the Arms of the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>VIII. That he renounces for ever all the Rights and Claims which he and his Predeceſſors have had to the Duke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of <hi>Savoy,</hi> Principality of <hi>Pied<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mont,</hi> and County of <hi>Nice.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>IX. That in caſe the War continue in <hi>Italy</hi> by the Refuſal of the Neutra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, the moſt Chriſtian King will lend him his Forces for the Conqueſt of <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neva:</hi> That if the Neutrality be accepted, that Expedition ſhall be reſerv'd till after the general Peace.</item>
            </list>
            <pb n="134" facs="tcp:101085:74"/>
            <p>His Royal Highneſs, on his Part, promiſes to the <hi>French</hi> King,
<list>
                  <item>I. To renounce the Confederacy, and join himſelf for ever with the Crown of <hi>France:</hi> To act unanimouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with the Moſt Chriſtian King, in all that can make their Union laſting, and their Alliance inviolable for the future.</item>
                  <item>II. That he ſhall never give his Conſent to the Reſtoration of the <hi>Vaudois;</hi> and that he ſhall repeal all the Edicts by which he had lately granted them the free Exerciſe of their Religion, and their Return to the Valleys.</item>
                  <item>III. That he will uſe his Mediati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to bring the Allies to a General Peace.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Let us examine theſe Articles, and ſee whether his Royal Highneſs ought at this time to depend upon the Word of a Monarch who never ſcrupl'd to violate the Treaties he had concluded with the other Princes of <hi>Europe,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any Exception.</p>
            <p>We muſt conſider, in the firſt place, That when the <hi>French</hi> King conſents to reſtore <hi>Pignerol,</hi> he does as much
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:101085:74"/>as give the Key of his Kingdom (on the Side of the <hi>Alps</hi>) to keep, to the Duke of <hi>Savoy,</hi> and loſes for ever all the Advantages he had, by that im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portent Place, upon all the Princes of <hi>Italy.</hi> By that means he leaves the Province of <hi>Dauphinê</hi> expos'd to the Irruptions of his Enemies, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firms the ſtaggering Liberty of all the Princes beyond the <hi>Alps,</hi> who were before as it were bridled up by <hi>Caſal</hi> and <hi>Pignerol.</hi> To this we may add, That by that Reſtitution he ſacrifices all the Reſentments, which for ſome late Years have occaſion'd the Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rels he has had with the Court of <hi>Rome,</hi> during the <hi>Papacy</hi> of <hi>Innocent</hi> XI. with the Republick of <hi>Genoa,</hi> and ſome other States of <hi>Italy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If the <hi>French</hi> King be ſincere in the Reſtitution of <hi>Pignerol,</hi> the Duke of <hi>Savoy</hi> has all the reaſon in the World to be ſatisfied with the Generoſity of <hi>France,</hi> and not to grudge all the Complaiſance he has had for that Crown. And indeed,
'tis a great matter for his Highneſs to get ſo im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portent a Place as <hi>Pignerol.</hi> Beſides, the <hi>French</hi> King does not ſtay till he
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:101085:75"/>be compell'd to it by force of Arms: He makes this voluntary Preſent to his Royal Highneſs, even at a time when his Forces are ſo much ſuperiour in <hi>Italy,</hi> and that he is in a condition to ſtrip the Duke of all his Territories, by the taking of <hi>Turin,</hi> the Capital City of his Dominions.</p>
            <p>'Tis a great matter, I ſay, for the Duke of <hi>Savoy</hi> to get <hi>Pignerol:</hi> But after we have taken a View of what the <hi>French</hi> King gives to his Highneſs, let's ſee what he reſerves to himſelf. He conſents to the Reſtitution of <hi>Pig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerol,</hi> I grant it; but then this is to be at a General Peace, and after all its Fortifications are razed to the Ground. By theſe two Reſervations the <hi>French</hi> King plainly ſhews, Firſt, That what he aim'd at, was to engage the Duke of <hi>Savoy</hi> to uſe his utmoſt Endeavours to haſten a General Peace: Secondly, That when he reſtores this Place diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mantl'd, 'tis only with deſign to re-take it whenever he pleaſes: So that at beſt the Duke of <hi>Savoy</hi> is like to enjoy it but for ſome ſmall time; and perhaps Ten Months after the General Peace is concluded, the <hi>French</hi> King will
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:101085:75"/>order his Troops to clear the Place.</p>
            <p>To be convinc'd of this, we muſt obſerve, That in all Treaties of Peace, the <hi>French</hi> King never offers to reſtore any ſtrong Place, but on condition of razing the Fortifications; which ſhews his Double-dealing, his want of Sincerity, and his ſecret De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of making himſelf Maſter of them as ſoon as he has gain'd his preſent Ends, which are chiefly, to diſarm his Enemies, while he keeps on foot a numerous Army of well-diſciplin'd experience'd Soldiers, when the other Princes disband theirs. 'Tis well-known by experience, that <hi>France</hi> can raiſe again the Fortifications of a Place in very few Months, and that often with little Expence, becauſe he not only makes uſe of his own Soldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, but alſo of the Inhabitants of the Place, and their Money to boot: Witneſs the Fortifications of moſt of the Fortreſſes in <hi>Flanders,</hi> which have been built with the vaſt Sums that he got by Contributions. All that the <hi>French</hi> King provides for his Share, are Engineers, good Order, and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence; as for Materials and Money,
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:101085:76"/>the poor Inhabitant is always oblig'd to find them.</p>
            <p>This Conſideration makes the <hi>French</hi> King value ſo little the Reſtoration of a ſtrong Place, provided its Fortifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions be demoliſh'd, without which lie would never conſent to it. His End therefore in reſtoring <hi>Pignerol,</hi> was to caſt a Miſt before the Duke of <hi>Savoy</hi>'s Eyes, and decoy him to break all the Engagements he was enter'd into with the Confederates: But when he has brought his Deſigns about, he will retake it the more eaſily, becauſe its Fortifications will then be razed, which he ſhall never want either for Money, Men, or Materials to rebuild. Beſides, what uſe can the Duke of <hi>Savoy</hi> make of <hi>Pignerol,</hi> when diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mantl'd? Will that hinder the <hi>French</hi> King from having a free Paſſage to enter his Dominions upon the firſt Quarrel? Or, is his Country the more ſecure by it? Not at all: Therefore 'tis evidently plain, that the <hi>French</hi> has had no other Deſign than to delude the Duke of <hi>Savoy,</hi> and at the ſame time lay a Trap for the Confederates, the ſooner to bring them to treat of a General Peace.</p>
            <pb n="139" facs="tcp:101085:76"/>
            <p>After all, what does the <hi>French</hi> King give more to that Prince, than what he had already offer'd in the firſt Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſals of Peace he made to the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies? But the Deſign of the Confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates was to oblige <hi>France</hi> to ſurrender <hi>Pignerol</hi> into the Hands of the Duke of <hi>Savoy,</hi> in the Condition it was at that time, and would never hear of its being raz'd. Nevertheleſs, his Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Highneſs accepts of it as ſuch, and thinks it a good Bargain to get it in any Condition the <hi>French</hi> King is pleas'd to reſtore it to him. But he may judge by this firſt Step, of the Since<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the <hi>French</hi> King's Promiſes; and ſince that Monarch deludes him in this Article, he muſt expect no better in all the reſt. Therefore he loſes more by abandoning the Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deracy, than he gets by entring into a Private Treaty, to the prejudice of his own Intereſt, and the Contempt of ſo many Princes, who had never hearken'd to a Peace, without procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to him the Reſtitution of all his Places, with new Advantages, which would have ſecur'd for ever his Repoſe and Liberty, render'd his Condition
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:101085:77"/>more Honourable, and juſtifi'd his Conduct.</p>
            <p>Let's come to the Second Article. The <hi>French</hi> King promiſes to pay Four Millions of <hi>Livres</hi> upon the Ratifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Treaty. 'Tis likely the <hi>French</hi> King will be as good as his Word, as to thoſe Four Millions, let Money be never ſo ſcarce in <hi>France,</hi> as well as elſewhere, ſince this great Negotiation could never have been brought about without the <hi>Ready.</hi> The Reaſon of it is, that the Duke of <hi>Savoy</hi> is certainly the moſt covetous Prince in <hi>Europe;</hi> and that's the weak Side by which the Miniſters of <hi>France</hi> have crept into his Favour, and have been ſo much conſider'd at the Court of <hi>Turin.</hi> Thro' the means of their <hi>Louidors</hi> they have been made privy to the moſt ſecret Conſultations and Reſolves of the Cabinet-Council, and have at laſt brought things to that paſs they are now at. The <hi>French</hi> King little matters what he ſpends, provided he bring his Deſigns about. The firſt Rule of his Politicks is, to ſtick at no Coſt to triumph over his Enemies; and therefore he has been
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:101085:77"/>willing enough to part with thoſe Four Millions: 'Tis Money he has lent upon Uſury, of which he expects a <hi>Cent. per Cent.</hi> Intereſt. But it is now the Confederates Part to take their Meaſures accordingly, and look to their Private Intereſts. The <hi>French</hi> King, as we ſaid before, explain'd himſelf openly upon that Matter, and did not ſtick to ſay, <hi>That a General Peace will make him amends for the Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges he has been at for the Peace of</hi> Italy.</p>
            <p>But if nothing but Money could ſatisfie the Duke of <hi>Savoy,</hi> and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage him to be true to the Confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racy, I wonder he, or his Miniſters, did not give a Hint of it to the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies; for, I am ſure, they would have given him Satisfaction in an Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fair which was of ſo great conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence to them, and have attempted any thing that had appear'd poſſible, to give him more than ever <hi>France</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns or promis'd to give. To this, the <hi>French</hi> King's <hi>Partiſans</hi> will an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, That it was a very difficult matter for the Confederates to pay ſo great a Sum to the Duke, ſince there ſtill remains Four Millions five
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:101085:78"/>hundred thouſand <hi>Livres</hi> due to him. To which I reply, That theſe Arrears had long ſince been paid, had not his Highneſs's Conduct given ſufficient Reaſons to ſuſpect his juggling with <hi>France.</hi> The King of <hi>England</hi> has had ſeveral Informations of his Foul-play a long while ago; and if he did not take notice of it, 'tis becauſe it was hop'd he might by amicable Means be kept from a Deſign that will cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly be his Ruine.</p>
            <p>By the third Article the <hi>French</hi> King promiſes to reſtore to the Duke of <hi>Savoy, Nice, Montmelian,</hi> and in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral all the Places conquer'd during this War: which Reſtitution is the leaſt thing he could have expelled at a General Peace. But thoſe that have had a watchful Eye over his Highneſs's Conduct, do aſſure us, that <hi>Nice</hi> was yielded up to the <hi>French</hi> by his Orders; and that the Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of that Place, the better to co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver his Foul-play, found a way to blow up the Magazin, and ſpread at the ſame time a Report, That this was effected by the <hi>French</hi> Bombs; whereas it was nothing but the reſult
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:101085:78"/>of his Treachery, and of the ſecret Intelligence betwixt the <hi>French</hi> King and his Royal Highneſs.</p>
            <p>The Reduction of the important Fortreſs of <hi>Montmelian</hi> was owing to the ſame Deſtiny as that of <hi>Nice;</hi> and the <hi>French</hi> had never made them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves Maſters of it, but for the ſecret Orders his Highneſs gave to the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſs of <hi>Bagnaſque</hi> its Governour. The vigorous Reſiſtance of <hi>Coni</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd both his Highneſs and the <hi>French;</hi> and it muſt be wholly aſcrib'd to the Bravery of Monſieur <hi>Julien,</hi> and the <hi>French</hi> Proteſtants who defend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Place. 'Tis well known, that his Highneſs, to be reveng'd of it, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of recompenſing the Merit of ſo many gallant Men, who ſignaliz'd themſelves in the Defence of that Place, did, by an unheard-of Barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, keep them from the Preferments that fell to them of Courſe; which enrag'd Monſieur <hi>Julien,</hi> and ſome other Officers, to that degree, that they quitted his Highneſs's Service, and went over to that of <hi>France.</hi> The <hi>French</hi> King preſently made Monſieur <hi>Julien</hi> a Lieutenant-General, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanc'd
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:101085:79"/>the other Officers proportiona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly to their Merit.</p>
            <p>By what follow'd, it is plain, that his Highneſs's Deſign in abuſing thoſe Officers, was only to be rid of them, becauſe they were look'd upon at the Court of <hi>Turin</hi> as an Obſtacle that broke all the Meaſures the Duke of <hi>Savoy</hi> had taken with the <hi>French</hi> King. One may ſee, by all theſe Proceedings, how careful the Duke was to pleaſe the <hi>French</hi> King in all things, and to act in combination with him, to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe upon the Allies. This Conduct has conſtantly been obſerv'd in <hi>Italy</hi> during all the Campagns, from the beginning of the War to this preſent time: Therefore the ſmall Progreſs of the Confederate Forces is not to be wonder'd at, ſince the only thing his Royal Highneſs aim'd at, was to amuſe them, and favour the Deſigns of <hi>France</hi> by this Diverſion.</p>
            <p>There's all the Juſtice in the World for the <hi>French</hi> King to reſtore all the Places he has taken from the Duke of <hi>Savoy,</hi> ſince he did depoſite them in truſt into his Hands, till there was a Peace. The <hi>French</hi> King now keeps
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:101085:79"/>his Promiſe, and ſo far his Highneſs has reaſon to be ſatisfi'd. The Affairs have ſucceeded according to the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects they had concerted together; and the <hi>French</hi> King is mightily ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lig'd to the Duke for playing his part ſo well. But Time will ſhew whether his Highneſs ought always to have the ſame Thoughts of the <hi>French</hi> King's Honeſty, who has made him a Property upon this Occaſion, juſt as he formerly did Cardinal <hi>Furſtemberg,</hi> to compaſs his grand De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns, which are now a Riddle to the Court of <hi>Turin,</hi> but which will be accompliſh'd when the general Peace is concluded.</p>
            <p>To this we may add, that his Highneſs ought not to have been in ſuch haſte to conclude a private Treaty with <hi>France,</hi> upon Conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Advantages he gets by it. The moſt ſerene Allies would have procur'd to him the Reſtitution of all his Places; and <hi>France</hi> had already offer'd it to them: So that his High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs would have made a more Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Treaty, and contributed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides to the Concluſion of a ſolid
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:101085:80"/>and laſting general Peace, both for him and all the Confederates; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as by his late Proceedings he raiſes the Hopes of the common Enemy, violates his Promiſe and the Oaths he had ſworn to the Allies.</p>
            <p>Let us now proceed to the Marriage of the young Princeſs of <hi>Savoy</hi> with the Duke of <hi>Burgundy.</hi> This Match has dazzl'd the Duke of <hi>Savoy</hi> and his Miniſters, and ought to be look'd upon as the greateſt Artifice of the Council of <hi>France,</hi> to bring that Prince to a ſeparate Peace. And in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed it is much for a Prince of his Degree to have his Daughter mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried to the Duke of <hi>Burgundy,</hi> the firſt Son of <hi>France,</hi> and preſumptive Heir to the Crown, not to mention the Heroical Virtues that ſhine in that young Prince, to the Admiration of all the Court.</p>
            <p>According to the general Courſe of human Life, this young Duke is like to ſit one Day on the Throne. Nay, perhaps the Crown is reſerv'd for him, preferable to the <hi>Dolphin</hi> his Father: and therefore his Highneſs may reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nably flatter himſelf to ſee his Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Queen of <hi>France.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="147" facs="tcp:101085:80"/>
            <p>And here we muſt acknowledge the <hi>French</hi> King's Council to be compos'd of moſt wiſe and judici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Politicians; and admire how for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunate that Monarch is in all his Undertakings; and how skilful and ſubtle his Miniſters are in bringing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout their Negotiations.</p>
            <p>The Reſtitution of the Places taken from the Duke of <hi>Savoy,</hi> was too little to engage that Prince: And on the other hand, the <hi>French</hi> King could not without his Aſſiſtance make a Breach to the Union of the Confederate Princes, and thereby compaſs his Aim, which is a general Peace. Now what could they have offer'd him, that looks more glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, more fair, and more alluring than this Match? Nothing in the World. Several Millions of Money, and the other Advantages the <hi>French</hi> King propoſed to the Duke, had been ineffectual, and nothing leſs than this Alliance was ever able to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce him to ſacrifice the ſolemn En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagements he had with the moſt ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rene Allies.</p>
            <pb n="148" facs="tcp:101085:81"/>
            <p>
               <hi>France</hi> was ever happy in her Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liances; and 'tis to the Matches of the Princes and Princeſſes of the Blood into the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> and ſome other Princely Families of <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope,</hi> that ſhe owes that ſupreme De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of Grandeur and Power, at which we ſee her arriv'd in our Days: And on the contrary, 'tis by thoſe Matches that <hi>Spain</hi> is now in a declining Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition. This being firſt laid as a Principle, there's no queſtion but that the ſame Considerations have prevail'd with the <hi>French</hi> King to propoſe a Marriage between the Duke of <hi>Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gundy</hi> and his Highneſs's Daughter. For over and above the private Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages he hopes to get by it towards a general Peace, he has ſtill further Deſigns unknown to the Court of <hi>Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rin,</hi> which are undoubtedly to lay the Foundations of ſeveral new Pretenſions and Claims to the Dominions of his Royal Highneſs, which will be ſet up in due ſeaſon, in caſe the Duke ſhould die without Iſſue Male. It is his High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs's Miniſters Part to frame their Meaſures accordingly; and if they be at preſent <hi>French</hi> by Inclination,
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:101085:81"/>they may very well be ſo one Day by Duty. 'Tis to no purpoſe to alledge that the Court of <hi>Turin</hi> has obviated that Inconvenience, by cauſing the Duke of <hi>Burgundy</hi> to renounce the Succeſſion to the Duke of <hi>Savoy</hi>'s Dominions, in caſe of no Iſſue Male. The Experience of what paſs'd be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the <hi>French</hi> King and the late King of <hi>Spain</hi> on the Account of the Marriage of <hi>Maria Thereſa,</hi> does fully evince by the Quarrels that have kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dled the preſent War, how little one may depend upon ſuch Renunciations. The Kings of <hi>France</hi> ſeldom keep their Word after the Ratification of a Treaty; ſince we ſee the preſent <hi>French</hi> King has broke all the Oaths he made at his Marriage. 'Tis upon that ſcore that all the Princes of <hi>Europe</hi> have at this time undertook a War to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tect the Crown of <hi>Spain</hi> in her law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Rights, againſt the Attempts, U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurpations and double Dealing of the <hi>French</hi> King; and does not the Duke of <hi>Savoy</hi> expoſe himſelf by this Match to the ſame Quarrels, and the Danger of loſing his Dominions?</p>
            <pb n="150" facs="tcp:101085:82"/>
            <p>What could <hi>Spain</hi> do (in the weak Condition ſhe is now in) without the Support of the Confederate Princes? Had ſhe not been ſtript by this time of the beſt part of her Dominions? And when <hi>France</hi> ſhall attack the Duke of <hi>Savoy</hi> upon the ſame Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, will that Prince be able to reſiſt him with his own Forces? Muſt he not then call the moſt ſerene Allies to his Aſſiſtance, whoſe Intereſt he now baſely forſakes, in contempt of that Alliance he had ſo earneſtly courted?</p>
            <p>I am perſwaded, that if the Court of <hi>Turin</hi> had duly conſider'd the ſad Conſequences that may attend the Marriage of the young Princeſs of <hi>Savoy,</hi> his Royal Highneſs would not have been in ſuch haſte to conſent to it; ſince in all probability this Match will coſt him dear, and be fatal to his Liberty and the Repoſe of his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects. But rather he would have made it his Buſineſs to entertain the friendly Engagements he was in with the Allies, upon Conſideration of their powerful Protection, upon which he might have depended for preſent and future Advantages.</p>
            <pb n="151" facs="tcp:101085:82"/>
            <p>In fine, the <hi>French</hi> King, to make this Alliance look the more glorious and glittering to the Court of <hi>Turin,</hi> order'd the Honours due to a Dutcheſs of <hi>Burgundy,</hi> to be paid to the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs of <hi>Savoy</hi> at her Arrival at the Court of <hi>France.</hi> Yet before he went ſo far, he caus'd the Book of the Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies of the Crown to be turn'd over: And as it was found that the Daughter of <hi>Maximilian</hi> the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, had the Honours of <hi>Dolphineſs</hi> paid her in <hi>France,</hi> under the Reign of <hi>Lewis</hi> XI. tho' ſhe never had been ſuch; becauſe the ceremonial Book ſays in explicit Terms, that thoſe Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours were not paid to her as Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to the Emperour, but as <hi>Dolphi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> deſign'd: And ſo the Caſe being the ſame, the <hi>French</hi> King reſolv'd to look upon the Princeſs of <hi>Savoy</hi> as his Grand-daughter; and order'd that at her Arrival at the Bridge of <hi>Beauvoiſin,</hi> ſhe ſhould be receiv'd as ſuch; and that none but the Dutcheſs of <hi>Lude</hi> ſhould have the Privilege of ſitting before her.</p>
            <pb n="152" facs="tcp:101085:83"/>
            <p>We ſee by all this what mighty care the <hi>French</hi> King has taken to have this Marriage lik'd at the Court of <hi>Turin.</hi> The Princeſs of <hi>Savoy</hi> is far from being handſome: But the Duke of <hi>Burgundy</hi> is an accompliſh'd Prince. Aſſoon as the March was agreed upon, they preſented that Princeſs's Picture to the Duke, asking him how he did like her; <hi>She's handſome enough to give a Peace to Italy,</hi> return'd agreeably that young Prince. The <hi>French</hi> King and all the Court did extremely com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend this witty and judicious Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partee, which, by the by, was a tart Jeſt upon all the Artifices which <hi>France</hi> has us'd to draw off the Duke of <hi>Savoy</hi> from the Confederacy, and engage him to make a ſeparate Peace.</p>
            <p>'Twould be an endleſs Work nicely to examine the ſecret Springs which the <hi>French</hi> Council have ſet a going at the Courts of <hi>Rome,</hi> and of all the other Princes of <hi>Italy</hi> to bring this Negotiation about. There are no Tricks, no Fetches, that they have not employ'd; not to mention the vaſt Summs they have given to cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt his Royal Highneſs's Favourite
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:101085:83"/>Miniſters, who by their ſhameful A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>varice, have at laſt prevailed with him to conſent to an Alliance that will make him a Slave for ever, and coſt him the infallible Loſs of his Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions.</p>
            <p>It is provided by the ſixth Article, that in caſe the Allies do not agree to a Neutrality in <hi>Italy,</hi> the <hi>French</hi> King and the Duke of <hi>Savoy</hi> will joyn their Forces together in order to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer the <hi>Milaneſe:</hi> And this, on the Duke's part, is the higheſt Degree of Treachery imaginable. If that Prince had only been contented to forſake the Intereſt of the moſt ſerene Allies, and to receive under-hand thoſe Summs of Money that <hi>France</hi> has remitted to him, he might now in ſome mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure excuſe himſelf, by publishing to the World, that he could not refuſe the Advantageous Offers made to him without betraying his own Intereſt, and oppoſing his good Fortune.</p>
            <p>But his Royal Highneſs does not confine himſelf within thoſe Bounds; For with one Hand he receives Money of the Confederates, and with the other of <hi>France;</hi> and moreover
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:101085:84"/>plots and contrives with the common Enemy the Ruin of his beſt Friends and Allies; and makes his Market of their Liberty and his own. He puts him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf at the Head of the <hi>French</hi> Forces; and in the ſame Campagn is General of two powerful contrary Armies. Was there ever ſo ſingular, and at the ſame time ſo perfidious a Conduct as this is? But what can engage this Prince in this foul Play. That Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion is anſwer'd in this Article—, the Hopes of conquering the <hi>Mila<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſe.</hi> The <hi>French</hi> King tells him by his Miniſters, what Title he has to that Dutchy, which he looks upon as a Dependency from the Crown of <hi>France,</hi> upon the Account of the Marriage of <hi>Lowis</hi> of <hi>Orleans,</hi> Son to <hi>Charles</hi> V, King of <hi>France,</hi> with <hi>Valentina Galeas,</hi> Daughter to <hi>John Galeas</hi> Duke of <hi>Milan,</hi> who claim'd the Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion to that Dutchy by the Deceaſe of her two Brothers, who left no Iſſue.</p>
            <p>By this Artifice the <hi>French</hi> King has cunningly inſinuated himſelf into the Court of <hi>Turin;</hi> and while he enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains the Duke of <hi>Savoy</hi> with the Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merical
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:101085:84"/>Hopes of conquering the Dutchy of <hi>Milan,</hi> he makes him a Property to his Deſigns, which are the Neutrality in <hi>Italy.</hi> By that means the <hi>French</hi> King frees himſelf from a moſt burdenſome and expenſive War, which perplex'd him more than all the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies he keeps in <hi>Flanders</hi> and on the <hi>Rhine;</hi> and gives beſides a fatal Blow to the Union of the Confederate Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. This Event on one ſide raiſes the Honour and Hopes of the <hi>French</hi> King; and on the other makes the Duke of <hi>Savoy</hi>'s Conduct for ever odious to the Allies.</p>
            <p>There's no Queſtion but the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of <hi>France</hi> did give his Royal High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to underſtand, that the <hi>Milaneſe</hi> would infallibly fall a Prey to him; becauſe, ſaid they, there was little Probability of the Allies ever con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting to a Neutrality; and by this Decoy they have drawn in this cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulous Prince, while the Court of <hi>France</hi> was very well perſuaded that the Affairs would turn a contrary way. To put ſtill the Change upon him, and delude him the better, the <hi>French</hi> King promiſes him by the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:101085:85"/>Article, that after the Redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of that Dutchy, it ſhall be put into his Highneſs's Hands, by him to be enjoy'd for ever, without demand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any thing for the Expences of this Expedition; and his moſt Chriſtian Majeſty engages himſelf beſides to protect him in the peaceful Enjoyment of i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, againſt the Arms of the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When a Man ſeriouſly reflects upon all the ſine Promiſes of the <hi>French</hi> King, to engage his Royal Highneſs, he will not be much ſurpriz'd at the ſmall Precaution the Council of <hi>Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rin</hi> have us'd in ſo important an Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fair. To hear the <hi>French</hi> Miniſters ſpeak, 'twas but entring the <hi>Milaneſe</hi> to make an entire Conqueſt of it. They reckon upon it as a thing already done: and to dazzle his Royal High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>tter him with their Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection againſt the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> they promiſe to ſecure him in the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyment of it for ever; and over and above all this, their Generoſity goes ſo far, as to be at all the Changes of this Expedition, of which the <hi>French</hi> King makes a Preſent to his Royal Highneſs.</p>
            <pb n="157" facs="tcp:101085:85"/>
            <p>The <hi>French</hi> King was ever liberal of fallacious Promiſes. He might as well have promis'd to the Duke of <hi>Savoy</hi> the Conqueſt of all <hi>Italy,</hi> as he has done that of the <hi>Milaneſe.</hi> If his Royal Highneſs be ſo credulous as to depend upon his Word, he'll ſoon be Maſter of all the Princes beyond the <hi>Alps.</hi> But time will make it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear that nothing can be more Chime<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rical than thoſe Projects. This, as well as the preceding Articles, have been kept very ſecret by the Council of <hi>France;</hi> becauſe they have been look'd upon as the chief Springs to engage the Duke of of <hi>Savoy,</hi> by the Hopes of becoming the greateſt Prince of <hi>Italy.</hi> Ambition and a Deſire of en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larging ones Power was ever a natural Paſſion in all Sovereigns; and I doubt not but <hi>France</hi> has done more at the Court of <hi>Turin</hi> by this <hi>Artifice,</hi> than by all the other Stratagems he has there employ'd.</p>
            <p>Let's come to the VIIIth Article. The moſt Chriſtian King renounces for ever all the Rights and Pretenſions he and his Predeceſſors had to the Dukedom of <hi>Savoy,</hi> the Principality
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:101085:86"/>of <hi>Piedmont,</hi> and County of <hi>Nice.</hi> One can ſo little depend upon ſuch ſort of Renunciations, that the Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience of this Age has taught all the Princes of <hi>Europe,</hi> that the <hi>French</hi> King obſerves Treaties no longer than they ſerve his Intereſt: For if after the Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tification is ſign'd, his Conncil do but ſuggeſt to him a new way of extend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Power and Dominions, nothing is able to ſtop him. He then only conſults his Favourite-Policy, and knows no other Rule beſides his Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition, to which there's no preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing of juſt Bounds; becauſe he is ſtill too powerful. The ſtronger docs e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver give Laws to the weaker. And ſince the <hi>French</hi> King is not yet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due'd by the united Forces of the moſt powerful Princes in <hi>Europe,</hi> we muſt neceſſarily conclude, that he has not yet chung'd his Maxims.</p>
            <p>In the Year 1640, there was a Book printed at <hi>Madrid,</hi> and writ by a <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh</hi> Plenipotentiary, entituled, <hi>Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſos principales de la Monarchia de l' Eſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia el Anno</hi> 1639. wherein the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor, by a kind of Prophetical Spirit, ſaid, that the <hi>French</hi> King took the
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:101085:86"/>way to arrive at the Empire: That his Predeceſſors had ſhew'd it him by the taking of <hi>Mets, Toul</hi> and <hi>Verdun:</hi> That <hi>Lewis</hi> XIII. had follow'd them, by making himſelf Maſter of <hi>Alſatia</hi> and <hi>Lorrain:</hi> That if <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. could but take <hi>Thionville,</hi> he would ſeize up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Luxemberg,</hi> compleat the Conqueſt of the Dutchy of <hi>Burgundy,</hi> lay the <hi>Palatinate</hi> open and without Defence, and would make himſelf abſolute in all the Country of <hi>Treves,</hi> and all the ancient <hi>Auſtraſia.</hi> His Prophecy went ſtill further: He added, that by the Conqueſt of <hi>Thionville,</hi> that Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch would make the three Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Electors his Subjects: That <hi>Spain</hi> would loſe <hi>Flanders,</hi> the Empire and Cities of <hi>Germany</hi> their Liberty, and the <hi>German</hi> Princes their Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions.</p>
            <p>This Prophecy had certainly been accompliſh'd, had the Confederate Princes any longer delay'd to put a Stop to the Deſigns of the <hi>French</hi> King.</p>
            <p>However we may ſay, that 'tis by the Violation of Treaties that he has laid the Foundation of that over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grown
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:101085:87"/>Power, which one might juſtly call the <hi>Tyrant of Europe,</hi> and which has an abſolute Sway in almoſt all Courts.</p>
            <p>After ſo many living Examples, and repeated Experience of the ſmall Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit that can be given to the <hi>French</hi> King's Word, we may ſafely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, that his late Renunciation to the Dominions of his Royal Highneſs, will not be of long Continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance.</p>
            <p>The ninth Article whereby the <hi>French</hi> King engages and promiſes to aſſiſt the Duke of <hi>Savoy,</hi> in order to reduce the City of <hi>Geneva,</hi> was never made publick, through Reaſons of State and Policy; as well as ſeveral others which have ſecretly been agreed upon by the <hi>French</hi> King and the Duke of <hi>Savoy.</hi> Time will clear this great Myſtery. However it is certain that <hi>France</hi> for theſe many Years paſt has meditated the Ruin of that City. The Proteſtant Religion, which is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs'd there, is the chief Reaſon of theſe two Princes Hatred againſt it. Beſides, the good Succeſſes the <hi>French</hi> King has had in extinguiſhing the
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:101085:87"/>Reform'd Religion in <hi>France,</hi> give him the Hopes to bring it under his Subjection after a general Peace is concluded. This grand Deſign had by this time been accompliſh'd, had he not fear'd a Rupture with the <hi>Switzers,</hi> who have declar'd them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves Protectors of it. He has alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy but too many Enemies upon his Back; and therefore it is convenient for him to diſſemble and temporize till he has decided the Quarrels he has with the Allied Princes. In the mean time he has taken all the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary Meaſures for that Purpoſe, and the <hi>French</hi> Reſident at <hi>Geneva,</hi> is an ill <hi>Omen</hi> to the Safety and Liberty of that Republick, ſince he only lives there to know their weak and ſtrong Sides, and obſerve all that paſſes, which he preſently ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaints his Maſter withal.</p>
            <p>But when all is done, perhaps the <hi>French</hi> King promiſes more to the Duke, than he is able to perform. 'Tis not the firſt time he has been out in his Projects. The Face of Affairs does often change in a moment; and a ſmall Diſappointment may make
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:101085:88"/>his Deſigns miſcarry. But let us ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe that the <hi>French</hi> will make himſelf Maſter of <hi>Geneva;</hi> what Security can his Royal Highneſs have that he will put it into his Hands, and punctually perform all his Promiſes? I do not know any Body would take upon him that Guarranty. The <hi>French</hi> King's Honeſty in thoſe ſort of Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters is now become ſo ſlippery and ſuſpicious, that it is more likely he would keep that Conqueſt for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, than reſign it to the Duke. Let us therefore conclude, That this Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle is juſt as thoſe that went before, that is, imaginary and chimerical. The <hi>French</hi> King will never want for colourable Pretences to call back his Word, and keep his Promiſes to the Duke no farther than he has a mind to</p>
            <p>Thus having examin'd the Treaty of Peace concluded betwixt the <hi>French</hi> King and <hi>Victor Amedeus</hi> II. Duke of <hi>Savoy;</hi> let's now conſider the Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences of that Peace: And firſt let us begin with its ſolemn Publication at <hi>Paris,</hi> on the Tenth of <hi>September,</hi> 1696.</p>
            <pb n="163" facs="tcp:101085:88"/>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <p>BE it known to all, That a good, firm, ſtable, and ſolid Peace, with an en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire and ſincere Friendſhip and Reconcilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, has been made and agreed upon be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Moſt High, Moſt Excellent, and Moſt Mighty Prince <hi>LEWIS</hi> by the Grace of God, of <hi>FRANCE</hi> and <hi>NAVARRE</hi> King, our Sovereign Lord; and the Moſt High and Mighty Prince <hi>VICTOR AMEDEUS</hi> the Second, Duke of <hi>SAVOY;</hi> their Vaſſals, Subjects, and Servants, in all their Kingdoms, Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, Countries, Lands, and Lordſhips of their Obedience. That the ſaid Peace is general betwixt them and their ſaid Vaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſals and Subjects; and that, by vertue of the ſame, it is lawful for them to go and come, to return and ſojourn in all the Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the ſaid Kingdoms, Dominions, and Countries; to Trade and Merchandiſe, hold Correſpondence and Communication one with another, in all manner of Freedom and Security, as well by Land as by Sea, and on Rivers and other Waters, on this ſide and that ſide the Mountains, and in the ſame manner as it has and ought to have been done in time of good, ſincere, and amicable Peace, ſuch as it has pleaſed the
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:101085:89"/>Divine Goodneſs to grant unto the ſaid Lords, Kings, and Dukes of <hi>Savoy,</hi> their People and Subjects. Which to maintain and entertain, it is moſt expreſly forbidden to all Perſons, by what Quality or Title ſoever dignified or diſtinguiſh'd, to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take, attempt, or innovate any thing to it contrary or p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>judicial, upon pain of being ſeverely puniſh'd, as Infringers of Peace, and Diſturbers if the Publick Repoſe. Given at Oar Court at <hi>Verſailles</hi> the Eighth day of <hi>September, 1696.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Signed,</hi> LEWIS.</item>
                           <item> 
                              <hi>And a little lower,</hi> Phelypeaux, &amp;c.</item>
                        </list>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>This Peace, as you ſee, was pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh'd at <hi>Paris</hi> with all the Pomp and Solemnity that uſually attend thoſe great Events in which <hi>France</hi> has a more than ordinary Concern: And there's no doubt but ſhe has affected to ſhew an uncommon Magnificence in this, thereby to dazle the Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate Princes, and make the Succeſs of a Negotiation, which ſhe looks up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on as the Foundation of a General Peace, ſound high in all the Courts of <hi>Europe.</hi> The <hi>French</hi> King's Policy
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:101085:89"/>is good enough, as to that matter: He loſes nothing by crying up and proclaiming whatever he does and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertakes; but often draws a great deal of Good from a falſe Shew, and ſo turns both his good and bad Succeſſes to his own advantage. According to this Maxim, it is obſervable, That during this War, when he has loſt a Battel or a Town, or ſuffer'd any other Damage, he has caus'd Publick Rejoycings to be made, and order'd his Generals and Governours of Towns to diſcharge their Artillery, as if he had won a ſignal Victory over his Enemies. This Conduct, tho' a little unſincere, has brought great Advantages to him.</p>
            <p>Firſt, By that means he has dazzl'd his Subjects, and kept them in Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, by flattering them with ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginary Succeſſes; and has receiv'd from them, at the ſame time, all the neceſſary Subſidies to anſwer the vaſt Charges of a burdenſom War. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, He thereby has confirm'd the ſtaggering Fidelity of the Conquer'd Nations. In fine, He has rais'd the drooping Spirits of the Soldiers that
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:101085:90"/>fought under his Generals, and has, as we ſay, ſet a good Face on a bad Game: Witneſs the extravagant Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joicings made at <hi>Paris</hi> after the Battel of the <hi>Boyne,</hi> upon the falſe Report of the Death of the King of <hi>England,</hi> thoſe that were made after the loſs of a Fight at Sea, and generally in all the Rencounters where the <hi>French</hi> King's Arms were worſted. But we may freely ſay, That all the Parade and Oſtentation of the Court of <hi>France,</hi> upon the ſcore of the Peace of <hi>Italy,</hi> will be ſo far from making any Impreſſion upon the moſt Serene Allies, to engage them to agree the ſooner to a General Peace, that it will rather beget in them the Reſolution of carrying on the War more vigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly than ever. Their Intereſt has no relation with that of the Duke of <hi>Savoy;</hi> and if that Prince has been willing to undo himſelf, and ſacrifice his Dominions and Liberty out of a Frolick, the Confederate Princes will not make his Conduct the Standard of Theirs. They have taken up Arms to make a ſolid and laſting Peace, and will not lay them down upon any other Terms.</p>
            <pb n="167" facs="tcp:101085:90"/>
            <p>The general Publication of that Peace was follow'd by a Letter di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected to the Archbiſhop of <hi>Paris,</hi> in order to have <hi>Te Deum</hi> ſung as a Thankſgiving; wherein the <hi>French</hi> King gives us a true Idea of the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives upon which he has acted during this War. There the Language and Genius of the Court of <hi>France</hi> are expreſs'd in their genuine and natural Colours. That Piece being already made publick, we ſhall diſpenſe with inſerting it here; and tho' it deſerve to be examin'd at large, we will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent our ſelves with making ſome few particular Reflections upon it, and ſo conclude. The Court of <hi>France</hi> never publiſhes Pieces of that importance, before they are maturely ſtudied, and have paſt the Cenſure of his moſt able Miniſters. In a word, This is a Draught in Little of the vaſt Deſigns and moſt ſecret Thoughts of the <hi>French</hi> King.</p>
            <p>That Monarch begins with the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives that have induc'd him to take up Arms, which are to defend Religion and <hi>Vindicate the Injur'd Majeſty of KINGS.</hi> This Declaration is agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:101085:91"/>to that he made before, in all the <hi>Manifeſto's</hi> he publiſh'd before the Rupture. And therefore we may conclude, That the Council of <hi>France</hi> have long before ſtudied the Artifices they now employ to break the Union of the Confederate Princes. Thoſe Artifices are ſo much the more dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous, as they ſtrike at the moſt ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible Part of Civil Society, that is to ſay, <hi>Religion,</hi> and <hi>the Majeſty of Kings.</hi> As to the firſt, All Sovereign States are naturally very tender of the Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion they profeſs; the Catholick Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, of their Religion; and the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Princes, of theirs: But to hear the <hi>French</hi> King ſpeak, one would think him the Only Defender of the <hi>Roman</hi> Catholick Religion, and that the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour, the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> and the other Catholick Princes, whoſe Zeal is unqueſtionable, have abandon'd its Intereſt.</p>
            <p>If the <hi>French</hi> King ſhould ſpread abroad ſuch Diſcourſes in an unknown Country, remote from our Continent, and among a barbarous People, igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of the Tranſactions of <hi>Europe</hi> for theſe Fifty Years paſt, eſpecially ſince
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:101085:91"/>the Death of Cardinal <hi>Mazarin,</hi> 'tis certain he might impoſe upon their Credulity: But what can be more ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurd and extravagant, than to publiſh now all thoſe Impoſtures before the face of all <hi>Chriſtendom,</hi> to which he has been a Scourge and a Perſecutor? Witneſs the Quarrels he had with the Court of <hi>Rome,</hi> under the Pontificate of <hi>Innocent</hi> XI. If that Pious Pope had not oppos'd all the Extravagancies of the Court of <hi>France,</hi> were not we like to ſee the Church rent and torn by a more cruel and monſtrous Schiſm, than ever the Perſecutions of the moſt dreadful Heathen Tyrants have been? There's no need of renew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing here the Remembrance of thoſe Ills that have made all <hi>Chriſtendom</hi> to groan; they are too freſh to be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten: Let us be contented to ſay, That the <hi>French</hi> King is ſo unſincere upon that Point, that all the Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate Princes are fully convinc'd that <hi>Religion</hi> has the leaſt ſhare in his un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaking the preſent War. 'Tis well known alſo, that it is upon another Motive, that he has ſuppreſt the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd Religion in <hi>France.</hi> This laſt
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:101085:92"/>Step ought to be look'd upon as a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret Spring to make himſelf a ſurer Way to the Univerſal Monarchy; ſince we ſee he has in a manner done more miſchief to the Catholick than Proteſtant Princes. This is a dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Decoy, and a ſecret Warning to the Catholick Princes, who are in Confederacy with the Proteſtant, not to give ear to the Artifices of <hi>France,</hi> whoſe aim is to diſunite them, and, by that means, invade their Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Liberty.</p>
            <p>The Duke of <hi>Savoy,</hi> as we have ſeen of late, has begun to make a Breach in that Alliance: The Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of <hi>France,</hi> like deceitful <hi>Syrens,</hi> have drawn him into dangerous Snares, by their ſweet enchanting Voice. The fair and ſpecious Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of Religion has put all the Courts of <hi>Italy</hi> in motion, and by that means the <hi>French</hi> King was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concil'd to the Court of <hi>Rome,</hi> which was before his mortal Enemy. He could not have pitch'd upon a ſurer way to further his Deſigns, than by pretending, as he does at this time, that he acts out of a Zeal for Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion:
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:101085:92"/>By that means he caſts a Miſt before the Eyes of all the Catholick Princes; and inſinuates himſelf into all Courts. But what will become of the Dominions of ſo many Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reigns, if once divided from the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liance of the Proteſtant Princes? Since we now ſee that their Safety and mutual Preſervation wholly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends upon that Alliance. We ſtill repeat it here: Let not the Duke of <hi>Savoy</hi>'s Example ever ſhake this ſacred Union; for this is the only thing the <hi>French</hi> King aims at, and the Hinges upon which all his Deſigns turn. All Princes are for their Share in an Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fair that concerns every one in parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular, and all in general.</p>
            <p>The preſent War is not upon the account of Religion: 'Tis only <hi>France</hi> that ſays ſo, to impoſe upon the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federates, and diſunite them. 'Tis plain, the <hi>French</hi> King endeavours to perſwade the Catholick Princes, that the only Cauſe which has brought this War upon him, is the implacable Hatred of the Proteſtant Princes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, for perſecuting his Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Subjects; which is both falſe and
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:101085:93"/>ridiculous: For if the <hi>French</hi> King had deſign'd nothing but the pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Extirpation of <hi>Hereſie,</hi> never had the preſent War been kindled in <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope;</hi> becauſe the different Intereſts of the Proteſtant Princes were ſo far from uniting them in a Cauſe which was ſo juſt in it ſelf, that they rather ſeem'd to divide them ſtill the more.</p>
            <p>'Tis therefore to no purpoſe that the <hi>French</hi> King makes uſe of the Cloke of Religion, to cover a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce which every one knows to have no other than Temporal Motives; ſuch as are the Violation of all Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, the Uſurpation of his Neighbours Dominions, the Ruin of the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> the Protecting of the <hi>Turk,</hi> his Deſigns upon <hi>England,</hi> by ſupport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the late King <hi>James,</hi> his Attempts upon the Princes and States beyond the <hi>Alps,</hi> the Slavery of all <hi>Europe,</hi> and, in a word, the accompliſhing of his grand Maſter-piece, the <hi>Univerſal Monarchy.</hi> After ſo many cruel and treacherous Attempts, after ſo many Reaſons of Complaint given to the Confederates, and after the repeated Experiences they have had of the
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:101085:93"/>
               <hi>French</hi> King's Double-dealing and Foul-play, how can they now believe he is ſincere, when he tells us, That he had no other Aim than the Defence and Protection of Religion.</p>
            <p>Let's now paſs to the <hi>Majeſty of Kings,</hi> of which the <hi>French</hi> King de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares himſelf Defender and Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor. For theſe Nine Years paſt, ſays that Monarch, he maintains the War againſt a Conſpiracy of all <hi>Europe.</hi> Upon what account? To defend Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and <hi>Vindicate the Majeſty of Kings:</hi> Nothing can be more Great, more Glorious, and more Noble, than ſuch a Deſign. That Monarch em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploys all his Forces, exhauſts his Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, and ſacrifices his People and Subjects, and all this <hi>to vindicate the Majeſty of Kings.</hi> We muſt confeſs the <hi>French</hi> King's Zeal to be very great, his Projects magnanimous and pious, in a word; worthy of the Firſt Monarch of <hi>Chriſtendom.</hi> King <hi>James</hi> is to be accounted Happy for being under the Protection of <hi>France,</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided this Protection be Sincere, and the <hi>French</hi> King do not play foul upon this Occaſion, as he has done hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:101085:94"/>in ſeveral Quarrels betwixt Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Princes. He has often been ſeen to eſpouſe the Intereſt of the one, by forſaking the Party of the other for whom he had declar'd himſelf, and do ſuch Work as has ruin'd both in the Concluſion.</p>
            <p>So that in all Quarrels he alone has got ſomething by them: He never keeps ſuch a ſtir, and takes ſo much pains for nothing; and whenever he does any great Service, 'tis always up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on condition, that the private Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages he ſhall draw from it, will be proportionable to his Labour. Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to this Principle, if the <hi>French</hi> King could make a Peace with the Allies upon ſuch eaſie Terms as he deſires, the <hi>Majeſty of Kings,</hi> which he pretends to vindicate, would ſoon be forgotten; I had almoſt ſaid, ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crific'd; for, what will he not do, when his Intereſt lies at ſtake? No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing can be more ſingular than the Zeal and Ardour the <hi>French</hi> King pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends for King <hi>James</hi>'s Intereſt: All the World are inform'd, how the pernicious Counſels of <hi>France</hi> have been the Cauſe of the Misfortunes
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:101085:94"/>and Fall of that Prince. 'Tis <hi>France</hi> that has rais'd him to the Throne, by ſecret and underhand Practices, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known to moſt People to this very day; and it may be ſaid, That <hi>France</hi> has made him loſe his Crown, by put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting him upon ſuch violent Methods as have render'd him odious to his Subjects, whoſe Ruin he had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triv'd, if God Almighty had not ſnatch'd them from the impending Danger by a miraculous Revolution. The <hi>French</hi> King's Zeal and Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity deſerve to be commended: He endeavours to reſtore a Prince he has been the Ruin of, and this he calls, <hi>Vindicating the Majeſty of Kings;</hi> for which he ſacrifices the Majeſty of all other Monarchs in <hi>Chriſtendom.</hi> Who can be ſo credulous, as to think his Conduct ſincere upon this Occaſion? And is it poſſible the <hi>French</hi> King can ſtrain thoſe fine Sentiments of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſeration for an unfortunate Prince, ſo high, as not to ſcruple to declare War againſt all <hi>Europe,</hi> to vindicate that pretended <hi>Majeſty of Kings?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We may rather ſay, that he has quite another thing in Proſpect, and that
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:101085:95"/>he only uſes <hi>the Majeſty of Kings</hi> as a Pretence to colour a bad Cauſe, fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther his grand Deſigns, weaken the Confederacy by the Ruine of the For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the Crown of <hi>England,</hi> and weary the Allies by the Tediouſneſs of the War; ſtill keeping his old Max<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ims and Inclinations, which would ſoon revive more fierce than ever, if he could clap up a bad Peace with the Confederate Princes. Thoſe are the true Motives that prevail with the <hi>French</hi> King to vindicate the pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Majeſty of Kings,</hi> which he makes ſound ſo high in all the Courts of <hi>Chriſtendom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>'Tis upon that Account that he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>files himſelf with all manner of Crimes. Wicked Attempts, Plots, Treacheries and Murders, are nothing to him.</p>
            <p>If by this means the <hi>French</hi> King pretends <hi>to vindicate the Majeſty of Kings,</hi> he muſt own his Cauſe to be very bad; and that the Upſhot of all the Honour that will accrue to him upon this ſcore, will be no more than a monſtrous Parallel of what has been practiſed by thoſe Heathen Princes that have been the Execration
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:101085:95"/>of their Age. This Conduct ought to make all <hi>Chriſtendom</hi> to tremble, ſince the Court of <hi>France</hi> is ſo far from diſowning it, that they rather ſeem to authorize it openly by the vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lanous Aſſaſſins they ſend over to <hi>England.</hi> If this be the way whereby the <hi>French.</hi> King endeavours to arrive at a general Peace, we muſt confeſs that it will coſt dear to all <hi>Europe,</hi> and that all Honeſty is baniſh'd from the World.</p>
            <p>The <hi>French</hi> King having acquainted the World with the Motives that made him undertake the preſent War, exalts the Progreſſes wherewith God Almighty has bleſs'd his Deſigns and proſper'd his Enterprizes. To hear him ſpeak, his Arms have always been triumphant and victorious; and all the Advantages the Allies have had during this war, are to be counted for no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, and <hi>France</hi> alone has all the Honour of it. We do not wonder at this Haughtineſs: We know well e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough this is the Language of the Court of <hi>France.</hi> That Crown is ſo uſed to thoſe Expreſſions, that unleſs ſhe be entirely pull'd down, and ſtrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:101085:96"/>of her beſt Poſſeſſions, ſhe never will own her Loſſes; and perhaps then too ſhe will ſtill keep up her Pride. Glory muſt at any rate go be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all her Enterprizes. The <hi>French</hi> Nation alone knows now-a-days how to command and make war, and all other Nations are ignorant and fit for nothing but to obey her proud Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation.</p>
            <p>Yet for all this, the Confederates carried the very firſt Campagn three important Fortreſſes on the <hi>Rhine.</hi> Theſe Conqueſts were follow'd by a Victory won at <hi>Wallcour,</hi> by the Defeat of the beſt of <hi>French</hi> Kings Troops. Altho' this Fight was not general, the Advantages the Allies had in it gain'd them as much Honour as ever the <hi>French</hi> got in the Battels they won under the Conduct of the Mareſchal of <hi>Luxemburg;</hi> And during this Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagn the Confederate Arms were triumphant wherever<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> they fought. The Irruption into <hi>Dauphine,</hi> under the Conduct of the Duke of <hi>Savoy,</hi> and the Sea-Fight that was fought betwixt the <hi>French</hi> and Confederate Fleet, do alſo deſerve to be reckon'd
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:101085:96"/>among the Advantages got by the Confederates. The Siege of <hi>Namur,</hi> where <hi>France</hi> had the Shame to ſee the Triumph of the Arms of the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, is too memorable to be paſs'd over in Silence. This only Conqueſt eclip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes all the Victories of wich the <hi>French</hi> King now brags with ſo much Pride, ſince his united Forces were not able to prevent it; and that in ſpite of the Preſence of a Mareſchal of <hi>France,</hi> who got into the Place, ſupported by an Army within, and another with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out, as numerous as ever <hi>France</hi> had: Since, I ſay, all theſe Precautions have had no other Effect than to ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten the taking of that Fortreſs, and heighten the Honour of the Allies: If after all theſe Advantages, the <hi>French</hi> King gives it out, that he always was ſuperiour, it muſt be confeſs'd, that he makes Fools of all the Nations of <hi>Europe</hi> who have been Spectators of 'em; and affronts beſides the Honour of ſo many generous and brave Princes who have ſignaliz'd themſelves in 'em. <hi>All thoſe prosperous Succeſſes that have waited on my Arms,</hi> ſays the <hi>French</hi> King, <hi>have been the more grateful to
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:101085:97"/>me, as that I flatter'd my ſelf they might conduce to a Peace.</hi> The Allies do freely own, that <hi>France</hi> has been proſperous in her Undertakings; but they hope alſo that they have a Right to have the Advantages they got over that Crown taken notice of; and they cannot hear without a juſt Reſentment thoſe Diſcourſes which the <hi>French</hi> pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh to the World, to rob them of the Honour they have gain'd in this War at the Expence of their Blood, and Loſs of their beſt Subjects and braveſt Generals. All theſe Considerations ought to engage the Council of <hi>France</hi> to ſpeak another Language. Altho' the Duke of <hi>Savoy</hi> have deſerted 'em, their Union will not be the leſs in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>violable for it; and <hi>France</hi> has no great reaſon to boaſt ſo much of her Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periority. A croſs Accident is able to make her loſe all the Advantages ſhe pretends to draw from the Peace of <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taly:</hi> Therefore ſhe ought to have more Regard for the Allies than ſhe has hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto expreſs'd; and by a juſt Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſcenſion prevent the dubious For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune of War, and haſten the Conclusion of an honourable and laſting Peace.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:101085:97"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
